<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:hfe.a15a</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>HEAT FLOW EXPERIMENT for A15A</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a15a::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo 15 Preliminary Science Report, NASA SP-289, 546 pages, published by
                   NASA, Washington, D.C., 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLO15A1972</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo Scientific Experiments Data Handbook, NASA Technical Memorandum X-58131,
                   JSC-09166, published by NASA Johnson Space Center, Houston, Texas, Aug. 1974.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLOSEDH1974</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Keihm, S.J., and M.G. Langseth, Jr., Surface brightness temperatures at the
                   Apollo 17 heat flow site: Thermal conductivity of the upper 15 cm of regolith,
                   Proceedings of the Lunar Science Conference, 4th, Volume 3, pages 2503-2513,
                   1973.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KEIHM-LANGSETH1973</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Keihm, S.J., J.L. Chute, K. Peters, and M.G. Langseth, Apollo 15 measurement of
                   lunar surface brightness temperatures - thermal conductivity of the upper 1 1/2
                   meters of regolith, Earth Planetary Science Letters, 19, No. 3, pages 337-351,
                   July 1973.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KEIHMETAL1973</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Langseth, M.G., Jr., Lunar Heat-Flow Experiment: Final Technical Report: 6 Jun.
                   1966 - 30 Jun. 1975, NASA-CR-151619, CU-4-77, 289p, Lamont-Doherty Geological
                   Observatory of Columbia University, Palisades, New York, 1977.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.LANGSETH1977</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Langseth, M.G., Jr., S.P. Clark Jr., J.L. Chute, Jr., S.J. Keihm, and A.E.
                   Wechsler, The Apollo 15 Lunar Heat-Flow Measurement, In The Moon, Volume 4,
                   Issue 3-4, pages 390-410, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.LANGSETHETAL1972A</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Langseth, M.G., Jr., S.J. Keihm, J.L. Chute, Jr., and A.E. Wechsler, Heat flow
                   experiment, In Apollo 15 Preliminary Science Report, Section 11, NASA SP-289,
                   published by NASA, Washington, D.C., 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.LANGSETHETAL1972B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Langseth, M.G., Jr., S.J. Keihm, and J.L. Chute, Jr., Heat flow experiment, In
                   Apollo 17 Preliminary Science Report, Section 9, NASA SP-330, published by
                   NASA, Washington, D.C., 1973.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.LANGSETHETAL1973</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Langseth, M.G., Jr., S.J. Keihm, and K. Peters, Revised lunar heat-flow values,
                   Proceedings of the Lunar Science Conference, 7th, Volume 3, pages 3143-3171,
                   1976.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.LANGSETHETAL1976</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Nagihara, M.G., Y. Saito, and P.T. Taylor, Reexamination Of the Apollo 15 Heat
                   Flow Data Toward Understanding Potential Causes Of The Long-Term Subsurface
                   Warming Observed, In: Abstracts of Papers Submitted to the 41th Lunar and
                   Planetary Science Conference, Volume 41, Abstract 1353, 2010.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.NAGIHARAETAL2010</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>HEAT FLOW EXPERIMENT</name>
        <type>Regolith Properties</type> <!--RChen/EN was Geothermal Heat Flow Probe. No obvious choice. "METEOROLGY PACKAGE" in JSH's xl file-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    The Heat Flow Experiment (HFE), part of the Apollo Lunar Surface
    Experiment Package (ALSEP), was designed to determine the rate of heat
    loss from the lunar interior by temperature and thermal property
    measurements at and below the surface. The experiment was carried on
    the Apollo 15, 16, and 17 missions and was essentially identical on all
    three missions.  (The experiment was attempted during Apollo 16 but
    failed due to a broken cable connection.) The experiment apparatus
    consisted of two probes connected by 8 meter long cables to an
    electronics box which was in turn connected by a flat ribbon cable to
    the ALSEP station. The astronauts would drill two holes with the Apollo
    Lunar Surface Drill (ALSD). The ALSD was equipped with borestem caps
    and retainers, borestems, bore bits, a bore bit/drill adapter, a
    treadle, and a bore stem/core stem wrench. The borestem assemblies used
    in drilling consisted of lengths of hollow fiberglass tubes, 2.5 cm in
    diameter, which would be connected together as the drilling progressed,
    and remained in the holes to provide a casing to prevent collapse of
    the hole walls during insertion of the probes. Nominally the holes were
    to be drilled to a depth of 3 meters but in practice no holes reached
    this depth. The probe would be lowered down into the borestem until it
    came to rest on top of the drill bit at the bottom of the hole. The
    borestem tube would project out of the surface a distance dependent on
    the depth of the hole.
 
 
    Heat Flow Probes
    ----------------
      Each heat flow probe was constructed of two rigid cylinders connected
      by a flexible joint. Each cylinder was 50 cm in length and held four
      platinum resistance elements which were electrically connected in
      pairs to form two accurate (+/-0.001 K) differential thermometers.
      The first pair of elements were located with one element near the top
      and one near the bottom of the cylinder, 47 cm apart from each other,
      and were connected in a bridge circuit. These sensors were designated
      the gradient bridge (DTG). The other two sensors were located 9 cm
      below the top DTG sensor and 9 cm above the bottom DTG sensor, 29 cm
      apart from each other connected by a bridge circuit. This pair was
      designated the ring bridge (DTR).
 
      A thermocouple (the probe thermocouple) was mounted near the top of
      the upper cylinder, colocated with the top gradient sensor. Attached
      to the top of the upper cylinder was a long flexible cable which
      connected the probe to the electronics box.  The cable contained 3
      more thermocouples spaced 65 cm, 115 cm, and 165 cm from the probe
      thermocouple. The thermocouples were spaced so that at least some of
      them were outside the borehole on the lunar surface.
 
      1000-ohm Karma-wire platinum resistor heaters surrounded each of the
      four gradient bridge sensor housings on each probe. These were used
      for conductivity experiments and could be energized at either 0.002 W
      (low conductivity mode) or 0.5 W (high conductivity mode). The
      heaters would be turned on for approximately 36 hours for the low
      conductivity experiments and 6 hours in high conductivity mode.
 
      The probes return absolute temperature data, differential temperature
      data (across the bridges), low- and high-thermal conductivity data,
      and thermocouple temperature data. Specifically, the experiment
      measured lunar temperatures of the following types, with
      corresponding accuracies noted in parentheses -- gradient bridge
      high-sensitivity temperature difference  measurements (0.001 K)
      low-sensitivity temperature difference measurements (0.01 K), and
      absolute temperature measurements (0.05 K) over the temperature range
      190 - 270 K; ring bridge temperature difference measurements (0.002
      K) and absolute temperatures (0.05 K) over the range 190 - 270 K;
      thermocouple temperatures (0.07 K) over 70 - 400 K; and the reference
      bridge temperature (0.01 K) over 23 - 363 K.
 
      The electronics box contained two multiplexers and amplifiers, dc/dc
      converter, and an isothermal block which contained a reference
      thermocouple and reference bridge.  The electronics box was nominally
      kept at 278 to 328 K using heating elements, power control
      thermostats, a layered aluminized mylar insulation bag. fiberglass
      case, radiator plate, and sunshield.  The instrument was powered by
      29 volt d.c. from the central station.
 
 
    Sensor Naming Convention
    ------------------------
      The sensors were designated with a 6 character code, three letters
      followed by two numbers and one letter.  The first of the two numbers
      designates the probe number. The sensors on probe 1 were individually
      designated as follows;  for the upper cylinder the second number is
      &apos;1&apos;, the upper gradient bridge sensor was DTG11A and the lower sensor
      was DTG11B; the upper ring bridge sensor was DTR11A and the lower
      DTR11B. For the lower cylinder the second number was &apos;2&apos;, the upper
      gradient bridge sensor was DTG12A, the lower DTG12B, and the upper
      ring bridge sensor was DTR12A, the lower DTR12B.  The bridge sensor
      pairs were designated DTG11, DTR11, DTG12, and DTR12. The sensors on
      probe 2 had the same format except that the first number in each
      designation was replaced with a &apos;2&apos;, so the upper cylinder, upper
      gradient bridge sensor was DTG21A. Two numbering conventions exist in
      the literature for the thermocouples.  We are using the convention
      that TC14 designates the thermocouple at the top of probe 1, TC13 is
      the cable thermocouple closest to probe 1, followed by TC12 and TC11.
      Probe 2 would have TC24, etc. (Another convention, seen in the
      Preliminary Science Reports, has the probe thermocouple designated as
      TC11, followed successively in the cable by TC14, TC13, and TC12.)
 
 
    Instrument Operation
    --------------------
      In normal operating mode a 7.25 minute measurement sequence is used
      to collect the ambient high- and low-sensitivity differential data
      from the gradient sensors and the thermocouple outputs. The same
      measurement sequence would be used when the heaters were commanded on
      for the low conductivity (0.002 W) mode, with the heaters activated
      in turn for typically 36 hours.  For the high-conductivity (0.5 W)
      sequence, the ring bridge sensors were used and were read every 54
      seconds. This mode nominally would last 8 hours.  This mode could
      also be done without the heaters on, with measurements simply being
      made by the ring bridge sensors.  This mode, known as a ring bridge
      survey, would be used approximately every 6 hours at first and less
      frequently later in the experiment.  The measurement time intervals
      for a given sensor would vary over the course of its operation,
      such that the time sequences in resulting data do not necessarily
      follow a linear pattern.
 
 
    Apollo 15 Operational History
    -----------------------------
      The Apollo 15 heat flow electronics box was set up 9 meters north of
      the central station, with the hole for probe 1 drilled 4 meters east
      of the box and the hole for probe 2 drilled 4.5 meters west of the
      box. Difficulty was encountered in drilling both holes due to the
      resistant nature of the subsurface regolith.  The probe 1 borestem
      only penetrated to 162 cm and the probe 2 borestem to 160 cm.
      Additionally, an obstruction was encountered when emplacing probe 2,
      possibly a break in the borestem, at a depth of about 1 meter,
      leaving the top of the upper section of probe 2 above the surface and
      rendering the readings from this section unusable for heat flow
      studies.  For probe 1, the sensors were at the following depths:
      DTG12B - 138 cm; DTR12B - 129 cm; DTR12A - 100 cm; DTG12A - 91 cm;
      DTG11B - 83 cm; DTR11B - 74 cm; DTR11A - 45 cm; DTG11A - 36 cm.  All
      three cable thermocouples were above the ground, TC13 was in the
      borestem projecting above the surface.  For probe 2, the sensors were
      at depths: DTG22B - 96 cm; DTR22B - 87 cm; DTR22A - 58 cm; DTG22A -
      49 cm; DTG21B - 41 cm; DTR21B - 32 cm; DTR21A - 3 cm; DTG21A -
      approximately 6 cm above the surface.  All three cable thermocouples
      were above ground and out of the borestem.
 
      Probe 1 was placed in the hole on 31 July 1971 at approximately 18:47
      UT. The instrument was turned on at 19:28 UT on 31 July and the first
      reading from probe 1 came at 19:47:59. (The turn on time is according
      to the operational history in the Apollo Scientific Experiments Data
      Handbook.  The time is actually listed as &apos;19.47 hours&apos; which could
      be an error, possibly meaning 19:47). Because of the troubles with
      the obstruction in the probe 2 hole, probe 2 was not placed
      permanently in the hole until the end of the second EVA on 1 August
      at approximately 17:17 UT.  Since the experiment was turned on the
      previous day readings from probe 2 were coming in before it was
      emplaced in the hole. In December 1975 the experiment began returning
      anomalous data and only operated intermittently starting on 28 April
      1976. The experiment was commanded off from Earth on 15 January 1977.
 
 
    Heater schedule
    ---------------
      The heaters were turned on and off in the low power (0.002 W) mode in
      1971 as follows, with the heater designation followed in parentheses
      by the depth of the heater, the date and time the heater was turned
      on, and the date and time the heater was turned off, in UT. For probe
      1: H11 (36 cm, 30 Aug. 17:00 - 31 Aug. 17:00), H12 (83 cm, 4 Sep.
      05:04 - 5 Sep. 16:55), H13 (91 cm, 26 Aug. 04:58 - 27 Aug. 16:57),
      H14 (138 cm, 2 Sep. 05:01 - 3 Sep. 16:55). For probe 2 only the
      bottom two heaters were used:  H23 (49 cm, 24 Aug. 05:00 - 25 Aug.
      17:01), H24 (96 cm, 7 Sep. 05:00 - 8 Sep. 17:00).  In 1973 probe 1
      heaters H11 and H12 were rerun in low power mode because they were
      strongly affected by diurnal variations.  These times were chosen to
      minimize the effects of transient variations near the surface: H11
      (36 cm, 13 Mar. 15:01 - 15 Mar. 15:00), H12 (83 cm, 14 Feb. 14:42 -
      16 Feb. 02:26).
 
 
    For more information about the Apollo 15 Heat Flow Experiment, see
    the Apollo 15 Preliminary Science Report [APOLLO15A1972], the
    Apollo Scientific Experiments Data Handbook [APOLLOSEDH1974], the
    Apollo 15 Lunar Heat-Flow Measurement Report by Langseth, et al.
    (1972) [LANGSETHETAL1972A], the Apollo 15 Heat Flow Experiment
    Report by Langseth, et al. (1972) [LANGSETHETAL1972B], &apos;Revised
    Lunar Heat-flow Values&apos; by Langseth, et al. (1976) [LANGSETHETAL1976],
    &apos;Lunar Heat-Flow Experiment: Final Technical Report&apos; by Langseth
    (1977) [LANGSETH1977], &apos;Apollo 15 Measurement of Lunar Surface
    Brightness Temperatures - Thermal Conductivity of the upper 1 1/2
    meters of Regolith&apos; by Keihm, et al. (1973) [KEIHMETAL1973], and
    &apos;Reexamination Of the Apollo 15 Heat Flow Data Toward Understanding
    Potential Causes Of The Long-Term Subsurface Warming Observed&apos; by
    Nagihara, et al. (2010) [NAGIHARAETAL2010].
 
    Related publications include the Apollo 17 Heat Flow Experiment
    Report by Langseth, et al. (1973) [LANGSETHETAL1973] and &apos;Surface
    Brightness Temperatures at the Apollo 17 Heat Flow Site&apos; by Keihm
    and Langseth (1973) [KEIHM&amp;LANGSETH1973].
 
 
    This instrument description was provided by the NASA National Space
    Science Data Center.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
