<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mimi.co</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MAGNETOSPHERIC IMAGING INSTRUMENT for CO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.co::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Krimigis, S.M., D.G. Mitchell, D.C. Hamilton, S. Livi, J. Dandouras, S.
                   Jaskulek, T.P. Armstrong, J.D. Boldt, A.F. Cheng, G. Gloeckler, J.R. Hayes,
                   K.C. Hsieh, W.-H. Ip, E.P. Keath, E. Kirsch, N. Krupp, L.J. Lanzerotti, R.
                   Lundgren, B.H. Mauk, R.W. McEntire, E.C. Roelof, C.E. Schlemm, B.E. Tossman, B.
                   Wilken, and D.J. Williams, Magnetosphere Imaging Instrument (MIMI) on the
                   Cassini Mission to Saturn/Titan, Space Sci Rev. 114, 233-329, 2004.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KRIMIGISETAL2004</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Kusterer, M.B., L.M. Burke, Level 1A File Layouts, Cassini/MIMI Data Analysis
                   Center Level 1A File Layouts, The Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics
                   Laboratory Document, Revision 18, December 2003.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KUSTERER-BURKE2003</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Manweiler, J.W., W.A. Rasmuss, and S. Joy, MIMI Standard Data Products and
                   Archive Volume Software Interface Specification, v2.1, JPL Document D-31634,
                   Cassini document IO-AR-006, 2005.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MANWEILERETAL2005</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MAGNETOSPHERIC IMAGING INSTRUMENT</name>
        <type>Particle Detector</type> <!--RChen/EN was Energetic Particle Detector-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Abstract:
  =========
 
    The Cassini Magnetospheric Imaging Instrument (MIMI)
    consists of three separate sensors: the Charge Energy Mass
    Spectrometer (CHEMS) sensor, the Low Energy Magnetospheric
    Measurement (LEMMS) sensor, and the Ion Neutral Camera (INCA)
. This combination of sensors provides the capability
    to perform both global imaging and in situ measurements to study
    the overall configuration and dynamics of Saturn&apos;s magnetosphere
    and its interactions with the solar wind, Saturn&apos;s atmosphere,
    Titan, the icy satellites and the ring particles.
 
    The text of this instrument description has been abstracted from the
    instrument paper [KRIMIGISETAL2004]:
 
      Krimigis, S.M., Magnetosphere Imaging Instrument (MIMI) on the
      Cassini Mission to Saturn/Titan, in Space Science Reviews, Springer
      Science and Business Media, B.V., formerly Kluwer Academic
      Publishers B.V., Vol. 114, No. 1-4, pp. 233-329, December 2004.
 
 
  Scientific Objectives:
  ======================
 
    The MIMI instrument onboard the Cassini Orbiter has the following
    primary goals at Saturn:
    1.  Determine the global configuration and dynamics of hot plasma
        in the magnetosphere of Saturn through imaging and in situ
        measurements.
    2.  Study the sources of plasma and energetic ions through in situ
        measurements of energetic ion composition, spectra, charge
        state, and angular distributions.
    3.  Study magnetospheric substorm-like activity at Saturn.
    4.  Determine through imaging the formation of clouds of neutral
        hydrogen, nitrogen, and water products.
    5.  Investigate the modification of satellite surfaces and
        atmospheres through plasma and radiation bombardment.
    6.  Study Titan&apos;s cometary interaction with Saturn&apos;s magnetosphere
        via high resolution imaging and in situ measurements.
    7.  Measure the high energy (E_elec &gt; 1 MeV, E_p &gt; 15 MeV) particle
        component in the inner (L &lt; 5 Rs) magnetosphere to assess
        CRAND source characteristics.
    8.  Study magnetosphere-ionosphere coupling through remote sensing
        of aurora and in situ measurements of precipitating energetic
        ions and electrons.
 
  Calibration:
  ============
 
    Calibration processes are accomplished via both flight software
    and ground processing software.  Flight software is used primarily
    to accommodate variations in measurements due to spacecraft motion.
    Ground based calibration is accomplished through a combination of
    calibration data values (see COMIMI_0000) coupled with various
    algorithms to generate particle flux from measured count rates.
 
 
  Operational Modes:
  ===========================
    The INCA detector has the capability to be placed in either ion mode
    or neutral mode.  Ion mode indicates that the potential of the
    deflection plates is set to zero so that ions are also counted along
    with neutrals.  Neutral mode identifies that there is a potential
    applied to the plates that will cause the ions to deflect away from
    the entrance aperture and not be counted.  The efficiency of this
    process is strongly dependent upon the applied plate potential.  The
    applied plate potential is a configurable parameter within the system
    and is based upon the science goals, dust environment, and the
    expected plasma and high energy particle distributions. There are no
    other specific operational modes of the detectors.
 
  Operational Considerations:
  ===========================
 
    The MIMI power consumption is nomially ~19.0 W.  Typical operations
    include the capability to sense 6-7 orders of magnitude in particle
    flux over a dynamic energy range for electrons of 30 KeV to 5 MeV and
    for ions from 3 KeV to 160 MeV. Data quality is affected by direct sun
    exposure into the instruments and INCA operations are tailored to
    reduce the possibility of direct dust particle impacts into the sensor
    aperture during ring crossings.
 
 
  Sensors:
  ==========
 
    The MIMI experiment consists of three independent sensors: Charge
    Energy Mass Spectrometer (CHEMS), Ion Neutral Camera (INCA), and Low
    Energy Magnetospheric Measurements (LEMMS).  Each sensor has specific
    targeted energies and populations to be examined and collectively
    provide the ability to fully characterize the energetic charged and
    neutral particle population in the Saturnian Magnetosphere as well as
    the Solar Wind, the Jovian Magnetosphere, and the Earth Magnetosphere.
 
    Each sensor is a combination of geometric components, silicon
    detectors, micrpchannel plates, and electronics/software components
    that give them the ability to fully answer the missions scientific
    objectives. When the spacecraft is spinning the MIMI sensors obtain
    measurements over a full four pi steradians.  The different MIMI
    sensors share common electronics and provide complimentary
    measurements of energetic plasma distributions, composition, and
    energy spectrum, and the interaction of that plasma with the extended
    atmosphere and moons of Saturn.
 
    The CHEMS sensor is mounted on the particles and fields instrument
    pallet with a field of view of approximately 160 degrees in latitude
    (bisected by the spacecraft x-y plane) by 4 degrees in azimuth
    centered on the spacecraft -x axis. CHEMS measures ions from
    approximately 3 to 220 KeV/e.
 
    The INCA sensor is separately mounted and nearly co-aligned with the
    remote sensing instruments, with a field of view of 120 degrees in
    latitude and 90 degrees in azimuth, centered on a vector rotated 9.5
    degrees toward the spacecraft +x axis from the -y axis. INCA makes two
    different types of measurements.  It obtains the directional
    distribution, energy spectra, and crude composition of magnetospheric
    ions between 7 keV/nuc and 500 keV/nuc and it makes remote images of
    the global distribution of the energetic neutral emission of hot
    plasmas in the Saturnian magnetosphere, measuring the composition and
    energy spectra of those energetic neutrals for each image pixel.
 
    The LEMMS sensor is double ended, with oppositely directed 15 degree
    and 30 degree (full angle) conical fields of view (FOV).  LEMMS is
    mounted on a rotation platform, with the spin axis parallel with the
    spacecraft y axis, such that when rotating, the LEMMS telescopes sweep
    through 360 degrees in the spacecraft x-z plane.  The LEMMS spin
    mechanism failed on February 1, 2005.
 
 
    Frames diagram
    --------------
 
    All MIMI telescope directions are described in terms of the
    spacecraft fixed frame.
    LEMMS telescopes rotate around the -y axis (in the x-z plane) with
    the 15 degree (low energy) telescope at zero degrees when it is
    pointing in the -z direction and hence the 30 degree telescope (high
    energy) telescope is pointing along the +z axis.
    CHEMS latitudinal field of view of 160 degrees is bisected by the
    spacecraft x-y plane and its azimuthal field of view of 4 degrees
    is centered on the spacecraft -x axis.
    INCA is separately mounted and nearly co-aligned with the remote
    sensing instruments with a latitudinal field of view of 120 degrees
    and an azimuthal field of view of 90 degrees centered on a vector
    rotated 9.5 degrees toward the spacecraft +x axis from the -y axis.
 
    There are no otherwise specifically defined Cassini MIMI frames.
 
  Electronics:
  ============
 
    Signals from the sensors are first processed by the analog
    electronics and then by the digital processing unit (DPU). Analog
    data are placed into the digital system and with respect to CHEMS
    and LEMMS minimal processing is done.  With respect to INCA the
    data is shifted into appropriate bins based upon the current
    spacecraft orientation and spin rates.
    All channel definitions are predefined by the electronics for
    the LEMMS sensors and the CHEMS sensor has a variable high voltage
    potential to determine selection of particle based upon energy
    and to then subsequently place particles into energy, mass, and/or
    mass/charge bins. The INCA instrument has the ability through the
    use of high voltage potentials applied to the aperture plates to
    deflect ions away from the entrance slit and instead image
    neutral particles.  When the high voltage supply is turned off
    then the instrument see both neutrals and ions.
 
    The DPU unit&apos;s primary function is to catalog incoming particle
    measurements based upon underlying logic and to count events in
    accumulation bins.  The DPU also packages the data along with the
    instrument housekeeping data (instrument states) and then integrated
    into telemetry for broadcast to ground station.
    Parameters that control the high voltage supplies, the selection
    of priority counters etc, are expected to be updated periodically
    under normal operating conditions.
 
    Data compression and sampling techniques are used to maximize data
    return within the bandwidth allocated to the experiment.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
