<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
        xmlns:pds ="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" 
        xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
        xmlns:xsi ="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:schemaLocation=
        "http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1    https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd
        http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1   https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rss.co</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>2.0</version_id>
        <title>Radio Science Subsystem for Cassini Orbiter</title>
        <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        
        <Modification_History>
            
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-02-15</modification_date>
                <version_id>2.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Updated for Cassini Orbiter raw radio science data migration to PDS4.
                    Separated ground elements into a separate set of context products; this
                    context product describes only the spacecraft instrumentation.  Corrected
                    instrument type to be 'Radio Science'.  Reformatted for easier reading.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            
        </Modification_History>
        
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        
       <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.co</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
       </Internal_Reference>
        
       <Internal_Reference>
           <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.dsn</lid_reference>
           <reference_type>instrument_to_facility</reference_type>
           <comment>
               A description of the ground portion of the radio science instrument.
           </comment>
       </Internal_Reference>
        
       <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:radiosci.documentation:dsn.810-005</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>context_to_associate</reference_type>
            <comment>
                DSN document 810-005 is the Telecommunication Link Design Handbook for the
                NASA Deep Space Network.  It contains design data for flight projects using the
                NASA DSN. The document is modular, and modules are updated as appropriate.  
                This reference is to a PDS4 collection; products within the collection are 
                versions of the Handbook, released at various times.  Modules include:
                001 Handbook Introduction
                  101 70-m Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces
                  102 26-m Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces (omitted in 2009 and later versions)
                  103 34-m HEF Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces
                  104 34-m BWG Antennas Telecommunications Interfaces
                  105 Atmospheric and Environmental Effects
                  106 Solar Corona and Solar Wind Effects
                  107 Radio Source Catalog
                  201 Frequency and Channel Assignments
                  202 34-m and 70-m Doppler
                  203 Sequential Ranging
                  205 Command Service
                  206 Telemetry General Information
                  207 34-m and 70-m Telemetry Reception
                  208 Telemetry Data Decoding
                  209 Open-Loop Radio Science
                  210 Delta Differential One-way Ranging
                  211 Wideband Very Long Baseline Interferometry
                  214 Pseudonoise and Regenerative Ranging
                  301 Coverage and Geometry (includes antenna coordinates)
                  302 Antenna Positioning
                  303 Media Calibration
                  304 Frequency and Timing
                  305 Test Support
                  901 Handbook Glossary
            </comment>
       </Internal_Reference>
        
      <Internal_Reference>
        <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:radiosci.documentation:document:asmar.2014</lid_reference>
        <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
        <comment>
            User Guide for Cassini radio science data.
        </comment>
      </Internal_Reference>
        
      <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S. W., N. A. Renzetti, The Deep Space Network as an Instrument for Radio
                   Science Research, JPL Publication 80-93, Rev. 1, April 15, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   An overview of the accomplishments of the NASA Deep Space Network in the field of radio
                   science and a summary of current and planned capabilities as of the early 1990s.  The 
                   radio science implementation for the Cassini mission to Saturn and Titan is used as an 
                   example of planning.
            </description>
      </External_Reference>
        
      <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Deep Space Mission Systems, Tracking and Navigation Service, Requirements and
                   Design, DSMS No. 821-104, Rev. B, JPL D-17235, Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
                   Pasadena, CA, 2003.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   A document providing requirements for the Tracking and Navigation Service
                   within the Deep Space Mission System.
            </description>
      </External_Reference>
        
      <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Deep Space Mission Systems, Radio Science Service, Requirements and Design,
                   DSMS No. 821-110, Rev. A, JPL D-17241, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA,
                   2001.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   A document establishing the functional requirements for the Deep Space
                   Mission Systems Radio Science Service for the 1999 through 2008 time period. 
                   The requirements focus at the service level, mainly in the areas of external 
                   interface requirements (requirements to other services), Radio Science service 
                   functional requirements, Radio Science service performance requirements, 
                   reliability, maintainability requirements, and design and implementation 
                   constraints.
            </description>
      </External_Reference>
        
      <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Deep Space Mission System/Cassini Project Network Operations Plan, 
                   JPL Document DSN 871-011, March 2003.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   A document containing guidelines for support of the Cassini-Huygens mission, 
                   categorizes the Deep Space Network (DSN) operations functions, provides systems 
                   configuration, and details the DSN operating procedures necessary to 
                   prepare and train for committed support to the project.
            </description>
      </External_Reference>
        
      <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Kliore, A.J., J.D. Anderson, J.W. Armstrong, S.W. Asmar, C.L. Hamilton, 
                   N.J. Rappaport, H.D. Wahlquist, R. Ambrosini, F.M. Flasar, R.G. French, 
                   L. Iess, E.A. Marouf, and A.F. Nagy, Cassini Radio Science, Space Science 
                   Reviews, 115, 1, 1-70, November 2004.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   The Cassini Radio Science Team paper, published as the Cassini Orbiter began its
                   science observations within the Saturn system. Radio science investigations began
                   during the cruise phase of the mission and included searches for gravitational 
                   waves and solar conjunction observations. During the Saturnian Tour, atmospheric, 
                   ionospheric, ring, and satellite occultations were observed, and determinations
                   of masses and gravity fields were extracted from radio tracking data. New 
                   technologies in the construction of the instrument, which consisted of a portion 
                   on-board the spacecraft and another portion on the ground, were described in the
                   paper.  These included the use of a Ka-band signal, in addition to those 
                   at S- and X-bands, opening new opportunities for important discoveries in each
                   of the above scientific areas due to increased accuracy, resolution, sensitivity,
                   and dynamic range.
            </description>
      </External_Reference>
        
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>Radio Science Subsystem</name>
        <Type_List_Area>
            <ctli:Type_List>
                <ctli:type>Radio Science</ctli:type>
            </ctli:Type_List>
        </Type_List_Area>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>
        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>
        <description>
             The Cassini Radio Science instrument included elements on both the spacecraft
             and the ground. The spacecraft element (covered by this context product) was 
             further distributed among several subsystems on the Orbiter, while the ground 
             element included NASA Deep Space Network (DSN) complexes in California, 
             Australia, and Spain and occasional support from other ground stations such 
             as antennas of the European Space Agency tracking network.
 
             The Radio Science 'instrument' operated in two fundamental modes. For 'two-way' 
             measurements, the 'uplink' signal from the ground could be a single carrier 
             at either X-band (7.2 GHz) or Ka-band (34 GHz); or both carriers could be 
             transmitted at the same time.  The spacecraft radio equipment then acted as a
             repeater, collecting the carrier signal with the spacecraft High Gain Antenna 
             (HGA) and transforming it to one or more 'downlink' frequencies (2.3 GHz, 8.4 GHz, 
             or 32 GHz) by elements in the Radio Frequency Subsystem (RFS) and Radio Frequency
             Instrument Subsystem (RFIS). For 'one-way' measurements, the signal source was 
             on board the Cassini Orbiter; the output from an Ultrastable Oscillator (USO) was 
             transformed to downlinks at 2.3, 8.4, or 32 GHz.   
             
             The downlink signals were amplified and radiated through the HGA toward Earth.
             After passing through the medium of interest (e.g., plasma, rings, a neutral 
             atmosphere or gravitationally curved space), the perturbed signal was collected  
             by a ground antenna, amplified, down-converted, and recorded for later analysis.
        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
