<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch"         schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.sch"  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:pds ="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" 
    xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
    xmlns:xsi ="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation=
    "http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1    https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd
     http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1   https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.xsd">

    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:dsn.media</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Deep Space Station Media Calibration Subsystem</title>
        <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-05-10</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Initial version of the DSN Median Calibration Subsystem context product.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:radiosci.documentation:dsn.810-005</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This is the DSN Telecommunications Link Design Handbook. The reference is 
                to a PDS Collection. Each member product in the Collection comprises several 
                modules -- sometimes separate files, sometimes wrapped together into a single
                file, depending on the Handbook version included in the Collection.  Modules 
                are added, removed, and/or updated as needed. Each version of the Handbook
                (each member product of the Collection) contains all modules that were
                current as of the publication date.  Module 303 describes equipment used by 
                the DSN to obtain data from which correction factors can be determined for 
                media effects that limit accuracy in radio tracking of spacecraft.  The data 
                are forwarded from each Deep Space Communications Complex to the Network 
                Operations Control Center at JPL for processing, distribution, and archive.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Mannucci, A. J., B. D. Wilson, D. N. Yuan, C. H. Ho, U. J. Lindqwister, and
                T.F. Runge, A global mapping technique for GPS-derived ionospheric total 
                electron content measurements, Radio Science, 33, 3, 565-582, 1982.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                This paper describes a technique for retrieving global distribution of 
                vertical total electron content (TEC) from GPS-based measurements. TEC is
                interpolated within triangular tiles that tessellate the ionosphere, modeled
                as a thin spherical shell.  High spatial resolution can be achieved using
                gradient values and polynomial fitting.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Keihm, S. J., Water vapor radiometer measurements of the tropospheric delay
                fluctuations at Goldstone over a full year, TDA Progress Report, 42-122, 1-11,
                Pasadena: Jet Propulsion Laboratory, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                The report describes the performance of the DSN Water Vapor Radiometers (WVR),
                used to estimate radio path delay in the troposphere.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Keihm, S. J., A. Tanner, and H. Rosenberger, Measurements and calibration 
                of tropospheric delay at Goldstone from the Cassini media calibration system, 
                IPN Progress Report 42-158, Pasadena: Jet Propulsion Laboratory, 2004.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                The report describes the performance of the Advanced Media Calibration 
                (AMC) system developed to support Cassini radio science.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Asmar, S. W., J. W. Armstrong, L. Iess, and P. Tortora, Spacecraft 
                Doppler Tracking: Noise Budget and Accuracy Achievable in Precision Radio 
                Science Observations, Radio Science, 40, RS2001, doi:10.1029/2004RS003101,
                2005.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                The paper discusses noise in Doppler tracking of deep space probes and 
                provides a detailed noise model for Doppler radio science experiments. 
                Current technology allows velocity measurements to better than 1 micron 
                per second when data are averaged over 1000 seconds.  Examples from 
                Cassini are included.  Applications of the noise model to experiment 
                planning are considered, and the authors discuss the prospects for 
                significant sensitivity improvements.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Instrument>
        <name>Deep Space Station Media Calibration Subsystem</name>
        <Type_List_Area>
            <ctli:Type_List>
                <ctli:type>Radio Science</ctli:type>
            </ctli:Type_List>
        </Type_List_Area>
        <description>
             The Media Calibration Subsystem (DMD) provides three types of data:
             (1) Global Positioning System (GPS) data consisting of L-band carrier
                 phase and group delay of GPS satellite signals, ephemeris, and almanac
                 data for the GPS satellites;
             (2) Weather data, including temperature, barometric pressure, relative
                 humidity, precipitation rate, total precipitation, wind speed, and
                 wind direction.
             (3) Data from fixed Water Vapor Radiometers (WVR), which measure emission 
                 by water vapor in the atmosphere.  The WVR is part of normal DSN 
                 operations. At selected DSN stations, an advanced version (AWVR) 
                 measures emissions at 20.7 and 31.4 GHz along the line of sight to a
                 spacecraft being tracked. The AWVR is remotely operated for the DSN 
                 by the JPL Radar and Radio Science Systems Group (RRSSG) in Pasadena;
                 it is an element of a larger Advanced Media Calibration (AMC) system.
                 The AMC also includes a microwave temperature profiler and a sensitive
                 digital barometer. The AMC is capable of measuring the tropospheric 
                 relative frequency shift under summer conditions with a precision of 
                 better than 1e-14.
        </description>
    </Instrument>
 </Product_Context>
