<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:lidar.hay</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>LIGHT DETECTION AND RANGING INSTRUMENT for HAY</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.hay::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Abe, S., T. Mukai, N. Hirata, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, A.F. Cheng, H. Demura, R.W.
                   Gaskell, T. Hashimoto, K. Hiraoka, T. Honda, T. Kubota, M. Matsuoka, T. Mizuno,
                   R. Nakamura, D.J. Scheeres, and M. Yoshikawa, Mass and Local Topography
                   Measurements of Itokawa by Hayabusa, Science, 312, 1344-1347, 2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ABEETAL2006B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Mukai, T., H. Araki, T. Mizuno, N. Hatanaka, A.M. Nakamura, A. Kamei, H.
                   Nakayama and A. Cheng, Detection of mass, shape and surface roughness of target
                   asteroid of MUSES-C by LIDAR, Adv. Space Res., 29, 1231-1235, 2002.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MUKAIETAL2002</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Mukai, T., A.M. Nakamura and T. Sakai, Asteroidal surface studies by laboratory
                   light scattering and LIDAR on HAYABUSA, Adv. Space Res., 38, 138-141, 2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MUKAIETAL2006</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Mukai, T., S. Abe, N. Hirata, R. Nakamura, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, and 11 others, An
                   overview of the LIDAR observations of asteroid 25143 Itokawa. Advances in Space
                   Research 40, 187-192, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MUKAIETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>LIGHT DETECTION AND RANGING INSTRUMENT</name>
        <type>Altimeter</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
  The principal components of LIDAR are a diode-pumped, Nd:YAG laser
  transmitter that emits 1.064 micrometer wavelength laser pulses, a 0.126 m
  diameter telescope, a silicon avalanche photodiode detector, and a time
  interval unit with 14 nsec resolution. During the long Home Position phase
  (~7km from Itokawa) of the misson, LIDAR provides measurements of the
  topography of Itokawa within approximately 12x4.9 m footprints. The
  center-to-center along-track footprint spacing is highly
  variable throughout the mission. Range measurements, with an effective
  resolution of 50 cm, are converted to profiles of asteroid radius and
  topographic height after correction for orbit and pointing errors.  Shot
  locations are determined to within 10 m in the along-track and across-track
  directions. The current radial inaccuracies of the LIDAR data do not permit
  the generation of global grids of the surface of Itokawa.  Additional
  refinements are still required.
 
  LIDAR was designed, built and tested at the Institute of Space and
  Astronautical Science (ISAS) in Sagamihara, Japan part of the Japan
  Aerospace Exploration Agency.
 
 
  LIDAR Science Objectives
  =======================
 
  The primary LIDAR objective was to determine the distance between the
  HAYABUSA spacecraft and Itokawa to ensure a safe touch and go sampling of
  the asteroid. The LIDAR was key for obtain a reliable shape model of the
  surface of the asteroid, required for establishing its volume and mass.  In
  addition, it was found suitable for addressing problems in geology and
  geophysics [see  ABEETAL2006,MUKAIETAL2007].
 
 
  Instrument Specifications
  =========================
 
  The following table summarizes LIDAR characteristics.
 
  Parameter                          Value            Unit
  ----------------------------------------------------------------
  Physical Characteristics
   Volume                            0.0137          m^3
   Mass                              3.56            kg
   Power (TOTAL)                    22.00            W
 
  Laser Transmitter
   Laser type                 Q-switched, diode-pumped Nd:YAG*
   Wavelength                        1.064            micrometer
   Laser energy                      10               mJ pulse^-1
   Laser power consumption           17               W
   Pulse width                       14               ns (FWHM**)
   Pulse repetition rate             1                sec^-1
   Beam divergence                   1.7x0.7          mrad
 
  Altimeter Receiver
   Telescope type                     Cassegrain
   Mirror composition                 SiC
   Telescope diameter                 0.126            m
   Detector type          Silicon avalanche photodiode (Si APD)
 
  Receiver Electronics
   Receiver type            Filtered peak trigger
   Time resolution                    3.0              nsec
   Range resolution                   0.5              m
   Range accuracy (@50km)            10.0              m
 
  Measurements
   Footprint size (@ 7 km)          12.0x4.9           m
 
  * Nd:YAG is neodymium-doped yttrium aluminum garnet.
  ** FWHM is full width at half maximum.
  ----------------------------------------------------------------
 
 
  Operational Considerations
  ==========================
 
  The LIDAR instrument measures the round-trip time of flight of infrared
  laser pulses transmitted from the HAYABUSA spacecraft to the surface of
  Itokawa. The instrument operates in a single autonomous mode, in which it
  produces ranging measurements.  Surface topography estimates can be derived
  from these data, given appropriate corrections for the position and attitude
  of the spacecraft.
 
  LIDAR&apos;s transmitter is a Q-switched, Nd:YAG laser oscillator.  The Q-switch
  controls the emission of the laser, and Nd:YAG refers to the composition of
  the material that is optically excited to produce laser
  action: Neodymium-doped Yttrium Aluminum Garnet. The laser emits a
  14-ns-wide (full width at half the maximum pulse amplitude, FWHM) pulses at
  1.064 micrometers. The pulse repetition rate is 1 Hz, and the pulse energy
  was 10 mJ durign the entire peroid of operation. The laser consumed 17 W
  when operating, and it functioned without flaws for the entire 3 month
  period of the encounter with Itokawa.
 
  For additional information on the HAYABUSA LIDAR and its usage see
  MUKAIETAL2002 and MUKAIETAL2006. For a summary of some of the results
  obtained with the LIDAR see ABEETAL2006.
 
  References
  ==========
 
  Abe, S., T. Mukai, N. Hirata, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, A.F. Cheng, H. Demura, R.W.
  Gaskell, T. Hashimoto, K. Hiraoka, T. Honda, T. Kubota, M. Matsuoka, T.
  Mizuno, R. Nakamura, D.J. Scheeres, and M. Yoshikawa, Mass and Local
  Topography Measurements of Itokawa by Hayabusa,  Science, 312, 1344-1347,
  2006. [ABEETAL2006B]
 
  Mukai, T., H. Araki, T. Mizuno, N. Hatanaka, A.M. Nakamura, A. Kamei, H.
  Nakayama and A. Cheng, Detection of mass, shape and surface roughness of
  target asteroid of MUSES-C by LIDAR, Adv. Space Res., 29,1231-1235,
  2002.[MUKAIETAL2002]
 
  Mukai, T., A.M. Nakamura and T. Sakai, Asteroidal surface studies by
  laboratory light scattering and LIDAR on Hayabusa, Adv. Space Res., 38,
  138-141, 2006.  [MUKAIETAL2006]
 
  Mukai, T., S. Abe, N. Hirata, R. Nakamura, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, and 11 others,
  An overview of the LIDAR observations of asteroid 25143 Itokawa. Advances in
  Space Research 40, 187-192, 2007.  [MUKAIETAL2007]

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
