<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:amica.hay</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>ASTEROID MULTI-BAND IMAGING CAMERA for HAY</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.hay::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Ishiguro, M., R. Nakamura, D.J. Tholen, N. Hirata, H. Demura, E. Nemoto, A.M.
                   Nakamura, Y. Higuchi, A. Sogame, A. Yamamoto, K. Kitazato, Y. Yokota, T.
                   Kubota, T. Hashimoto, and J. Saito, The Hayabusa Spacecraft Asteroid Multi-Band
                   Imaging Camera: AMICA, Icarus (2010), doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2009.12.035, 2010.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ISHIGUROETAL2010</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Nakamura, T., A.M. Nakamura, J. Saito, S. Sasaki, R. Nakamura, and three
                   others, plus the AMICA team. Multi-band imaging camera and its sciences for the
                   Japanese near-earth asteroid mission MUSES-C. Earth, Planets, Space 53,
                   1047-1063, 2001.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.NAKAMURAETAL2001</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Saito, J., H. Miyamoto, R. Nakamura, M. Ishiguro, T. Michikami, and 29 others,
                   Detailed images of asteroid 25143 Itokawa from Hayabusa, Science 312, pp.
                   1341-1344, 2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.SAITOETAL2006</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Tedesco, E.F., D.J. Tholen, and B. Zellner, The eight-color asteroid survey:
                   Standard stars, The Astronomical Journal, 87, 11:1585-1592, 1982.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TEDESCOETAL1982</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>ASTEROID MULTI-BAND IMAGING CAMERA</name>
        <type>Imager</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
  The Asteroid Multi-Band Imaging Camera (AMICA) is one of the Optical
  Navigation Cameras (ONCs) of the Hayabusa mission, a Japanese-led
  sample-return mission to the asteroid 25143 Itokawa.  The three ONCs are
  AMICA (also known as ONC-T), and two wide angle navigation cameras ONC-W1
  and ONC-W2.  The AMICA system was used both for science and for optical
  navigation.  Pre-flight information about the instrument is available in
  Nakamura et al. (2001).  Preliminary results of AMICA are reported in Saito
  et al. (2006).  Full information about the specifications, performance, and
  calibration of AMICA may be found in Ishiguro et al. (2010).
 
  The optical axis of AMICA is designed to be boresighted with the NIRS and
  LIDAR instruments.  In-flight measurements of the star Alpha Scorpii
  determined that the boresight of NIRS is centered on the (493, 510) pixel in
  the AMICA frame.  Co-alignment of NIRS and LIDAR was adjusted as accurately
  as possible pre-flight and was confirmed after arrival at Itokawa.
 
  AMICA is a refracting telescope consisting of five lenses, each of which is
  cosmic-radiation-resistant and anti-reflection coated.  A quartz optical
  parallel window is placed in front of the first lens for radiation
  protection.  The SITe CCD chip, developed and built by NEC TOSHIBA Space
  Systems, Ltd., is of the back-illuminated MPP (Multi-Pinned Phase) type.
  The CCD is kept below -10 degrees C in ordinary in-flight condition.  The
  CCD dimensions are 1024 x 1000 pixels and the camera field of view is 5.83 x
  5.69 degrees.  The 12 columns on either side of the 1024 x 1000 pixel array
  are dark due to an obscuring mask.  DNs in these areas were found to be
  dependent on both incident flux and wavelength, suggesting that the masks
  are not perfectly impermeable to light.  Therefore, these pixels cannot be
  used for dark current correction.  The remaining unobscured region has the
  dimensions 1000 x 1000.
 
  Due to cosmic-ray irradiation during flight, hot pixels have developed in
  the AMICA CCD.  The known hot pixels and their dark rates are tabulated
  here:
 
  pixel (x,y)     dark rate (DN/sec)
  (407,300)         540
  (599,408)         330
  (820,14)          310
  (930,624)         305
  (897,716)         290
 
  Since the CCD is of the frame-transfer type, AMICA has no mechanical shutter
  but the exposure is controlled electronically.  30 different exposure times
  can be specified from 5.44 ms through 178 sec, plus a zero second exposure.
  The exposure time accuracy (including for the zero second exposure) is 1
  microsec.  The zero second exposure is necessary to correct readout smear
  which is inevitable for shutterless and frame-transfer type CCDs.
 
  AMICA has an eight position filter wheel, of which seven filters are nearly
  eqivalent to the ECAS bands (Tedesco et al. 1982).
 
  filter:   central wavelength (nm):   FWHM (nm):
    ul         381                      45
    b          429                     108
    v          553                      72
    w          700                      70
    x          861                      81
    p          960                      75
    zs        1008                      66
 
  The eighth position has a wide-bandpass filter.
 
  filter:   central wavelength (nm):   FWHM (nm):
  WIDE         650                     300
 
  Each filter aperture is sector-shaped and the filters are placed closely
  side by side at the edges to enable imaging in case the filter wheel stops
  accidentally at an improper position.
 
  AMICA has four position-angle glass polarizers placed immediately in front
  of the CCD on one side and each covering 200 x 200 pixels.  The four
  polarizers are placed with position angles of 0, 45, 90, and 135 degrees.
 
  The characteristics of AMICA are summarized below.
 
  Weight of camera:  1.74 kg
  Weight of electronics:  4.0 kg
  Power usage for camera:  6.8 W
  Power usage for electronics:  9.5 W
  Dimensions:  120mm x 135mm x 180 mm
  Effective lens diameter:  15 mm (F/8.0)
  Focal length:  120.80 mm (fixed)
  Field of view:  5.83 x 5.69 deg
  CCD dimensions:  1024 x 1000 pixels
  Pixel size:  12 micron square
  Pixel resolution:  20.490 arsec/pix
  Quantum efficiency:  45% at 350nm, 20% at 1000nm, 8% at 1050nm
  A/D conversion:  12 bits
  System spectral response:  360nm - 1050nm
  Stellar V limiting magnitude:  5 - 6
  Electronic shutter exposure time:  5.44 ms - 178 s
  Image memory storage:  16 frames
  Filters:  7 bands nearly equivalent to ECAS
  Polarizers:  4 position-angle glass polarizers
 
 
  References
  ==========
 
  Ishiguro, M., R. Nakamura, D.J. Tholen, N. Hirata, H. Demura, E. Nemoto,
  A.M. Nakamura, Y. Higuchi, A. Sogame, A. Yamamoto, K. Kitazato, Y. Yokota,
  T. Kubota, T. Hashimoto, and J. Saito, The Hayabusa Spacecraft Asteroid
  Multi-Band Imaging Camera: AMICA, Icarus (2010), doi:
  10.1016/j.icarus.2009.12.035, 2010.
 
  Nakamura, T., A.M. Nakamura, J. Saito, S. Sasaki, R. Nakamura, and three
  others, plus the AMICA team.  Multi-band imaging camera and its sciences for
  the Japanese near-earth asteroid mission MUSES-C.  Earth, Planets, Space 53,
  1047-1063, 2001.
 
  Saito, J., M. Miyamoto, R. Nakamura, M. Ishiguro, T. Michikami, and 29
  others.  Detailed images of asteroid 25143 Itokawa from Hayabusa.  Science
  312, 1341-1344, 2006.
 
  Tedesco, E.F., D.J. Tholen, and B. Zellner.  The eight-color asteroid
  survey:  Standard stars.  Astron. J. 87, 1587-1592, 1982.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
