<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nirs.hay</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>NEAR-INFRARED SPECTROMETER for HAY</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.hay::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Abe, S., T. Mukai, N. Hirata, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, A.F. Cheng, and 11 others,
                   Near-infrared spectral results of asteroid Itokawa from the Hayabusa
                   spacecraft, Science 312, 1334-1338, 2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ABEETAL2006</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Abe, S., T. Mukai, N. Hirata, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, A.F. Cheng, H. Demura, R.W.
                   Gaskell, T. Hashimoto, K. Hiraoka, T. Honda, T. Kubota, M. Matsuoka, T. Mizuno,
                   R. Nakamura, D.J. Scheeres, and M. Yoshikawa, Mass and Local Topography
                   Measurements of Itokawa by Hayabusa, Science, 312, 1344-1347, 2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ABEETAL2006B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Fujiwara, A., T. Mukai, J. Kawaguchi, and K.T. Uesugi, Sample Return Mission to
                   NEA : MUSES-C. Advances in Space Research 25, 231-238, 2000.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.FUJIWARAETAL2000</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Kitazato, K., B.E. Clark, M. Abe, S. Abe, Y. Takagi, T. Hiroi, O.S.
                   Barnouin-Jha, P.A. Abell, S.M. Lederer, F. Vilas, Near-infrared
                   spectrophotometry of Asteroid 25143 ltokawa from NIRS on the Hayabusa
                   spacecraft, Icarus 194, 137-145, 2008.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KITAZATOETAL2008</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>NEAR-INFRARED SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  The following information is taken from Kitazato et al. (2008) and Abe
  et al. (2010) (Unpublished).
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
  The Hayabusa Near-Infrared Spectrometer (NIRS) is composed of a grating
  infrared spectrometer (N1RS-S), a spectrometer electronics (NIRS-E) and a
  data processing unit to control NIRS, which is also used to operate the
  Hayabusa XRS. The NIRS-S is mounted on -Y panel inside surface of the
  spacecraft chassis in such a way that the viewing is fixed in almost the
  spacecraft Z-axis, direction in which opposite the solar arrays and
  high-gain antenna (see Fujiwara et al., 2000).
 
  The NIRS optical design consists of an entrance aperture stop, a field
  stopslit, two mirrors, a diffraction grating, a camera lens assembly, a
  detector, and two calibration targets.  The assembled spectrometer is
  covered with carbon-fiber reinforced plastic box case (300x150x100mm in
  size).  After passing through the slit, incident light is dispersed by a
  grism transmission diffraction grating, combined with a cross disperser
  and re-imaged by camera optics. The first-order light falls on a
  64-element indium-gallium-arsenide (1nGaAs) linear detector array that
  covers the range of 750-2250 nm in increments of 24 nm. The cross
  disperser prevents light other than first-order from reaching the detector.
  NIRS carries the two types of onboard calibration targets, an incandescent
  halogen lamp and a light-emitting-diode (LED), for periodic monitoring of
  detector stability. These targets are mounted on the aperture plate. The
  design was developed in accordance with the requirements of downsizing and
  weight saving.
 
  Table 1 lists key specifications and characteristics of the instrument.
  Note that the calibration LED is fixed outside of the aperture but the
  lamp is fixed on the inner edge of the aperture so that the effective
  aperture size drops off by 4 percent. The slit size was determined to
  provide an angular field-of-view (FOV) of 0.1 x 0.1 degrees, which
  corresponds to a spatial resolution of 17 x 17 meters at a distance of
  10 km.  A moveable shutter can be used to block the slit completely for
  dark current measurements. The signal in a dark spectrum represents the
  background electronic and other noise inherent in the instrument.  A
  thermoelectric Peltier device actively cools the InGaAs detector arrays
  in order to achieve a sufficient signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). The detector
  has a built-in complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) image sensor,
  which is used to multiplex the outputs to a single analog to digital (A/D)
  converter.
 
  Table 1:  NIRS Specifications
  -----------------------------------------------------
  Characteristic                 Value
  -----------------------------------------------------
  Spectral range                 850 - 2100 nm
  Spectral resolution            24 nm/channel
  Detector element size          30 x 100 microns
  Number of detector elements    64
  Grating ruling                 75 grooves/mm
  Slit size                      70 x 70 microns
  Field of view                  0.1 x 0.1 degrees
  Aperture                       27.2 mm
  Imaging interval               65.536 ms
  Integration time               0.256 - 57.344 ms
  Shutter driving                7.63 Hz (131.072 ms)
  Size (NIRS-S)                  336 x 165 x 100 mm
  Mass (NIRS-S)                  1.53 kg
  Power (NIRS-S)                 9.50 W
  Power (NIRS-E)                 0.45 W
  ------------------------------------------------------
 
 
  Operating Modes and Data Acquisition
  ====================================
 
  NIRS operation modes are implemented in the onboard software using
  instrument parameters that can be changed by ground operation commands.
  There are a total of five modes available to NIRS; NORMAL, RAW, HIST,
  LIDAR, and FLASH.
 
  In the NORMAL mode, each observation consists of certain sequential sets
  of alternate light and dark frames.  That is accomplished by the chopping
  motion of the shutter, allowing the dark current level of the detector to
  be subtracted on a channel-by-channel basis every time. The CMOS image
  sensor serves to read differences of outputs on each detector element
  between light and dark frames. The NIRS frame length is 65.536 ms, which
  corresponds to half of the shutter driving cycle, and exposure time can be
  changed at 256-stage from 0.256 ms to 57.344 ms.  In addition, the number
  of stacked light-dark frames can be also changed from 1 to 2 to the 255th
  power as the n-th power of two. Most of NIRS data were taken in this mode.
 
  The basic unit of spectral data for any given NIRS channel is digital
  number (DN) showing the integrated photon counts during a setting
  exposure-time interval. The raw data are originally sampled with 14 bits
  per channel (0-16383 DNs). A DN has a value of approximately 0.565 mV
  output from the detector pre-amplifiers when at gain 1.08x.  In the
  NORMAL mode, the data averaging of light frames subtracted dark spectrum
  are operated with onboard software, and only the mean, standard deviation,
  maximum and minimum of the DNs at individual channels were downloaded
  in instrument telemetry. The RAW mode prohibits the data averaging on
  board the spacecraft. The HIST mode provides a sequential output of the
  housekeeping (HK) data for NIRS. However, the RAW and HIST modes have not
  been used in reality until the completion of the asteroid observation.
 
  The LIDAR and FLASH modes were supposed to be used in the descent and
  touchdown phase during the Hayabusa rendezvous with ltokawa. In the LIDAR
  mode, NIRS carries out the frame difference readout in sync with the
  periodic laser pulse of LIDAR (a laser ranging instrument on Hayabusa) so
  as to observe the reflected laser light of the LIDAR from the asteroid
  surface. The shutter stays open during this observation mode. On the
  other hand, the FLASH mode was designed to remove the frame contaminated
  by flashlights to irradiate target markers for autonomous navigation of
  sampling.  This mode is identical to the NORMAL mode, excluding the
  removal of the synchronized frame with flashlights.
 
 
  Pre-launch Calibration and Characterization
  ===========================================
 
  The NIRS instrument was tested and calibrated extensively at the
  piece-part and instrument levels to verify its performance and to
  define its operational characteristics to levels required to meet the
  science objectives.  The tests and calibrations were carried out at
  ambient and vacuum chamber conditions.  Also the instrument underwent
  extensive vibrational and thermal vacuum testing.
 
  The ground testing and calibrations of NIRS were conducted primarily at
  the Institute of Space and Astronautical Science (ISAS), Japan. The
  tests at the piece-part level included measurements of detector linearity,
  responsivity as functions of wavelength and temperature, dark current
  characteristics and spectral transmission properties of the grating.
 
  Instrument-level calibrations of NIRS included measurements of the
  responsivity as a function of wavelength and FOV of each detector element
  (to verify detector linearity and alignment and to yield spectral
  resolution, spatial resolution, and flux calibration data),
  characterization of dark current levelsfor each detector element as a
  function of temperature, characterization of the level of spectral
  crosstalk on detector channels, and electronic performance
  characteristics of the detector arrays.  Finally, measurements of the
  calibration targets and some of mineral and rock samples were made with
  the assembled NIRS instrument.  The NIRS calibrations show that the
  detectors are linear and well aligned and that the instrument operates
  at very close to its design parameters for spatial and spectral
  resolution.
 
  Spectral Calibration
  --------------------
 
  Spectral calibration was conducted in order to establish the wavelengths
  sensed by a detector for each of the 64 possible grating positions.  That
  was performed by illuminating the instrument aperture with the
  monochromator, which is used in conjunction with an incandescent source
  and an integrating sphere.  The signals from the detector arrays were
  recorded with the monochromator wavelength scanned in 100 nm increments
  over the first-order wavelength range. The spectral calibration was
  performed under the ambient temperature of 2 degrees C.
  The central wavelength in nm of each of the detector arrays and the
  channel-to-wavelength relationship is expressed by
 
          lambda = -23.56n + 2271.44
 
  where n is the channel nuniber between 1 to 64. The accuracy of this
  equation for linear fitting is approximately 2 nm.
 
  Although the full range of the N1RS detector array is 751.8 to
  2259.7 nm, it is further limited, however, to 850 to 2100 nm
  (channels 7-60). The lower six channels (channels 1-6, at 2248-2130 nm)
  are near or in the detector cutoff, making the effective upper bound
  for good signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) around 2100 nm for the signal level
  expected at Itokawa. The upper four channels of the InGaAs detector
  (channels 61-64, at 834-763 nm) register very low signal due to fall-off
  in detector responsivity and grism efficiency.
 
  Radiometric Calibration
  -----------------------
 
  Tilt radiometric response of the NIRS was determined in a number of
  tests by recording the detector response while viewing a laboratory
  calibrated field with a halogen lamp and a Spectralon reflectance
  target. The measurements used a 1 kW filament lamp with a quartz envelope
  containing halogen gas. The spectral radiance of this source has been
  calibrated by the Oriel Instruments and this calibration is directly
  traceable to the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST).
  The lamp was powered by regulated direct current at the prescribed
  amperage, measured using NIST-traceable instruments.  In order to produce
  an extended source of known radiance, a Labsphere Spectralon standard,
  calibrated with traceability to NIST, was used.
 
  The response of the instrument was found to be linear and uncertainties
  of the NIRS absolute radiometric calibration of were estimated to be
  approximately 10 percent in the effective wavelength range. Though the
  calibration was performed under the ambient condition, we applied the
  correction of atmospheric water vapor using the MODTRAN software. The NIRS
  radiometric calibrations showed that for radiances expected at Itokawa, a
  signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) in excess of 100 is easily attainable in
  57 InGaAs channels (from 2 to 58) with nominal detector temperature of
  -15 degrees C. Since the detector temperature was maintained in an almost
  constant value in flight, except for caltarget observations, no temperature
  correction is required for the radiometric calibration.
 
  Spatial Calibration
  -------------------
 
  Alignment of the boresights of the Hayabusa scientific instruments relative
  to each other and to the nominal common boresight, the spacecraft -Z axis
  (the Z axis is perpendicular to the plane of Hayabusa&apos;s solar panels, and
  +Z direction on the spacecraft points toward the Sun with the spacecraft
  in its nominal orientation), were measured on ground, after spacecraft
  integration, using the reference optical cubes on each instrument For NIRS,
  the accurate boresight vector was found to be inclined toward the spacecraft
  -Z axis with the Euler angles (-0.1140, -0.0012, 0.0 degrees) and the
  co-alignment with LIDAR was verified. The FOV has rectangular shape with its
  sides along the X and Y axes of the instrument&apos;s frame and the angular size
  of 0.1 degrees.
 
  As these measurements were done under conditions of 1 gravity and room
  temperature, conditions experienced by Hayabusa in space will distort the
  coalipment between instruments slightly.  Coalignment between the
  instruments was re-measured in flight and during the asteroid rendezvous.
 
  In-flight Calibration
  =====================
 
  After launch, NIRS performed a comprehensive series of in-flight tests to
  validate and supplement ground calibration data, and to characterize
  instrument stability, pointing, and co-alignment with other instruments
  under flight conditions. The in-flight observations of astronomical targets
  took place during the cruise phase before the arriving at Itokawa, with NIRS
  obtaining spatially resolved spectra of the Earth and Moon, and
  disk-integrated spectra of the Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn, including three
  bright stars.
 
  Long-term Stability
  -------------------
 
  The periodic onboard calibration-target observations in space assessed the
  long-term stability of radiometric and spectral characteristics.  The
  onboard calibrated LED generates a narrow spectrum centered at the specific
  wavelength of  1.8 microns. Under a constant temperature condition, its peak
  wavelength does not shift beyond the NIRS spectral resolution.
 
  Without short-term general increases as in Earth swingby and the arrival,
  the calibration measurements show the gradual changes in NIRS channel
  responses up to +/- 3 percent. The reason for this behavior is probably
  related to spectral alignment of the detector. Using the data of detector
  wavelength drift, we found that displacement of detector channels can
  generate such changes in the detector responses. The general high
  responsivity seen in Earth swingby may be occurred by the lamp
  brightening due to the NIRS continuous operation. The rest of the overall
  time series corresponds to a gradual decay of the instrument primarily due
  to solar and cosmic ray radiation damage to the detectors and electronics.
  In addition, a general loss of 3-4 percent of NIRS response in the detector
  resulted from the launch.
 
  The slight changes in instrument sensitivity over two years of in-flight
  operations were found, but the radiometric response had been highly stable
  on time scale of a few months. The linearities of NIRS detector response
  also were verified from the various exposure-time frames on the
  calibration-target observation. Thus, we found that differences in
  instrument sensitivity of NIRS for the rendezvous phase fall within
  ~1 percent for overall effective detector channels.
 
  Validation of Calibration Coefficients
  --------------------------------------
 
  Validation of the absolute calibration was performed through observations
  of the astronomical targets during the cruise.  The spectra show an overall
  close match between the NIRS data and ground-based observations.
 
  Stray light from outside of the FOV was not a major issue with NIRS since it
  was not identified in the pre-launch test with a blackbody cavity. However,
  significant stray reflections were found when NIRS had observed across the
  limb of Moon. This may be due to the scattered light by the calibration lamp
  mounted on the aperture stop. The effect was dominant in the shorter
  wavelengths and required correction for proper calibration of the
  instrument. NIRS calibration did not incorporate a scattered light
  correction from pre-launch tests. The magnitude of out-of-field signal was
  quantified by acquiring swaths of spectra across the limb of Moon and
  Itokawa, during different orbits as the source of stray light changes in its
  size and illumination.  These results will also be augmented by the results
  of the more controlled investigations of stray and scattered light conducted
  during pre-flight calibrations.
 
  The magnitude of the scattered light is less than ~7% as shown in Figure 8
  of Abe et al. (2010), but its correction for the Itokawa spectral data has
  not been performed yet.  At wavelengths &gt; 1 micron, the effect of the
  scattered light is small compared with reflected light from Itokawa&apos;s
  surface.
 
  As for NIRS alignment and pointing, the co-alignment of NIRS with the
  AM1CA and with respect to the spacecraft was determined from the
  simultaneous observations of bright stars as point sources.  The other
  observation was attained during the Itokawa rendezvous phase. The NIRS
  had detected the reflected laser light of the LIDAR from the asteroid
  surface during the spacecraft descent (Abe et al. 2006). The LIDAR generates
  a 1064-nm yttrium-aluminus-garnet-Nd (YAG-Nd) laser beam to measure distance
  by determining the time of flight for laser light to travel from the
  spacecraft to asteroid and return. The detected LIDAR spectra have shown
  the peak wavelength same as that obtained in prelaunch.  Therefore, we found
  that there is no alteration of the NIRS spectral alignment from the
  prelaunch to final stage of the rendezvous phase. Moreover, L1DAR has a beam
  width of 0.04 degrees x 0.097 degrees, and such detection means that
  LIDAR boresight has been coaligned with NIRS as expected.
 
 
  References
  ==========
 
  Abe, M., Y. Takagi, K. Kitazato, S. Abe, T. Hiroi, F. Vilas, B.E. Clark,
  P.A. Abell, S.M. Lederer, K.S. Jarvis, T. Nimura, Y. Ueda, A. Fujiwara,
  Near-Infrared Spectral Results of Asteroid Itokawa from the Hayabusa
  Spacecraft, Science 312, 1334-1338, 2006.
 
  Abe, S., T. Mukai, N. Hirata, O.S. Barnouin-Jha, A.F. Cheng, H. Demura,
  R.W. Gaskell, T. Hashimoto, K. Hiraoka, T. Honda, T. Kubota, M. Matsuoka,
  T. Mizuno, R. Nakamura, D.J. Scheeres, M. Yoshikawa, Mass and Local
  Topography Measurements of Itokawa by Hayabusa. Science 312, 1344-1349,
  2006.
 
  Abe, M., Y. Takagi, S. Abe, and K. Kitazato, Instrument calibration of the
  Hayabusa near-infrared spectrometer, Unpublished, 2010.  (A copy of this
  paper may be found in the document directory of the NIRS calibrated data
  set, HAY-A-NIRS-3-NIRSCAL-V1.0.)
 
  Fujiwara, A., T. Mukai, J. Kawaguchi, and K.T. Uesugi, Sample Return Mission
  to NEA : MUSES-C. Advances in Space Research 25, 231-238, 2000.
 
  Kitazato, K., B.E. Clark, M. Abe, S. Abe, Y. Takagi, T. Hiroi,
  O.S. Barnouin-Jha, P.A. Abell, S.M. Lederer, F. Vilas, Near-infrared
  spectrophotometry of Asteroid 25143 ltokawa from NIRS on the Hayabusa
  spacecraft, Icarus 194, 137-145, 2008.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
