<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:irtf.3m0.mirac</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Mid-Infrared Array Camera</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_title>MIRAC</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-10-16</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Initial creation of the context product. 
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <External_Reference>
            <doi>10.1117/12.158697</doi>
            <reference_text>Hoffmann, W.F., et al., (1993), MIRAC: a mid-infrared array camera for astronomy, Proc.
            SPIE 1946, Infrared Detectors and Instrumentation (20 October 1993).
            </reference_text>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Instrument>
        <name>Mid-Infrared Array Camera</name>
        <type>Imager</type>
        <subtype>Mid-Infrared</subtype>
        <description>
            MIRAC (Mid-Infrared Array Camera) was built by Steward Observatory at the University of Arizona, Harvard
            Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, and the Center for Advanced Space Sensing at the Naval Research 
            Laboratory.  It uses a Hughes Aircraft Co. 20 X 64 pixel arsenic-doped silicon impurity band conduction
            hybrid array with a capacitance transimpedance amplifier readout (CRC 444A) operating at 10 K in a liquid-
            helium-cooled cryostat.
            
            The operating wavelength of MIRAC is 2 to 26 µm. Using 20 parallel readout lines and frame rate of 10 KHz,
            the array exhibits low noise and good linearity at high background flux, which is essential for 10 and 20 µm
            ground-based observing conditions. Peak efficiency of 0.42 at 22 µm, and a well size of 120,000 electrons.
            
            MIRAC operated on Steward Observatory 2.3-meter and the IRTF 3.0-meter telescopes for observing a variety of
            objects including infrared-luminous galaxies, planetary nebulae, star forming regions, young stellar objects, 
            and Solar System objects. The NEFD of the MIRAC on the IRTF at 11.7 µm is 0.1 Jy/arcsec^2 in one second of 
            integration on-source, four seconds of total time, including nodding and chopping off-source. 
            
        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
