<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:jiram.jno</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Jovian Infrared Auroral Mapper</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
      <Alias_List>
        <Alias>
          <alternate_id>JIRAM</alternate_id>
        </Alias>
      </Alias_List>        
      <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-10-12</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adriani, A., Filacchione, G., Di Iorio, T., Turrini, D., Noschese, R., Cicchetti, A., Grassi, D.,
                   Mura, A., Sindoni, G., Zambelli, M., Piccioni, G., Capria, M.T., Tosi, F., Orosei, R., Dinelli, B.M., 
                   Moriconi, M.L., Roncon, E., Lunine, J.I., Becker, H.N., Bini, A., Barbis, A., Calamai, L., 
                   Pasqui, C., Nencioni, S., Rossi, M., Lastri, M., Formaro, R. and Olivieri, A., JIRAM, the 
                   Jovian Infrared Auroral Mapper, Space Science Reviews, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11214-014-0094-y, 2017.
            </reference_text>
            <description>Space Science Reviews Instrument Paper</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>Jovian Infrared Auroral Mapper</name>
        <type>Imager</type> 
        <description>
          Instrument Overview                                                           
          ===================                                                           
          
          The JIRAM instrument has a two-fold objective:                                
          a- perform imaging of Jupiter, especially around the polar regions,           
          in the spectral region of 3.2-3.8 /Lm, where most of the auroral              
          emissions occur                                                               
          b- perform co-located spectroscopy and imaging of selected regions of         
          Jupiter'S atmosphere in the broader 2.0-5.0 /Lm wavelength range with         
          medium spectral resolution.                                                   
          JlRAM combines 2 data channels in one instrument: the imager and the          
          spectrometer, which are housed in the same optical subsystem.                 
          
          JIRAM is equipped with a single telescope that accommodates both an           
          infrared camera and a spectrometer to facilitate a large observational        
          flexibility in obtaining simultaneous images in the L and M bands with        
          the spectral radiance over the central zone of the images.                    
          Moreover, JIRAM will be able to perform spectral imaging of the planet        
          in the 2.0-5.0 m interval of wavelengths with a spectral resolution          
          better than 10 nm.                                                            
          Instrument design, modes, and observation strategy will be optimized          
          for operations on-board a spinning satellite in polar orbit around            
          Jupiter.                                                                      
          The JIRAM heritage comes from Italian-made, visual-infrared imaging           
          spectrometers dedicated to planetary exploration, such as VIMS-V on           
          Cassini, VIRTIS on Rosetta and Venus Express, and VIR-MS on the Dawn          
          mission.                                                                      
          JIRAM combines two data channels in one instrument: the imager and the        
          spectrometer, which are housed in the same optical subsystem.                 
          The instrument is composed of the Optical Head (OH) and the Main              
          Electronic (ME).                                                              
          The ME contains the electronics to drive the Focal Plane Arrays (FPAs)        
          and compensating mirror, and perform the acquisition and conversion of        
          the science and housekeeping data. It also manages the operation of           
          the two channels, gathers data and housekeeping information from them,        
          stores the data, performs data compression, and interfaces the                
          instrument with the spacecraft.                                               
          The single ME box contains the Digital Processing Unit, the proximity         
          (detector driver and readout board), the main (CPU board) electronics,        
          the power supply, and the limited angle de spinning mechanism driver          
          board.                                                                        
          
          
          OPERATIONAL MODES                                                             
          =================                                                             
          
          JIRAM FSW manages different operations, organised for operating modes         
          as follows:                                                                   
          PROM SW modes                                                                 
          Initialization mode (INI)                                                    
          SW Maintenance mode (SWM)                                                    
          Safe mode (SAF)                                                              
          Stand-by mode (STB)                                                          
          Science mode (SCI)                                                           
          Calibration mode (CAL)                                                       
          
          
          INITIALIZATION MODE                                                           
          ===================                                                           
          
          At the start-up (or after any reset), the instrument executes the INI         
          mode, where all the preliminary operations necessary for the nominal          
          working (HW and SW initialisation, memory checks, etc.) are executed          
          (Primary Boot). At the end of the Primary Boot the instrument is able         
          to check TC and send TM via the LSSL. The Secondary Boot is performed         
          after the reception of the proper TC.                                         
          
          
          SW MAINTENANCE MODE                                                           
          ====================                                                          
          
          The SWM mode is commanded from INI to allow the direct access to the          
          on board RAM and EEPROM memories which can be modified and checked to         
          allow SW patching and parameters                                              
          
          SAFE MODE                                                                     
          =========                                                                     
          
          The SAF mode is commanded from SWM or INI mode after the successfully         
          loading of the EEPROM SW (Secondary Boot). The IR detectors are Off.          
          This mode can be entered (commanded or autonomously)                          
          by all the EEPROM. This mode can be accessed by all the modes.                
          
          STAND-BY MODE                                                                 
          =============                                                                 
          
          The STB mode is commanded from SAF. In this mode the detectors are            
          on to allow thermal stabilization. The instrument is ready to receive         
          command to set and select the operative modes (SCI, CAL). The mode is         
          autonomously entered at the end of each acquisition sequence.                 
          
          
          SCIENCE MODE                                                                  
          ============                                                                  
          
          In the SCI mode the instrument performs a Science Session according to        
          the parameters received in STB. The main tasks are: NADIR acquisition         
          time evaluation based on SC Dynamics, IR commanding, data                     
          pre-processing, data compression, data packetization                          
          and transmission via HSSL\LSSL to SC, de-spinning mirror motor command        
          to compensate the SC rotation. Several sub-modes are selectable to            
          
          combine the capabilities of the two IR detectors (the first for               
          images,the second for spectra).                                               
          Simulated sub-modes are implemented too (I0S0 60 00).                         
          Data from the S/C are trasmitted in sub-frames. Each detector full            
          active areas is split into 6 sub-frames.                                      
          
          OPERATIVE MODE                                                                
          ==============                                                                
          
          SCI_I0_S1: Science, no IMAGE, SPECTRUM (256x336) High Spatial and High        
          
          SCI_I0_S2:                                                                    
          Science, no IMAGE, SPECTRUM (64x336) High Spatial and Low Spectral            
          
          SCI_I0_S3:                                                                    
          Science, no IMAGE, SPECTRUM(16x336) High Spatial and very Low Spectral        
          
          SCI_I1_S0:                                                                    
          Science, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition, no SPECTRUM                         
          
          SCI_I1_S1:                                                                    
          Science, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition, SPECTRUM (256x336) High             
          Spatial and High spectral                                                     
          
          SCI_I1_S2:                                                                    
          Science, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition, SPECTRUM (64x336) High              
          Spatial and Low spectral                                                      
          
          SCI_I1_S3:                                                                    
          Science, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition, SPECTRUM (16x336) High              
          Spatial and Low spectral                                                      
          
          SCI_I2_S0: Science, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, no SPECTRUM .                      
          
          SCI_I2_S1: Science, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, SPECTRUM(256x336) High             
          Spatial and High Spectral.                                                    
          
          SCI_I2_S2: Science, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, SPECTRUM (64x336) Medium           
          Spatial and High Spectral                                                     
          
          SCI_I2_S3: Science, IMAGE(128x432)                                            
          M-Band, SPECTRUM (16x336) Low Spatial and High Spectral                       
          
          SCI_I3_S0: Science, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, no SPECTRUM                        
          
          SCI_I3_S1: Science, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, SPECTRUM (256x336)                 
          High Spatial and High Spectral                                                
          
          SCI_I3_S2: Science, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, SPECTRUM(64x336) Medium            
          Spatial and Hogh Spectral                                                     
          
          SCI_I3_S3: Science, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, SPECTRUM (16x336)                  
          Low Spatial and Hogh Spectral                                                 
          
          
          CALIBRATION                                                                   
          ===========                                                                   
          
          The calibration procedure provides a standard sequence of 6                   
          measurements described in Table 11. The specific the meaning of the           
          steps is the following:                                                       
          1 - the detectors look at the internal calibration unit where the             
          calibration sources are in the off state, the integration time is             
          fixed;                                                                        
          2 - the detector is acquired with an integration time virtually equal         
          to 0 (actually 20 ?s);                                                        
          3 - one of the calibration source is turned on and powered with a             
          previously defined current, integration time is as in step 1;                 
          4 - the same calibration source is turned on and powered with a               
          previously defined current but higher than in step 3 to produce a             
          different level of signal, integration time is as in step 1;                  
          5 - same of step 1;                                                           
          6 - same of step 2.                                                           
          
          OPERATIVE MODE                                                                
          ==============                                                                
          
          CAL_I0_S1: Calibration, no IMAGE, SPECTRUM (256x336) High Spatial and         
          High Spectral                                                                 
          
          CAL_I0_S2: Calibration, no IMAGE, SPECTRUM (64x336) Medium Spatial and        
          High Spectral                                                                 
          
          CAL_I0_S3: Calibration, no IMAGE, SPECTRUM(16x336) Low Spatial and            
          very High Spectral                                                            
          
          CAL_I1_S0: Calibration, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition                       
          (L and M images), no SPECTRUM                                                 
          
          CAL_I1_S1: Calibration, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition (L and M              
          images), SPECTRUM (256x336) High Spatial and High spectral                    
          
          CAL_I1_S2: Calibration, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition (L and M              
          images),  SPECTRUM (64x336) Medium Spatial and High spectral                  
          
          CAL_I1_S3: Calibration, IMAGE(256x432) full acquisition (L and M              
          images), SPECTRUM (16x336) Low Spatial and High  spectral.                    
          
          CAL_I2_S0: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, no SPECTRUM                    
          
          CAL_I2_S1: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, SPECTRUM (256x336) High        
          Spatial and High Spectral                                                    
          
          CAL_I2_S2: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, SPECTRUM (64x336)              
          Medium Spatial and High Spectral                                              
          
          CAL_I2_S3: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) M-Band, SPECTRUM (16x336) Low          
          Spatial and High Spectral                                                     
          
          CAL_I3_S0: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, no SPECTRUM                    
          
          CAL_ I3_S1: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, SPECTRUM (256x336)            
          High  Spatial and High Spectral                                               
          
          CAL_I3_S2: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, SPECTRUM(64x336) Medium        
          Spatial and High Spectral                                                     
          
          CAL I3S3: Calibration, IMAGE(128x432) L-Band, SPECTRUM (16x336) Low           
          Spatial  and High Spectral                 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
