<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:fgm.jno</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MAGNETOMETER for JNO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.jno::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Connerney, J.E.P., M. Benn, J.B. Bjarno, T. Denver, J. Espley, J.L. Jorgensen,
                   P.S. Jorgensen, P. Lawton, A. Malinnikova, J.M. Merayo, S. Murphy, J. Odom, R.
                   Oliversen, R. Schnurr, D. Sheppard, and E.J. Smith, The Juno Magnetic Field
                   Investigation, Space Science Reviews, TBD, TBD-TBD, doiTBD, 2016.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CONNERNEYETAL2016</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MAGNETOMETER</name>
        <type>Magnetometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    The Juno spacecraft, atop an Atlas 551 launch vehicle, lifted
    off from Kennedy Space Center on August 5, 2011. The spacecraft
    uses an energy efficient Delta V-EGA trajectory in transit to Jupiter
    (&apos;delta V, Earth gravity assist&apos;). This trajectory used deep space
    maneuvers on 30 August 2012 and 14 September 2012 followed by an
    Earth gravity assist (close flyby) on 9 October 2013, during which
    it passed by the Earth at an altitude of approximately 500 km.
 
    Jupiter arrival (orbit insertion) occurs on 5 July 2016. The capture
    orbit and orbit to follow will be 53.5-day orbits prior to commencing
    operations. Juno&apos;s year-long prime mission (one Earth year) consists
    of 32 or more high inclination, high eccentricity orbits of Jupiter.
    The orbit is polar (90 degrees inclination) with a periapsis altitude of
    about 4500 km and a semimajor axis of 19.91 RJ; the corresponding
    orbital period is 10.9725 days (Earth days). An alternative science
    orbit period of 14-days is also under consideration at this time.
    The primary science is acquired during approximately 6 hours centered
    on each periapsis.  However, fields and particles data are acquired
    at lower rates for the remaining portion of each orbit. All orbits
    will include fields and particles measurements of the planet&apos;s auroral
    regions.
 
    The Juno Magnetometer (MAG) Investigation is a principal science
    investigation on the Juno New Frontier Mission to Jupiter. MAG will
    conduct the first global magnetic mapping of Jupiter and contribute
    to studies of Jupiter&apos;s polar magnetosphere.  The Juno MAG investigation
    is designed to acquire highly accurate measurements of the magnetic
    field in Jupiter&apos;s environment, mapping the planetary magnetic field
    with extraordinary accuracy and spatial resolution (orders of magnitude
    better than current knowledge).
 
    The MAG Instrument Suite consists of two boom mounted observing
    platforms (MAG Optical Bench, or MOB) each supporting a vector Fluxgate
    Magnetometer (FGM) and two non-magnetic Advanced Stellar Compass (ASC)
    Camera Head Units (CHUs).  The FGM uses two miniature ring-core fluxgate
    sensors to measure the magnetic field in three components of the vector
    field.  The ASC determines the attitude of the MOB in inertial space
    and relative to the JUNO spacecraft&apos;s Stellar Reference Units (SRU). The
    FGM was built at the Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC); the ASC was
    built at the Technical University of Denmark (DTU).
 
    The Juno MAG sensors are remotely mounted (at approximately 10 m and 12
    m) along a dedicated MAG boom that extends along the spacecraft +x axis,
    attached to the outer end of one of the spacecraft&apos;s three solar array
    structures.
 
    The JUNO sensor design covers the wide dynamic range with six instrument
    ranges (see below) increasing by factors of four the dynamic range in
    successive steps. The analog signals are digitized with a 16 bit analog
    to digital (A/D) converter, which yields a resolution of +/- 32768 steps
    for each dynamic range. In the table below, resolution, equal to half
    the quantization step size for each range, is listed in parentheses.
 
       FGM Characteristics        Dual Tri-Axial Ring Core Fluxgate
 
       Dynamic range (resolution) 16.3840 G (+/-25.0 nT)
                                   4.0960 G (+/-6.25 nT)
                                   1.0240 G (+/-1.56 nT)
                                   0.2560 G (+/-0.391 nT)
               (1 G = 100,000 nT)   6400 nT (+/-0.10 nT)
                                    1600 nT (+/-0.02 nT)
       Measurement accuracy:         0.01% absolute vector accuracy
       Intrinsic noise level         &lt;&lt;1 nT (range dependent)
       Zero level stability           &lt;1 nT (calibrated)
       Intrinsic sample rate          64 vector samples/s
 
    The data from each sensor can be in one of eight data formats. The
    instrument intrinsic sample rate of 64 samples/second is supported
    in data formats 0 and 1; averages over 2 to the n power samples
    (n = 1,2,3,4,5,6) are supported in telemetry modes 2 through 7.
 
    The MAG instrument suite is described in full detail in
    [CONNERNEYAL2016].

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
