<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nsp2.lcross</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>NEAR INFRARED SPECTROMETER 2 for LCROSS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.lcross::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   unk
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TBD</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>NEAR INFRARED SPECTROMETER 2</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Infrared Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
  The LCROSS payload contains two near-infrared spectrometers
  (NSP1/NSP2).  Their electronics units are identical, but they have
  different fore-optics designs.
 
  Near infrared spectrometer #1 (NSP1), also known as the nadir NSP, is
  located inside the Payload Observation Deck and is orientated
  along the +X axis in LCROSS spacecraft coordinate system.  The
  payload bore-sight is defined as the central position of the NSP1
  bore-sight throughout the mission.
 
  During the final stages of the mission, the LCROSS spacecraft&apos;s +X axis
  is orientated towards the lunar impact site. The payload&apos;s bore-sight
  (center of the NSP1 one-degree field of view (FOV)) is targeted towards the
  expected Centaur impact location.
 
  In comparison, the fore-optics feeding near infrared spectrometer #2
  (NSP2), also known as the solar-viewer or occulting NSP, is orientated
  along the -Z axis in LCROSS spacecraft coordinate system. This fore-optic
  is expected to collect radiance from the sun in its generous approximate
  130 degree FOV during the final hour of the mission.
 
  Both spectrometers provide 1.2-2.4 micron spectral coverage at low
  resolution. Both spectrometers are manufactured by Polychromix,
  a company whose primary spectrometer line is designed for material analysis
  and chemical sensing.  The spectrometers are designed to take a single
  SMA NA=0.22 fiber as input instead of a slit.  The diameter of this
  fiber defines the resolution of the instrument.
 
  Within the electronics unit of the spectrometer, light collected from
  the fiber (plus fore-optics) is reflected off a grating to spread
  frequencies across an innovative, electronically-tunable MEMS
  device.  This MEMS device reflects selected frequencies onto a
  single, TEC-cooled InGaAs sensor element.  The combination of
  frequencies merged together changes according to a timed sequence,
  and the resulting measurement stream is decoded on the ground to
  recover the individual frequencies.  The result is a highly
  sensitive, low power, and inexpensive spectrometer.  The spectrometer
  contains no moving parts other than the MEMs device and the peak power for
  each NSP is 2.5 W.
 
  NSP2 is fed by a 1.45 m length 600-micron core-diameter low-OH glass fiber
  attached to a fore-optics that is located external to the Payload
  Observation Deck (POD) housing. The NSP2 fore-optic is a diffuser providing
  ~130 degree field-of-view.
 
  Scientific Objectives
  =====================
 
  The two LCROSS near infrared spectrometers (NSP1/NSP2), by providing
  R~100 spectra over the 1.2 to 2.4 micron wavelength region, are the primary
  method to measure the amount of water vapor in the ejecta.  The LCROSS
  spacecraft will monitor spectral bands associated with water
  vapor, ice, and hydrated minerals covering the first overtones of the
  symmetric and asymmetric stretches of water.  This band, relatively free
  from interferences, is more brightly illuminated by sunlight than the
  fundamentals near 3 microns, more than compensating the weaker absorption
  of the overtones.  The regions near 1.4 and 1.9 microns, normally obscured
  by terrestrial atmospheric background in spectra from icy surfaces,
  will provide a sensitive indication of water vapor from ice or hydrates.
  The remainder of the spectral band will reveal the nature of ice crystals
  and mineral hydrates.
 
  NSP2 with its unique constant light source (the sun) provides a continuous
  mapping of the ejecta cloud in absorption by conducting an occultation
  experiment, until its FOV goes below the crater rim. The data set derived
  with NSP2 data provides a different viewing geometry through the ejecta
  cloud compared to the nadir-looking NSP1.
 
  Calibration
  ===========
 
  Spectra generated by the near infrared spectrometers are initially processed
  by the LCROSS GSEOS (Ground Support Equipment Operating System) which
  extracted the CCSDS files from telemetry, applied a fixed mathematical
  function (the Hadamard transform provided by the manufacturer) to
  convert 256 mask positions to 100 spectral elements, and converted them to
  an ASCII comma-separated file with some metadata and with MET-based packet
  timestamp  encoded in the filename. Spectra taken in Flash or Diagnostic
  Mode are saved into one file appended by subsequent sampling.
 
  Wavelength calibration, mapping pixel to wavelengths in microns, is
  provided by cross-checking in-orbit data  against lab reference spectra
  taken on the ground. Wavelength calibration is applied only to the 100
  pixels for Hadamard Mode, and a look-up table providing a the wavelength
  range across each mask position in Flash Mode.
 
  Conversion from raw data values [DN] to a scene spectral radiance
  [W/m^2 um sr], with errors, is performed using a response curve measured
  by the instrument in-flight using a data set from the preimpact
  sequence on Oct 9, 2009 ~11:00 UTC with the Sun as the source and providing
  a correction for the cosine angle to the it (~15.3 degrees for the data set
  used). This calibration was validated against pre-flight laboratory test
  of the same instrument,  using a NIST-calibrated reference source, although
  with a different fore-optic configuration, whose attributes were measured
  independently to correct out. In the lab-based comparison data,
  particular attention has been paid to addressing and correcting for any
  water contamination. The flight calibration for this instrument is derived
  from the solar spectrum measured on orbit during the last day of the
  mission. The calibration steps are described in the LCROSS Instrument
  Response and Calibration Report in the CALIB directory of this archive.
 
  For Hadamard spectra, a separate additional raw (pre-Hadamard transform)
  ASCII file containing the original mask positions, will also be part of
  the PDS delivery.
 
  The data for the NSP2 is also self-calibrating in orbit as reference
  spectra (sun, no ejecta) can be used for a constant reference source.
 
 
  Operational Modes
  =================
 
  Both spectrometers have three modes: Impact Flash (IF), Hadamard
  Spectrum (HS) and Diagnostic (DI), which are configurable by sending
  a command to the unit.
 
  The nominal Hadamard Spectrum Mode provides a 100-pixel spectra at 1.7 Hz
  rate with continuous coverage across 1.2 to 2.4 microns.
 
  The Impact Flash mode provides a five point (with a dark mask) sampling
  at known wavelengths across the spectral range at a 72 Hz sampling rate.
  The mask wavelengths, set approximately around the water bands, are
  described in the Instrument Response and Calibration Report.
 
  The instrument mode will be documented with each spectra or mask product.
 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
