<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nsp1.lcross</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>NEAR INFRARED SPECTROMETER 1 for LCROSS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.lcross::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   unk
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TBD</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>NEAR INFRARED SPECTROMETER 1</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Infrared Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
  The LCROSS payload contains two near-infrared
  spectrometers (NSP1/NSP2).  Their electronics units are
  identical, but they have different fore-optics designs.
 
  Near infrared spectrometer #1 (NSP1), also known as the
  nadir NSP, is located inside the Payload Observation Deck
  and is orientated along the +X axis in LCROSS spacecraft
  coordinate system. The payload bore-sight is defined as
  the central position of the NSP1 bore-sight throughout the
  mission.
 
  During the final hour of the mission, the LCROSS
  spacecraft&apos;s +X axis was orientated towards the lunar
  impact site.  The payload&apos;s boresight (center of the NSP1
  one-degree field of view (FOV)) is targeted towards the
  expected Centaur impact location.
 
  In comparison, the fore-optics feeding near infrared
  spectrometer #2 (NSP2), also known as the solar-viewer or
  occulting NSP, is orientated approximately along the -Z
  axis in LCROSS spacecraft coordinate system. This
  fore-optic is expected to collect radiance from the sun in
  its generous approximate 130 degree FOV during the final
  hour of the mission.
 
  Both spectrometers provide 1.2-2.4 micron spectral
  coverage at low resolution. Both spectrometers are
  manufactured by Polychromix, a company whose primary
  spectrometer line is designed for material analysis and
  chemical sensing.  The spectrometers are designed to take
  a single SMA NA=0.22 fiber as input instead of a slit.
  The diameter of this fiber defines the resolution of the
  instrument.
 
  Within the electronics unit of the spectrometer, light collected from
  the fiber (plus fore-optics) is reflected off a grating to spread
  frequencies across an innovative, electronically-tunable MEMS
  device.  This MEMS device reflects selected frequencies onto a
  single, TEC-cooled InGaAs sensor element.  The combination of
  frequencies merged together changes according to a timed sequence,
  and the resulting measurement stream is decoded on the ground to
  recover the individual frequencies.  The result is a highly
  sensitive, low power, and inexpensive spectrometer.  The spectrometer
  contains no moving parts other than the MEMs device and the peak power for
  each NSP is 2.5 W.
 
  NSP1 is fed by 75 cm length 600-micron core-diameter low-OH glass fiber
  attached to a fore-optic in the Payload Observation Deck (POD). The
  fore-optics unit is a fixed two-mirror and one lens system designed to
  provide one degree circular field-of-view.
 
 
  Scientific Objectives
  =====================
 
  The two LCROSS near infrared spectrometers (NSP1/NSP2), by providing
  R~40-70 spectra over the 1.2 to 2.4 micron wavelength region, are the
  primary method to measure the amount of water vapor in the ejecta.  The
  LCROSS spacecraft will monitor spectral bands associated with water
  vapor, ice, and hydrated minerals covering the first overtones of the
  symmetric and asymmetric stretches of water.  This band, relatively free
  from interferences, is more brightly illuminated by sunlight than the
  fundamentals near 3 microns, more than compensating the weaker absorption
  of the overtones.  The regions near 1.4 and 1.9 microns, normally obscured
  by terrestrial atmospheric background in spectra from icy surfaces,
  will provide a sensitive indication of water vapor from ice or hydrates.
  The remainder of the spectral band will reveal the nature of ice crystals
  and mineral hydrates.
 
  In addition, the nadir NSP1, can be operated in a fast spectral mode to
  provide a coarser spectral sampling, but at faster sampling rate (75 Hz
  versus 1.7 Hz normal spectral mode), to capture the spectra  shape and
  radiance of the infrared impact flash event.
 
 
  Calibration
  ===========
 
  Spectra generated by the near infrared spectrometers are initially processed
  by the LCROSS GSEOS (Ground Support Equipment Operating System) which
  extracted the CCSDS files from telemetry, applied a fixed mathematical
  function (the Hadamard transform provided by the manufacturer) to
  convert 256 mask positions to 100 spectral elements, and converted them to
  an ASCII comma-separated file with some metadata and with MET-based packet
  timestamp encoded in the filename. Spectra taken in Flash or Diagnostic
  Mode are saved into one file appended by subsequent sampling.
 
  Wavelength calibration, mapping pixel to wavelengths in microns, is
  provided by cross-checking in-orbit data against lab reference spectra
  taken on the ground. Wavelength calibration is applied only to the 100
  pixels for Hadamard Mode, and a look-up table providing a the wavelength
  range across each mask position in Flash Mode.
 
  Conversion from raw data values [DN] to a scene spectral radiance
  [W/m^2 um sr], with errors, is performed using a response curve measured
  by the instrument pre-flight using a NIST-calibrated reference source.
  As the pre-flight calibration data was performed at atmosphere, particular
  attention has been paid to addressing and correcting for any water
  contamination in the calibration products. The calibration steps are
  described in the LCROSS Instrument Response and Calibration Report
  in the CALIB directory of this archive.
 
  For Hadamard spectra, a separate additional raw (pre-Hadamard transform)
  ASCII file containing the original mask positions, will also be part of
  the PDS delivery.
 
  Operational Modes
  =================
 
  Both spectrometers have three modes: Impact Flash (IF), Hadamard
  Spectrum (HS) and Diagnostic (DI), which are configurable by sending
  a command to the unit.
 
  The nominal Hadamard Spectrum Mode provides a 100-pixel spectra at 1.7 Hz
  rate with continuous coverage across 1.2 to 2.4 microns.
 
  The Impact Flash mode provides a five point (with a dark mask) sampling
  at known wavelengths across the spectral range at a 72 Hz sampling rate.
  The mask wavelengths, set approximately around the water bands, are
  described in the Instrument Response and Calibration Report.
 
  The instrument mode will be documented with each spectra or mask product.
 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
