<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:lp.er</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>ELECTRON REFLECTOMETER for LP</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.lp</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Acuna, M.H., J.E.P. Connerney, P. Wasilewski, R.P. Lin, K.A. Anderson, C.W.
                   Carlson, J. McFadden, D.W. Curtis, H. Reme, A. Cros, J.L. Medale, J.A. Sauvaud,
                   C. d&apos;Uston, S.J. Bauer, P. Cloutier, M. Mayhew, and N.F. Ness, Mars Observer
                   Magnetic Fields Investigation, J. Geophys. Res., 97, 7799-7814, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ACUNAETAL1992</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Binder, A.B., W.C. Feldman, G.S. Hubbard, A.S. Konopliv, R.P. Lin, M.H. Acuna,
                   and L.L. Hood, Lunar Prospector searches for polar ice, a metallic core, gas
                   release events, and the moon&apos;s origin, Eos, Trans. AGU, 79, 97, 1998.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BINDERETAL1998</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Carlson, C., D. Curtis, G. Paschmann, and W. Michael, An instrument for rapidly
                   measuring plasma distribution functions with high resolution, Adv. Space Res.,
                   2, 67, 1983.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CARLSONETAL1983</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>ELECTRON REFLECTOMETER</name>
        <type>Magnetometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Electron Reflectometer. Measures magnetic fields-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    The Lunar Prospector Electron Reflectometer (ER) instrument is based
    on the instrument flown on the Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft
    [ACUNAETAL1992].  Some changes were made to the Lunar Prospector
    version to account for the spinning spacecraft.  The ER
    instrumentation consists of a symmetric hemispherical electrostatic
    analyzer and an electronics box.  The electronics box is common to
    the ER and its companion instrument, the Magnetometer (MAG).  The ER
    has a 360 degree disk-shaped field-of-view.  The electrostatic
    optics select energy and focus the particles onto an imaging
    detector. The ER sensor is a 12 cm diameter cylinder, 9 cm high.
 
    The combined mass of the Magnetometer and Electron Reflectometer is
    about 5 kg, and the two instruments together use about 4.5 w of
    power.
 
 
  Scientific Objectives
  ====================
    The Magnetometer/Electron Reflectometer (MAG/ER) experiment will
    investigate the origin and nature of lunar crustal magnetic fields
    and constrain the size of a metallic core.  The experiment also will
    provide global maps of the lunar crustal magnetic fields and provide
    estimates of the lunar induced magnetic dipole moment
    [BINDERETAL1998].
 
 
  Operational Considerations
  ==========================
    The ER unit maintains its temperature using thermal blanketing,
    surface finishes, and its internal power dissipation.
 
    The magnetic fields measured by the ER will be a combination of the
    Earth&apos;s magnetic field, the field carried from the Sun by the solar
    wind, and the Moon&apos;s field, which is extremely weak.  The magnetic
    field at the lunar surface also is affected by local deposits of
    magnetic material.
 
 
  Detector Mounting Descriptions
  ==============================
    The ER and electronics box are mounted at the ends of a small cross
    bar on the MAG/ER boom, about 1 m inboard from the MAG.  (The MAG is
    on the end of the same boom, about 2.6 m away from the spacecraft
    bus.)  The ER unit is mounted so that its field-of-view includes the
    spin axis and is perpendicular to the boom.  The only blockage of
    the ER field-of-view is the boom itself.
 
    The ER can measure magnetic fields as weak as one-millionth of the
    strength of the Earth&apos;s magnetic field.
 
 
  Principal Investigator
  ======================
    The Co-I and magnetics group leader for the Lunar Prospector
    Magnetometer and Electron Reflector experiment is Dr. Robert Lin of
    the University of California, Berkeley.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
