<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:lp.grs</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>GAMMA RAY SPECTROMETER for LP</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.lp</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Binder, A.B., W.C. Feldman, G.S. Hubbard, A.S. Konopliv, R.P. Lin, M.H. Acuna,
                   and L.L. Hood, Lunar Prospector searches for polar ice, a metallic core, gas
                   release events, and the moon&apos;s origin, Eos, Trans. AGU, 79, 97, 1998.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BINDERETAL1998</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Feldman, W.C., B.L. Barraclough, K.R. Fuller, D.J. Lawrence, S. Maurice,
                   M.C. Miller, T.H. Prettyman, and A.B. Binder, The Lunar Prospector
                   gamma-ray and neutron spectrometers, Nuc. Inst. and Meth. A, 422, 562,
                   1999a.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.FELDMANETAL1999A</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Feldman, W.C., D.J. Lawrence, S. Maurice, B.L. Barraclough, K.R. Fuller,
                   and R.D. Belian, Instrument Description Document (IDD) for the Lunar
                   Prospector Spectrometers, Los Alamos National Laboratory Report
                   LAUR-99-2752, 1999b.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.FELDMANETAL1999B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Feldman, W.C., et al., Gamma-ray, neutron, and alpha-particle
                   spectrometers for the Lunar Prospector mission, J. Geophys. Res., 109,
                   E07S06, doi:10.1029/2003JE002207, 2004.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.FELDMANETAL2004</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Genetay, I., S. Maurice, W.C. Feldman, O. Gasnault, D.J. Lawrence, R.C.
                   Elphic, C. d&apos;Uston, and A.B. Binder, Lunar neutrons at energies less than
                   500 keV, Planet. Space Sci., 51(3), 271-280, 2003.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GENETAYETAL2003</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Maurice, S., W.C. Feldman, D.J. Lawrence, O. Gasnault, C. d&apos;Uston, I.
                   Genetay, and P.G. Lucey, High-energy neutrons from the Moon, J. Geophys.
                   Res., 105, 20365-20375, 2000.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MAURICEETAL2000</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>GAMMA RAY SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
Instrument Overview
===================
 
A preliminary description of the LP-GRS sensor is given by FELDMANETAL199A
and FELDMANETAL1999B, and a more detailed description is given by
FELDMANETAL2004. For details not found herein, the reader is referred to
the above mentioned manuscripts.
 
The Lunar Prospector Gamma Ray Spectrometer (GRS) sensor consists of a
7.1 cm diameter by 7.6 cm long bismuth germanate (BGO) crystal, placed
within a 12 cm diameter by 20 cm long, borated-plastic anticoincidence
shield (ACS).  Both scintillators are viewed by separate
photomultiplier tubes, and enclosed in a cylindrical, graphite-epoxy
housing.  The GRS has a mass of 8.6 kg and uses about 3 w of power
[BINDERETAL1998].
 
Science Objectives
==================
 
The GRS will estimate the global surface abundances of key elements
(U, Th, K, O, Si, Mg, Fe, Ti, Ca, Al, and H).  The GRS will provide
new constraints on the bulk composition of the crust, on compositional
variations over the lunar surface, and on the existence of lunar
resources.  The GRS will investigate how large-scale impacts and
volcanism have modified the structure and surface composition of the
lunar crust.
 
Platform Mounting Descriptions
==============================
 
The Gamma Ray Spectrometer is mounted on one of the three Lunar
Prospector booms.
 
Operational Considerations
==========================
 
The sensor housing is wrapped with a thermostat controlled heater
within a thermal blanket that will provide a stable operational
environment of -28 deg C for at least 1.5 years.  The ACS functions to
tag penetrating charged-particle events from the gamma ray spectrum
and to tag gamma rays that escape from the BGO.  The ACS also detects
neutrons using the boron content of the shield.
 
Operation and Sampling Modes
============================
 
The Gamma Ray Spectrometer is designed to operate continuously during
the Lunar Prospector Primary Mission.  It acquires a spectrum every 32
seconds.  The gamma ray energy range of the instrument covers 0.3 to 9
MeV with a sampling resolution of 17.6 keV.  The Lunar Prospector GRS,
as a function of energy, is 2 to 8 times more sensitive than the
Apollo gamma ray spectrometer.
 
Principal Investigator
======================
 
The Co-I and spectrometer group leader for the Lunar Prospector Gamma
Ray Spectrometer experiment is Dr. William Feldman of Los Alamos
National Laboratory.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
