<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:dlre.lro</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>DIVINER LUNAR RADIOMETER EXPERIMENT for LRO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.lro::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Paige, D.A., et al., The Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter Diviner Lunar Radiometer
                   Experiment, Space Sci. Rev., doi: 10.1007/s11214-009-9529-2, 2009.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.PAIGEETAL2009</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>DIVINER LUNAR RADIOMETER EXPERIMENT</name>
        <type>Radiometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
Instrument Overview
===================
 
The Diviner Lunar Radiometer Experiment is in most respects a copy
of the Mars Climate Sounder (MCS) instrument on Mars Reconnaissance
Orbiter.  Both instruments observe radiation with 21 detectors in
each of nine spectral bands.  MCS is primarily an atmospheric limb
sounder that measures temperature, pressure, water vapor, dust, and
condensates at Mars&apos; atmospheric limb.  In contrast, Diviner is a
surface pushbroom mapper that measures emitted thermal radiation
and reflected solar radiation from the surface of the moon. Two
Diviner solar channels measure 0.3-3 micrometers reflected solar
radiation.  Three Diviner channels near 8 micrometers classify
regolith mineralogy by mapping the location of the Christiansen
feature.  The remaining four Diviner channels measure surface
temperature in four spectral bands ranging from 12.5 micrometers
to beyond 200 micrometers.
 
Hardware Overview
=================
 
The Diviner Lunar Radiometer Experiment is a nine channel
infrared radiometer employing filter radiometry. These channels
are distributed between two identical, boresighted telescopes,
and an articulated elevation/azimuth mount allows the telescopes
to view the lunar surface, space, and calibration targets. The
instantaneous field-of-view (FOV) response of each channel is
defined by a linear, 21-element, thermopile detector array at
the telescope focal plane, and its spectral response is defined
by a focal plane bandpass filter.
 
The Diviner structure consists of an instrument optics bench
assembly (OBA), an elevation/azimuth yoke, and an instrument
mount. The OBA contains all of the instrument optical
subassemblies, and is suspended from the yoke. Elevation and
azimuth motors mounted on the yoke drive instrument articulation.
The OBA can be temperature controlled, and internal temperature
gradients are minimized by design. Radiometric calibration is
provided by views of blackbody and solar targets mounted on the
yoke. The electronics subassemblies control signal processing,
instrument operation and articulation, command processing, and
data processing.  These electronics are distributed between the
OBA and the yoke.
 
For more information, including instrument diagrams and channel
bandpasses and functions, please see the EDR Software
Interface Specification (SIS).

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
