<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1400.sch" 
   schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
   http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 
   http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1400.xsd 
   ">
   <Identification_Area>
      <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:lpw.maven</logical_identifier>
      <version_id>1.0</version_id>
      <title>LPW</title>
      <information_model_version>1.4.0.0</information_model_version>
      <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
      <Alias_List>
         <Alias>
            <alternate_title>Langmuir Probe and Waves Instrument</alternate_title>
         </Alias>
      </Alias_List>
      <Modification_History>
         <Modification_Detail>
            <modification_date>2015-03-24</modification_date>
            <version_id>1.0</version_id>
            <description>
               Initial version.
            </description>
         </Modification_Detail>
      </Modification_History>
   </Identification_Area>
   <Reference_List>
      <Internal_Reference>
         <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.maven</lid_reference>
         <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
      </Internal_Reference>
   </Reference_List>
   <Instrument>
      <name>Langmuir Probe and Waves Instrument</name>
      <type>Plasma Wave Spectrometer</type>
      <description>
         The LPW instrument measures the electron density (ne) and temperature (Te) of Mars ionosphere 
         and detects waves that can heat ions in resulting in atmospheric loss. The instrument is designed 
         to measure three different types of quantities using three sensors. First is the Extreme 
         UltraViolet (EUV) sensor monitoring the irradiance of the Sun. The details of the EUV sensor and
         higher order data products are described separately. The other two quantities use the same sensors 
         to measure the in-situ plasma. The sensors are two cylindrical sensors mounted on two ~7-meter 
         booms. Electronically the LPW sensors 1 and 2 are either operated as two separate Langmuir probe (LP) 
         instruments or as one electric field instrument. The Boom Electronics Board (BEB) and the Digital 
         Fields Board (DFB) controls the three sensors and process the three sensor information. The LPW is a 
         part of the Particle and Fields (PF) suite and controlled by Particle and Fields Digital Processing 
         Unit (PFDPU).  The BEB and DFB are part of the PFDPU located inside the spacecraft body.
      </description>
   </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
