<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1800.sch" 
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1800.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rss.maven</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Radio Science Instrument for MAVEN</title>
        <information_model_version>1.8.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2017-10-04</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Original version.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.maven::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:maven.rose.raw:document:rsr</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
            <comment>
              The version referenced is Rev. A, dated 2001, which should be adequate for 
              most users.  Rev. B included minor content/format changes.  Subsequent versions
              (now at Rev. F) have been issued solely to improve the documentation.  Status 
              of Revs. B and C is unknown; Revs. D-F have not been cleared for ITAR release.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:maven.rose.raw:document:dlf</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
            <comment>
              This document must be used in conjunction with maven_rose_rsr.  It describes 
              variations in RSR tuning that allow better real-time frequency tracking of 
              the downlink carrier when occultations are observed in two-way mode.  For 
              MAVEN ROSE the RSR tuning is adjusted at millisecond cadence rather than at 
              (nominal) one second cadence.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S. W., N. A. Renzetti, The Deep Space Network as an Instrument 
                   for Radio Science Research, JPL Publication 80-93, Rev. 1, 15 April 
                   1993.  Available at https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=19950015039
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   A description of the technical capabilities of the NASA Deep Space Network 
                   in the mid 1990s as they might be applied to radio science observations 
                   conducted with spacecraft.  The report also provides an overview of six 
                   types of radio science investigations conducted using the DSN (radio 
                   propagation and occultation, solar corona and solar wind, celestial 
                   mechanics, gravitational waves, relativistic time delay, and spacecraft 
                   deceleration in cometary comae).  Although somewhat dated in technical 
                   details, the overview remains useful since the antenna, transmitter, and 
                   receiver performance has changed little since 1993.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Deep Space Mission Systems (DSMS) Telecommunications Link Design 
                   Handbook (810-005), Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA.  
                   Available at https://deepspace.jpl.nasa.gov/dsndocs/810-005/
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   A modular document that provides technical information useful in designing 
                   telecommunications interfaces and estimating their performance.  It provides 
                   data on 26-, 34-, and 70-m antennas; solar, atmospheric, and environmental 
                   effects; frequency assignments; doppler, ranging, commanding, 
                   telecommunications, interferometry, and open-loop receiving subsystems; and 
                   geometry, coverage, calibration, and test support.  A glossary is also 
                   included.  The modular organization facilitates updates, the most recent 
                   being in February 2017.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter Telecommunications, 
                   Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA.  September 2006.
                   Available at https://deepspace.jpl.nasa.gov/DPSummary/summary.html
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                   The referenced document provides technical details about the 
                   telecommunications subsystem flown on Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter.  
                   The subsystem flown on MAVEN is similar.  Differences include a 2-meter 
                   parabolic reflector high-gain antenna on MAVEN (rather than the 3-m offset 
                   parabolic reflector with subreflector on MRO) and no special on-board
                   oscillator on MAVEN, compared with an ultra-stable oscillator on MRO.
                   The minimum downlink data rate for MAVEN was 271-550 kb/s whereas it was 
                   500 kb/s for MRO.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
            <name>Radio Science Instrument</name>
            <type>Radio-Radar</type>
            <description>
                   In two-way mode a DSN ground station transmits an uplink carrier at about 
                   7.2 GHz, referenced to the local frequency and timing standard (FTS), which 
                   ensures greatest stability.  The uplink signal is received at the spacecraft; 
                   there are small phase changes in the signal if it has passed through the 
                   atmosphere/ionosphere of Mars.  The spacecraft telecommunication subsystem 
                   locks to the uplink signal and echoes it back at about 8.4 GHz.  Additional 
                   phase changes are imposed if the downlink signal passes through Mars 
                   atmosphere/ionosphere.  The downlink signal is received by the DSN ground 
                   station using its open-loop Radio Science Receiver, which is referenced to 
                   the FTS.  
            </description>
    </Instrument>
    
</Product_Context>
