<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1400.sch" 
   schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
   http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 
   http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1400.xsd 
   ">
   <Identification_Area>
      <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:sep.maven</logical_identifier>
      <version_id>1.0</version_id>
      <title>SEP</title>
      <information_model_version>1.4.0.0</information_model_version>
      <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
      <Alias_List>
         <Alias>
            <alternate_title>MAVEN Solar Energetic Particle Instrument</alternate_title>
         </Alias>
      </Alias_List>
      <Modification_History>
         <Modification_Detail>
            <modification_date>2015-03-24</modification_date>
            <version_id>1.0</version_id>
            <description>
               Initial version.
            </description>
         </Modification_Detail>
      </Modification_History>
   </Identification_Area>
   <Reference_List>
      <Internal_Reference>
         <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.maven</lid_reference>
         <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
      </Internal_Reference>
   </Reference_List>
   <Instrument>
      <name>Solar Energetic Particle Instrument</name>
      <type>Energetic Particle Detector</type>
      <description>
         The Solar Energetic Particle Instrument (SEP) consists of 2 sensors, each consisting of a pair of 
         double-ended solid-state telescopes, measuring electrons and ions over the energy ranges ~30-1000 keV 
         and ~30-12,000 keV/nuc respectively. The SEP sensors are closely based on the Solid State Telescope 
         (SST) sensors on the THEMIS probes and also share significant heritage with the SupraThermal Electron 
         (STE) detectors on STEREO and the SST detectors on the Wind spacecraft.
         
         The SEP sensors are mounted on two corners of the top deck of the spacecraft, positioned to ensure 
         that the fields of view (FOVs) adequately cover the canonical Parker spiral direction (around which 
         solar energetic particle distributions are typically centered), while 1) always avoiding glint from 
         the spacecraft, other sensors and the Articulated Payload Platform (APP) and 2) avoiding direct 
         sunlight during spacecraft attitudes typical of normal science operations.
         
         SEP provides measurements that satisfy the MAVEN level 1 requirement to determine solar
         energetic particles characteristics, 50 keV to 5 MeV protons, with ~1 hr time resolution, energy
         resolution better than 50% and precision better than 30%.
      </description>
   </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
