<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mcdonald.struve2m1.molp</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>McDonald Observatory Linear Polarimeter</title>
    <information_model_version>1.10.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2020-02-18</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Initial export from OLAF</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:mcdonald.struve2m1</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_telescope</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <reference_text>Breger, M., Interstellar grain size: A look at the deviant four, Astrophysical
Journal 233, 97-101, 1979.</reference_text>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>McDonald Observatory Linear Polarimeter</name>
    <type>Polarimeter</type>
    <description>The Linear Polarimeter was put into service at McDonald Observatory in 1978.  The
main element is a Glan-Air prism, rapidly rotating to counteract atmospheric
transparency fluctuations.  The Glan prism was chosen as an analyzer due to its very
high throughput, achromatic nature, optical precision, and low cost.  A slight
disadvantage
results from the presence of an air gap inside the prism and the resultant lateral
image displacement (less than 0.1mm).  A slight image rotation causes an instrumental
polarization of 0.05% which varies slightly with wavelength, is constant in time, and
can easily be subtracted out.  Other sources of instrumental polarization, including
the aluminized telescope mirrors, have turned out to be less than 10^-4.

Tests have shown that under ideal observing conditions, the polarimeter can measure
accurately to a precision on the order 10^-4.  In practice, therefore, the precision
of the polarimeter is limited by photon statistics.

For more information about the instrument, including a schematic diagram, see Breger
(1979).

Breger, M., Interstellar grain size:  A look at the deviant four, Astrophysical
Journal 233, 97-101, 1979.</description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>

