<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:pancam.mer2</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>PANORAMIC CAMERA for MER2</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mer2::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Bell, J.F. III, The Mars Exploration Rover Athena Panoramic Camera (Pancam)
                   Investigation, Journal of Geophysical Research, June 23, 2003.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BELLETAL2003</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>PANORAMIC CAMERA</name>
        <type>Imager</type> <!--RChen/EN was Camera-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    The Panoramic Camera (Pancam) investigation is part of the Athena
    science payload launched to Mars in 2003 on NASA&apos;s twin Mars
    Exploration Rover (MER) missions. The scientific goals of the Pancam
    investigation are to assess the high resolution morphology,
    topography, and geologic context of each MER landing site; to obtain
    color images to constrain the mineralogic, photometric, and physical
    properties of surface materials; and to determine dust and aerosol
    opacity and physical properties from direct imaging of the Sun and
    sky. Pancam also provides mission support measurements for the
    rovers, including Sun-finding for rover navigation; hazard
    identification and digital terrain modeling to help guide long-term
    rover traverse decisions; high resolution imaging to help guide the
    selection of in situ sampling targets; and acquisition of education
    and public outreach products. The Pancam optical, mechanical, and
    electronics design were optimized to achieve these science and
    mission support goals. Pancam is a multispectral, stereoscopic,
    panoramic imaging system consisting of two digital cameras mounted
    on a mast 1.5 m above the martian surface. The mast allows Pancam to
    image the full 360 degrees in azimuth and +/-90 degrees in
    elevation. Each Pancam camera utilizes a 1024 x 1024 pixel active
    imaging area frame transfer charge-coupled device (CCD) detector
    array. The Pancam optics have an effective focal length of 43 mm and
    a focal ratio of f/20, yielding an IFOV of 0.27 mrad/pixel and a FOV
    of 16 degrees x 16 degrees. Each rover&apos;s two Pancam &apos;eyes&apos; are
    separated by 30 cm and have a 1 degree toe-in to provide adequate
    stereo parallax. Each eye also includes a small 8-position filter
    wheel to allow surface mineralogic studies, multispectral sky
    imaging, and direct Sun imaging, in the 400-1100 nm wavelength
    region. Pancam was designed and calibrated to operate within
    specifications on Mars at temperatures from 218 K to 278 K. An
    onboard calibration target and fiducial marks provide the capability
    to validate the radiometric and geometric calibration on Mars.
 
    Information in this instrument description is taken from the Mars
    Exploration Rover Athena Panoramic Camera (Pancam) Investigation
    paper[BELLETAL2003]. See this paper for more details.
 
 
  Scientific Objectives
  =====================
    The chief scientific objectives of the Pancam are:
 
    1) to obtain monoscopic and stereoscopic image mosaics to asses the
       morphology, topography, and geologic context of each MER landing
       site,
 
    2) to obtain multispectral visible to short-wave near-IR images of
       selected regions to determine surface color and mineralogic
       properties,
 
    3) to obtain multispectral images over a range of viewing geometries
       to constrain surface photometric and physical properties, and
 
    4) to obtain images of the Sun and martian sky to constrain aerosol
       physical and radiative properties.
 
 
  Calibration
  ===========
    A rigorous test and calibration program has been conducted to derive
    and monitor Pancam instrument performance and calibration parameters
    and to validate the instrument calibration pipeline. These tests
    were conducted at the individual component level (CCDs, filters), at
    the assembled (standalone) camera level for each flight unit, at the
    subsystem level when the cameras were integrated with the camera bar
    and Pancam Mast Assembly (PMA), and finally at the system level
    during fully assembled rover testing. Tests were performed at both
    (Earth) ambient temperature and pressure conditions and under
    thermal vacuum conditions simulating the range of expected
    conditions on Mars. The most critical flatfield, throughput, and
    responsivity, calibrations were performed under near-vacuum
    (P &lt; 10-6 torr) and at three temperatures (218 K, 263 K, and 278 K)
    chosen to bracket the expected nominal daytime range of surface
    conditions expected during the mission.  Co-alignment tests among
    Pancam, Navcam, Hazcam, and Mini-TES were conducted in ambient
    conditions and in near-vacuum at temperatures of 178 K, 218 K,
    243 K, and 273 K.
 
    The Pancam will also be calibrated inflight. Monitoring of the
    stability of the Pancam spatial response pattern (flatfield) will be
    performed during flight by occasional imaging of the martian sky
    (which, if the azimuth and elevation relative to the Sun are chosen
    properly, should be acceptably flat over the field of view of
    Pancam).  If variations are detected because of, for example, dust
    particles on the Pancam external sapphire window, then these
    flatfields may be used in place of the pre-flight ground flatfields
    in the Pancam calibration pipeline.
 
    Monitoring of the Pancam radiometric calibration stability will be
    performed on Mars by frequent imaging of the Pancam calibration
    target under repeatable illumination conditions, and by occasional
    downlinking of reference pixel and dark current images. Imaging of
    the Sun and potentially certain bright standard stars at night may
    also provide additional information on calibration stability.
 
    A baseline for Mars surface calibration performance of Pancam
    (and other MER instruments) will be established during a
    &apos;calibration campaign&apos; to be performed shortly after each rover&apos;s
    landing. Observations planned for this campaign include baseline
    calibration target imaging, dark current and reference pixel images,
    sky flatfields, and reassessment of PMA pointing by imaging surveyed
    fiducial marks on the rover deck and lander. In addition to
    validating (or not) the pre-flight calibration coefficients and
    overall camera and PMA performance, these baseline measurements will
    be used to monitor the potential build-up of dust over time on
    either the camera optics or the surfaces of the Pancam calibration
    targets or magnetic properties experiment magnets.
 
 
  Operational Considerations
  ==========================
    Pancam is a very versatile instrument, and it will be used in a
    number of different ways during operations. One of the most
    important operational roles will be to acquire full 360 degree
    panoramas. One of these per rover, in RGB color (L2: 753 nm, L5:
    535 nm, and L6: 483 nm) and stereo (R2: 754 nm), is called for by
    the formal MER Level 1 Mission Success requirements. We plan to meet
    this requirement while each rover is still on the lander preparing
    for egress. The approach for such a panorama will be to acquire
    red-filter images at full resolution in both eyes, along with
    green- and blue-filter images at reduced resolution (using
    compression and/or downsampling) in the left eye.  Such a panorama
    provides morphologic and textural information at the highest
    possible resolution, &apos;true color&apos; information at somewhat lower
    resolution, and good stereo ranging of the full scene around the
    rover.  After this early &apos;Mission Success&apos; panorama, we plan to
    acquire full 360 degree Pancam panoramas rather infrequently because
    they take considerable time and generate a large volume of data.
 
    Partial panoramas (i.e., image mosaics less than 360 degree in size)
    will be the most common use of Pancam. These can be monochromatic or
    in many colors, and they typically will be targeted on the basis of
    images from the lower-resolution Navcams. Some images will be
    acquired with full multispectral coverage, using all of the
    instrument&apos;s geology filters.  This will be done when testing of a
    specific hypothesis requires determination of spectrophotometric
    properties across the full spectral range of the camera. The spatial
    coverage of full multispectral imaging will be restricted
    significantly by time and data volume limitations, so such images
    will need to be targeted carefully on the basis of previous
    Navcam or other Pancam imaging.
 
    Imaging of the martian sky will be conducted on a regular basis to
    monitor atmospheric conditions. The Sun will be imaged directly
    through both solar filters to determine wavelength dependent optical
    depth, and the sky will be imaged through the geology filters over a
    range of angular distance from the Sun to determine aerosol
    scattering properties.
 
    Pancam will be used to conduct several kinds of coordinated
    observations with other instruments. For example, both full
    multispectral Pancam imaging and Mini-TES rastering will commonly be
    conducted on candidate targets for in situ investigation in order to
    obtain morphologic, textural, and compositional information before
    making the decision to drive the rover.
 
    The Pancam will also be used in tandem with the Microscopic Imager
    (MI), because engineering considerations made it impossible to
    package a filter wheel with the MI. There are plans to acquire at
    least three-color Pancam images of every MI target. Software
    currently in development will allow us to register the
    lower-resolution Pancam color information with the higher-resolution
    textural information that the MI provides.
 
    Pancam will also be important for supporting the magnetic properties
    experiment. The Capture and Filter magnets at the base of the PMA
    will be imaged in color on a regular basis to monitor the gradual
    buildup of magnetic dust. These images will be used to assess when
    the depth of dust is great enough to commit to making Mossbauer and
    APXS measurements of the magnets. The Sweep magnet is mounted
    directly adjacent to the Pancam calibration target, so it will be
    imaged with no additional impact on time or data volume every time
    the target is imaged. The RAT magnets are located within the RAT,
    and after a RAT operation the Instrument Deployment Device will be
    used to position the RAT so that the magnets can be imaged in color
    by Pancam.
 
    Some of the most important operational considerations associated
    with Pancam are related to the large volume of data that the
    instrument can generate. By practical necessity, most Pancam data
    may end up being transmitted to Earth by UHF relay through the Mars
    Odyssey or Mars Global Surveyor (MGS) spacecraft. The latency
    associated with these links is substantial: up to 5 hours for
    Odyssey, and up to 2 days for MGS. Therefore most Pancam images will
    probably be used for strategic rather than tactical science
    planning, though judicious management of direct-to-Earth X-band
    downlink resources may allow an important subset of Pancam images
    (including 64x64 pixel&apos;thumbnail&apos; versions of all Pancam images
    acquired on each sol) to be downlinked more quickly. Very careful
    selection of compression and downsampling parameters will also be
    essential to maximizing the science return from Pancam.
 
 
  Detectors
  =========
    All 9 cameras on each MER rover, plus the descent imaging system on
    each lander, use a common and nearly-identical set of detectors and
    electronics.  Each MER camera, including Pancam, utilizes a
    1024 x 2048 frame transfer CCD detector designed by JPL and
    fabricated by Mitel (now DALSA Semiconductor, Inc). The CCDs are
    front-side illuminated, buried-channel devices configured to use one
    half of the pixels (1024 x 1024) as the active imaging area, and the
    other half as a storage/readout area masked from illumination by an
    opaque black-painted aluminum light shield. The CCDs do not use
    UV-enhancing or anti-reflection coatings. There are no antiblooming
    structures built into the MER CCD pixels, but blooming is modestly
    controlled using a &apos;clocked antblooming&apos; technique that consists of
    transferring charge between two phases in the same pixel during the
    integration time. There is also a drain structure that runs along
    side the serial register that is used to rapidly remove charge from
    the array during fast transfer or windowing. While these methods are
    not as effective as having true antiblooming structures in each
    12 um square pixel, they do not impact fill factor or collection
    efficiency, both of which are important for meeting Pancam
    measurement objectives.
 
    When powered, the CCD is constantly running in a &apos;frame flush&apos; mode
    where charge is drained from the array every 5.1 msec. An exposure
    is initiated at the start of a new frame flush cycle. Photons are
    then collected in the imaging area during the specified integration
    time (from 0 to 65535 exposure counts, where each exposure count
    equals 5.12 msec) and then once the exposure is complete the
    accumulated charge is rapidly shifted (shift time = 5.12 msec) into
    the storage area. This rapid charge transfer obviates the need
    for a mechanical shutter on the camera, but also limits the minimum
    exposure time (0 counts) to 5.12 msec and leads to the generation of
    frame transfer smear signal that must be corrected in calibration
    (see Section 4.2.4 below).
    Once the collected photons are in the storage area, they are clocked
    out, row by row, into a horizontal serial register for subsequent
    amplification and digitization. The readout rate is 200 kHz
    (200,000 pixels/sec), or 5 msec per row, leading to a total readout
    time of approximately 5 seconds per full frame image. The horizontal
    register also contains 16 extended or &apos;reference&apos; pixels at each end
    that are also read out and digitized by the camera electronics.
    These pixels provide information on the video offset (bias) level,
    and can be optionally saved for downlink as a 32 x 1024&apos;reference
    pixel&apos; Experiment Data Record (EDR) image file.
 
 
  Electronics
  ===========
    The MER camera electronics consist of clock drivers that provide
    3-phase timing pulses for transfer of charge through the CCD, as
    well as a signal chain that amplifies the CCD output and converts it
    from analog voltages to a 12-bit digitized signal. An Actel Field
    Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) provides all of the timing, logic,
    and control functions in the signal chain. The FPGA also inserts a
    unique camera identification number into the telemetry for each
    camera to simplify data management and post-processing. A correlated
    doublesampling Analog-to-Digital Converter (ADC) compares the
    amplified CCD output voltage against a (commandable) reference
    voltage from the FPGA to achieve 12-bit (0-4095) digitization of the
    signal. Gain, read noise, and other performance metrics of the
    Pancam signal chain are reported below.
 
    The rovers&apos; flight software provides a substantial amount of
    capability for doing onboard image processing prior to downlink,
    with the primary goal to increase the compressibility of images and
    thus to maximize the amount of data that can be sent back to Earth
    during each downlink session. The image processing services offered
    by the rover CPU include bad pixel correction, flatfield correction,
    frame transfer smear correction, image downsampling, image
    subframing, pixel summing, 12 to 8 bit scaling via lookup tables,
    and image compression.
 
    However, frame transfer smear correction deserves special notice
    because of its importance and implications for Pancam imaging. As
    discussed above, there are analytic or empirical ways to remove
    frame transfer smear signal from Pancam images. The main advantage
    of the a posteriori analytic approach of modeling the effect is that
    no additional image acquisition time or processing time are required
    on Mars. However, the uncorrected images to be downlinked are likely
    to be less compressible than corrected images, and substantial
    additional post-processing time is required in the ground
    calibration pipeline. The main advantage of the in situ empirical
    approach of subtracting a zero-exposure image is that the removal of
    the bias, storage region dark current, and frame transfer ramp
    components should produce a much more compressible image for
    downlink than images that have not been corrected. The price for
    this increased downlink efficiency, though, is a doubling of the
    time required to acquire images, plus additional overhead for
    onboard CPU processing. It is anticipated that the tradeoffs will be
    made so that sometimes onboard frame transfer smear removal is more
    advantageous, while sometimes post-processing analytic removal may
    be more advantageous. Each situation will need to be considered on
    a case by case basis.
 
    Rapid lossless onboard compression of MER camera images can be
    performed using a routine called LOCO, which is based on the same
    kind of segmented discrete cosine transform method as the JPEG
    compressor. High quality lossy compression can be performed using a
    routine called ICER, which is a wavelet-based progressive
    compression routine that has been shown in tests by the MER science
    team to retain excellent image quality even at relatively high
    compression factors below 1 bit per pixel (compression ratios
    exceeding 12:1 for MER images).
 
 
  Filters
  =======
    Each Pancam camera is equipped with a small 8-position filter wheel.
    Fifteen of the sixteen filter wheel slots contain filters; one slot
    (L1) was left empty to maximize sensitivity during low-light and
    ambient Earth temperature (pre-flight) imaging conditions. The
    filters are glass interference filters, 11 mm in diameter (10 mm
    clear aperture) and were fabricated by Omega Optical, Inc.  Thirteen
    of the fifteen filters per camera pair are so-called &apos;geology&apos;
    filters, designed for imaging of the surface or sky, and the
    remaining two filters are &apos;solar&apos; filters, designed for direct
    imaging of the Sun. The geology filters were designed and fabricated
    to have peak transmission &gt;85%, transmission ripple within the
    passband of &lt; 10%, central wavelength uniformity and central
    wavelength shift resulting from angle of incidence variations across
    the FOV of &lt; 1%, and a wavelength-integrated rejection band response
    in the 400 to 1100 nm region of &lt; 1% of that filter&apos;s integrated
    in-band response. The solar filters have the same requirements for
    their bandpasses, but also are coated with metallic attenuation
    films to provide an additional factor of 105 reduction in overall
    transmission.  The shortest wavelength (440 nm) and longest
    wavelength (1000 nm) filters are actually short-pass and long-pass
    filters, respectively, to provide wider bandpasses to maximize the
    SNR at these extreme ends of the CCD spectral response profile. The
    filters are divided between the cameras so that, in general, the
    shorter wavelength filters &lt; 750 nm are in the left camera and the
    longer wavelength filters &gt; 750 nm are in the right camera. Two
    filters, near 440 and 750 nm, are redundant in the left and right
    Pancams. This provides stereo imaging capability in two colors, as
    well as redundancy for generating pseudo-true color images in the
    right Pancam, in the event of a left Pancam failure.
 
 
  Optics
  ======
    The science and measurement requirements outlined above (spatial
    resolution, depth of field, and field of view), the realities of
    limited payload mass and volume resources, and the harsh martian
    surface environmental conditions all dictate design constraints on
    Pancam optics. The resulting design is small (short focal length),
    lightweight, has a slow focal ratio (greater depth of field),
    employs discrete spherical or flat elements rather than cemented or
    aspherical surfaces, and does not allow vignetting of the field. An
    anti-reflection coated sapphire window protects the filters and
    filter wheel mechanisms from contamination by airborne dust
    particles and helps cut down stray and scattered light effects. A
    short sunshade and set of black internal baffles provide rejection
    of stray and scattered light. The Pancam lens design is a Cooke
    triplet. The lens was designed to have a focal length of 43 mm,
    which yields a field of view (FOV) of 16 degrees x 16 degrees
    (22.5 degrees on the diagonal) that is approximately equal to the
    FOV of a 109 mm telephoto lens on a standard 35 mm camera. The
    Instantaneous Field of View (IFOV) of each pixel was designed to be
    approximately 280 x 280 urad, yielding 560 urad limiting resolution
    on a pair of adjacent 12 um pixels, or a Nyquist limit for spatial
    frequency detection of 41.67 cycles/mm. The lenses were designed to
    operate at f/20 with a fixed (hyperfocal) distance of 3.0 m and to
    view objects in focus whose distances range from infinity to 1.5m
    (the depth of field). The Modulation Transfer Function (MTF)
    performance of the optics was assessed at the component level at
    three wavelengths: near the shortest Pancam bandpass around 430 nm,
    near the peak of the planet&apos;s spectral reflectance function at
    750 nm, and near the longest Pancam bandpass at 980 nm. At 430 nm,
    the actual MTF values cluster just below the diffraction-limited
    value of 55% at the Nyquist cutoff frequency. Similarly, for 750 nm,
    the actual curves cluster just below the diffraction limit of 25% at
    Nyquist. And for 980 nm, the curves drop to just below the
    diffraction limit of 8% at Nyquist.
 
 
  Location
  ========
    The Pancam is located atop the Pancam Mast Assembly (PMA)

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
