<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" 
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 
 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rss.mess</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>Radio Science Subsystem for Gravity Science on MESSENGER</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
          <Modification_Detail>
            <modification_date>2018-12-04</modification_date>
            <version_id>1.1</version_id>
            <description>
              Revised and streamlined during migration of PDS3 data set to PDS4.
            </description>
          </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mess</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
          <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:messenger:document-rs:instrument_rs</lid_reference>
          <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S. W., N. A. Renzetti, The Deep Space Network as an instrument for radio
                   science research, Jet Propulsion Laboratory Publication 80-93, Rev. 1, 15 April 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              Description of the NASA Deep Space Network as it was used for radio science in the mid-1990s.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S.W., R.G. Herrera, and T. Priest, Radio Science Handbook, JPL D-7938,
                   Volume 6, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              A handbook prepared by the JPL Radio Science Support Team. Volume 6 focused on
              radio science operations supporting redshift observations, USO tests, solar wind
              scintillations, and Jupiter occultations in NASA's Galileo mission.  No subsequent 
              volumes were released for missions after Galileo.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Chang, Christine, DSN Telecommunications Link Design Handbook, DSN Document 810-5, 
                   JPL D-19379, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              A modularized source of technical information for flight projects using the DSN. The Handbook
              provides information useful to flight projects contemplating the design of hardware and 
              software, with reasonable assurance that the resulting project telecommunications interfaces 
              will be compatible with established or planned DSN configurations.  The modules are revised 
              from time to time to reflect new capabilities when these new capabilities have been planned 
              and budgeted by the DSN Project Office.  The handbook was first released in 1970; its 48th 
              revision was released in 2018.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Sniffin, R. W., DSN Coverage and Geometry, DSN/Flight Project Interface Design
                   document GEO-10, Rev. E, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              A module of a larger document (810-5) that describes the geometry and visibility
              provided by the DSN in supporting spacecraft telecommunications. The module provides
              DSN station coordinates and locates the stations with respect to other points on the
              Earth's surface.  Coverage charts illustrate areas of coverage and non-coverage
              from selected combinations of stations for spacraft at selected altitudes.  Horizon
              masks are included so that the effects of terrain masking can be anticipated.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Deep Space Mission System (DSMS) External Interface Specification 0159-Science
                   Radio Science Receiver Standard Formatted Data Unit (SFDU), part of DSN
                   document 820-013 (JPL D-16765), Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 2001.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              The specification of the Radio Science Receiver (RSR) Standard Format Data Unit (SFDU).
              It documents the format and contents of the RSR SFDU and briefly describes the RSR
              itself and the various mechanisms by which RSR SFDUs are stored and transported.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Solomon, S.C., R.L. McNutt, Jr., R.E. Gold, and D.L. Domingue, MESSENGER
                   mission overview, Space Science Reviews, 131, 3-39, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              A description of the MESSENGER mission and its planned science, written before the
              spacecraft arrived at Mercury.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Srinivasan, D.K., M.E. Perry, K.B. Fielhauer, D.E. Smith, and M.T. Zuber, The
                   radio frequency subsystem and radio science on the MESSENGER mission, Space
                   Science Reviews, 131, 557-571, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
              A description of the MESSENGER radio science subsystem and the planned radio science
              investigations, written before the spacecraft arrived at Mercury.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>Radio Science Subsystem</name>
        <type>Radio Science</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>
        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>
        <description>
          The telecommunications system uses an X-band transponder on the spacecraft and
          transmitters and receivers at stations of the NASA Deep Space Network on Earth.
          Range and Doppler measurements made during communcations sessions can be used to
          determine the spacecraft trajectory; from the trajectory, Mercury's gravity field
          can be inferred.  Measurements of occultation times can be used to obtain the
          planet's radius at the occultation points, refining the planet's shape model.
        </description>
    </Instrument>
  
</Product_Context>
