<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:ns.mess</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>NEUTRON SPECTROMETER for MESS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mess::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Goldsten, J.O., E.A. Rhodes,, W.V. Boynton, W.C. Feldman, D.J. Lawrence, J.I.
                   Trombka, D.M. Smith, L.G. Evans, J. White, N.W. Madden, P.C. Berg, G.A. Murphy,
                   R.S. Gurnee, K. Strohbehn, B.D. Williams, E.D. Schaefer, C.A. Monaco, C.P.
                   Cork, J.D. Eckels, W.O. Miller, M.T. Burks, L.B. Hagler, S.J. Deteresa, and
                   M.C. Witte, The MESSENGER Gamma-Ray and Neutron Spectrometer, Space Science
                   Reviews, 131, 339-391, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GOLDSTENETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>NEUTRON SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Neutron Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
   The Mercury Surface, Space Environment, Geochemistry and Ranging
   (MESSENGER) mission is designed to orbit Mercury following one
   Earth flyby, two flybys of Venus and three of Mercury.  It launched
   in August 2004 and will use these flybys to achieve an orbit
   insertion around Mercury in March 2011.  Initial data collection
   will begin during the three flybys of Mercury, and will primarily
   consist of global mapping and measurements of the surface,
   atmosphere and magnetosphere composition.  MESSENGER will remain in
   orbit for the rest of the nominal mission, which is scheduled to
   end in March 2012. Once in orbit around Mercury it will begin a
   series of observations using multiple instruments. These
   observations will provide data to answer questions about the nature
   and composition of Mercury&apos;s crust, tectonic history, the structure
   of the atmosphere and magnetosphere, and the nature of the polar
   deposits.
 
   The Gamma-Ray and Neutron Spectrometer (GRNS) instrument forms part
   of the geochemistry investigation of the MESSENGER mission and will
   yield information about the elemental composition of the planet&apos;s
   surface. The GRNS package is composed of two independent sensors:
   the Gamma-Ray Spectrometer (GRS) and the Neutron Spectrometer (NS).
   GRS detects gamma-ray emissions in the 0.1 - 10 MeV range, allowing
   the identification of certain elements and their abundances to be
   determined. NS measures the flux of ejected neutrons in three
   energy ranges and is particularly sensitive to the H content of a
   body. Taken together, the gamma-ray and neutron measurements will
   be used to infer the composition of Mercury&apos;s surface over
   localized regions using established techniques, such as used
   recently on the Lunar Prospector and Mars Odyssey missions.
 
   The NS sensor consists of three scintillators, each wrapped
   separately and coupled to separate photo-multiplier tubes. The
   three scintillators are sensitive to neutrons of different
   energies: thermal neutrons (0.025 - 1 eV), epithermal neutrons
   (1 eV - 500 keV), and fast neutrons (500 keV - 7 MeV). The first
   and third scintillators are lithium (6Li)-glass scintillators (LG1
   and LG2) which respond to a combination of thermal and epithermal
   neutrons. The middle scintillator is a borated plastic (BP)
   scintillator that responds only to epithermal and fast neutrons due
   to its electronics setup. The interaction of galactic cosmic rays
   (GCR) with the surface of Mercury produces neutrons, some of which
   escape the surface and produce a neutron signal that can be
   measured by the orbiting NS sensor. The measured neutron energy
   spectrum reflects the transport properties of the surface
   composition and is sensitive to depths down to about 1 m. Thermal
   neutrons are sensitive to a variety of elements, including Fe, Ti,
   Gd, Sm, Cl, and C. Epithermal neutrons are mostly sensitive to H
   abundance. Fast neutrons can provide a good measure of average
   atomic mass. For the MESSENGER mission, the NS sensor will
   establish and map the abundance of H over most of the northern
   hemisphere of Mercury, providing significant new information
   regarding the potential presence of water ice within and near
   permanently shaded craters near the north pole.
 
   The GRS detector is described in the catalog file GRS_INST.CAT in
   the GRS archive. Both instruments are described in full detail in
   [GOLDSTENETAL2007].

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
