<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:xrs.mess</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>XRAY SPECTROMETER for MESS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mess::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Schlemm, C.E., II, R.D. Starr, G.C. Ho, K.E. Bechtold, S.A. Benedict, J.D.
                   Boldt, W.V. Boynton, W. Bradley, M.E. Fraeman, R.E. Gold, J.O. Goldsten, J.R.
                   Hayes, S.E. Jaskulek, E. Rossano, R.A. Rumpf, E.D. Schaefer, K. Strohbehn, R.G.
                   Shelton, R.E. Thompson, J.I. Trombka, and B.D. Williams, The X-Ray Spectrometer
                   on the MESSENGER spacecraft, Space Science Reviews, 131, 393-415, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.SCHLEMMETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>XRAY SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Xray Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    The Mercury Surface, Space Environment, Geochemistry and Ranging
    (MESSENGER) mission is designed to orbit Mercury following one Earth
    flyby, two flybys of Venus and three of Mercury.  It launched in
    August 2004 and will use these flybys to achieve an orbit insertion
    around Mercury in March 2011.  Initial data collection will begin
    during the three flybys of Mercury, and will primarily consist of
    global mapping and measurements of the surface, atmosphere and
    magnetosphere composition.  MESSENGER will remain in orbit for the
    rest of the nominal mission, which is scheduled to end in March
    2012. Once in orbit around Mercury it will begin a series of
    observations using multiple instruments. These observations will
    provide data to answer questions about the nature and composition of
    Mercury&apos;s crust, tectonic history, the structure of the atmosphere
    and magnetosphere, and the nature of the polar caps.
 
    The X-Ray Spectrometer (XRS) experiment is comprised of three
    identical gas proportional counters (GPC) that measure X-rays
    emitted from the surface of Mercury in the energy range from about 1
    to 10 keV.  X-rays in this energy range sample the planetary surface
    to depths of a few tens of microns.  The GPCs each have a 10-cm2
    active area and use both anti-coincidence wires and pulse shape
    discrimination to minimize background.  Balanced filters are used to
    resolve the lower energy X-ray lines from Mg, Al, and Si.  This
    technique has been used previously on other orbital X-ray
    experiments flown on the Apollo 15, 16 and NEAR-Shoemaker missions.
    One GPC has a thin aluminum filter, which filters out Si photons,
    one has a thin Mg filter, which filters out Al and Si photons, and
    the third GPC has no filter.  The energy resolution of the gas
    counters is sufficient to resolve the higher energy lines from S,
    Ca, Ti, and Fe.  A small Si- PIN detector is used as a solar
    monitor, because the Sun is the source of the planetary X-ray
    fluorescence.  The field-of-view (FOV) of the GPCs is 12 degrees.
 
    Both the GPCs and the Si-PIN detector count individual photons,
    producing an electronic pulse that is proportional to the energy of
    the absorbed photon. Each valid count is stored in energy histograms
    (spectra) that are 244 channels for the GPC and 231 channels for the
    Si-PIN.  The accumulation time for these histograms will vary
    depending upon proximity to the planet.  At periapsis the
    accumulation time will be 40 seconds and at apoapsis 450 seconds.
 
    The XRS is comprised of three physical units.  The GPCs make up the
    Mercury X- ray Unit (MXU).   The Solar Assembly for X-rays (SAX)
    includes the Si-PIN diode, preamplifier, shaping electronics and
    thermal electric cooler (TEC).  The analog and digital electronics
    are contained in the Main Electronics for X-rays (MEX) unit.  The
    SAX is located at the &apos;&apos;top center&apos;&apos; edge of the solar shield (see
    Figure 1 in the XRS EDR SIS document).  The MXU and MEX are
    co-located within the payload adapter ring.
 
    The XRS instrument is described in full detail in [SCHLEMMETAL2007].

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
