<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mla.mess</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MERCURY LASER ALTIMETER for MESS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mess::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Cavanaugh, J.F., J.C. Smith, X. Sun, A.E. Bartels, L. Ramos- Izquierdo, D.J.
                   Krebs, A.M. Novo-Gradac, J.F. McGarry, R. Trunzo, J.L. Britt, J. Karsh, R.B.
                   Katz, A. Lukemire, R. Szymkiewicz, D.L. Berry, J.P. Swinski, G.A. Neumann, M.T.
                   Zuber, and D.E. Smith, The Mercury Laser Altimeter instrument for the MESSENGER
                   mission, Space Science Reviews, 131, 451-479, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CAVANAUGHETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MERCURY LASER ALTIMETER</name>
        <type>Altimeter</type> <!--RChen/EN was Laser Altimeter-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    The Mercury Laser Altimeter (MLA) is one of the primary instruments on
    NASA&apos;s MErcury Surface, Space ENvironment, GEochemistry and Ranging
    (MESSENGER) mission, under NASA&apos;s Discovery Program. MESSENGER, the first
    spacecraft ever to orbit Mercury, reached its destination following one
    Earth flyby, two flybys of Venus and three of Mercury.  It launched on
    3 August 2004 and entered Mercury&apos;s orbit on 18 March 2011. Initial
    data collection began during the three flybys of Mercury, continued during
    the orbital phases and consist of global mapping and measurements of the
    surface, atmosphere and magnetosphere composition. MESSENGER completed its
    mission on 30 April 2015 when it impacted into the planet as planned. The
    nominal mission consisted of one year in orbit, but the mission was
    extended to span more than four years in orbit. Once in orbit around
    Mercury it began a series of observations using multiple instruments. MLA
    ranged to the surface only during the periapsis of the 12-hour orbit,
    limited by its 1800-km maximum range. During the final months of the
    mission, the spacecraft altitude was reduced and MLA took measurements at
    altitudes as low as 25 km. See the CDR_RDR_DS.CAT file for more
    information on the lower altitude campaign and the MLA data collected at
    those times. MESSENGER&apos;s observations provided data to answer questions
    about the nature and composition of the crust, tectonic history, the
    structure of the atmosphere and magnetosphere, interior structure, and the
    nature of the polar caps.
 
    The MLA is a bi-static system, meaning that it consists of separate
    transmitter and receiver systems. The transmitter uses a diode-pumped,
    Nd:YAG slab laser with passive Q-switching. The laser output is 20 mJ
    per pulse at 1064-nm wavelength. The beam pattern at the output of a 15X
    beam expander is roughly Gaussian, with 90% of its power lying within a
    divergence of 80 microradians. The laser electrical power consumption
    is 8.7 W, and its mass without the beam expander is 0.56 kg.
 
    The transmitter generates a 6-ns-wide laser pulse at 8 Hz intervals,
    and the instrument measures the time required for the light to reach
    the surface and return. The MLA data complements the visible and
    near-infrared imaging that will also be performed on Mercury. Unlike
    the imager, the MLA does not rely on solar illumination and can make
    measurements over the entire surface of Mercury including the night
    side. The MLA complements imaging because the direct range
    measurements enable unambiguous determinations of topography that
    will improve the interpretation of images. The MLA can also be
    operated as a laser transponder using the transmitter and receiver
    subsystems independently.
 
    The MLA range measurement unit (RMU) employs a unique APL-supplied
    &apos;Time-of-Flight&apos; (TOF) ASIC which uses on-chip signal propagation time
    to gauge the time interval between pulses and the next clock signal.
    It has the unique advantages of subnanosecond (0.4 ns) timing but
    without the need of high speed digital electronics. The RMU can time
    up to 15 pulses with less than 2 microseconds recovery time, which
    enables the receiver to lower its detection threshold to register
    weak signals in the presence of several false alarm pulses. On-board
    software rejects most of the false alarms and downlinks only the
    most likely range signals to earth. The RMU measures the distance
    between the spacecraft and the surface of Mercury with 10-cm
    precision. This allowed the science team to take detailed measurements of
    Mercury&apos;s shape and surface structure.
 
    The laser output is sensed by a diode pickoff, and its energy is
    recorded. A leading and trailing edge start pulse time is recorded
    by comparators within the range measurement unit (RMU), as well as
    the time of the reflected pulse, as described below. Return echoes
    are collected by an array of four refractive telescopes that are
    fiber-optic coupled into a single silicon avalanche photodiode.
    To accommodate surfaces of greater slope and roughness, the received
    signal is passed through each of three matched filters into separate
    comparators within the RMU. These filter channels have response
    times of 10, 60, and 270 ns. A sufficiently strong return pulse will
    trigger comparators on one of the three lower threshold channels
    (channel 1, 2, 3), whose arrival is measured by a common pair
    (leading, trailing edge) of TOF chips. Pulses that trigger
    a separate high threshold on the 10-ns channel (Channel 1
    high, also known as channel 0) are measured by an additional pair of
    TOFs. The combined detection of a single pulse at two thresholds will
    allow a solution for pulse energy and for the spread of an equivalent
    Gaussian pulse waveform. Thresholds are set independently for each channel
    by means of flight software (FSW) and programmable digital-to-analog
    converters, in response to changing numbers of noise counts issued by the
    comparators, so as to maintain a preset average rate of false alarms in
    the face of varying background illumination. One high-threshold return
    and up to 10 returns from low-threshold channels are returned by the FSW
    after signal processing. The FSW Science task tracks the surface so as to
    eliminate most noise returns, and outputs a variable-length packet.
    The RMU counts consist of coarse and fine times. Each of the six
    dedicated TOFs has a series of gates that generate a fine range
    count at the leading or trailing edge of a pulse. Thus each 200-ns
    interval generated by the 5 MHz clock is subdivided into
    approximately 500 subintervals of roughly 400 ps. Individual timing
    calibrations for each TOF are applied from a lookup table since each
    gate has a slightly different delay.
 
    Additionally, the MLA can perform active and passive radiometric
    measurements in a narrow spectral band centered at 1064 nm. The
    active measurement employs a dual-threshold measurement of pulse
    width to infer the area and width of the return pulse. The pulse
    area, together with a transmit energy monitor, provides the
    reflectivity of the target within a 0.08-mrad-diameter laser spot.
    Thus MLA may search for volatile deposits that exhibit high albedo
    within the permanently shadowed polar regions. Active measurements
    require sufficient signal to trigger the detector at both low and
    higher threshold settings on the lowest matched filter setting, 10
    ms. The passive measurement employs the noise counters and threshold
    settings on the detector subsystem to infer radiance from a
    0.4-mrad- diameter field of view. The passive mode is enabled in
    Science Mode, wherein the noise counts are summed over 0.5-s
    intervals. The Hardware Diagnostic packets may be enabled in Standby
    Mode to provide 8-Hz passive measurements.
 
    More details about the instrument can be found in [CAVANAUGHETAL2007].

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
