<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mgs.tes</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>THERMAL EMISSION SPECTROMETER for MGS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mgs::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Christensen, P.R., D.L. Anderson, S.C. Chase, R.N. Clark, H.H. Kieffer, M.C.
                   Malin, J.C. Pearl, J. Carpenter, N. Bandiera, F.G. Brown, and S. Silverman,
                   Thermal emission spectrometer experiment: Mars Observer mission, J. Geophys.
                   Res., 97, (E5) 7719-7734, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CHRISTENSENETAL1992</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>THERMAL EMISSION SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Thermal Infrared Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    The TES instrument consists of three sub-sections, the primary
    one being a Michelson interferometer that produces spectra from
    1700 to 200 cm-1 (~6 to 50 microns), at a spectral sampling of
    either ~5 or ~10 cm-1 [CHRISTENSENETAL1992].  The instrument
    cycle time, including collection of the interferogram, mirror
    flyback, and electronic reset, is 2 sec for 10 cm-1 (single
    scan) operation, and 4 sec for 5 cm-1 (double scan) operation.
    The interferometer includes a visible interferometer that is
    used to generate fringes which are used to control the linear
    drive servo and to determine position in the interferogram.
    This system uses two redundant neon lamps that produce an
    emission line at 703.2 nm for fringe generation and a continuum
    that is used for a quasi-white-light source for determination
    of zero path difference.  The finite size and off-axis position
    of the six detectors results in self-apodization and a spectral
    shift that is a function of both distance from the axis and
    optical frequency.  The resulting full-width half-maximum
    (FWHM) value is ~12.5 cm-1 for 10 cm-1 sampling at 200 cm-1 and
    15.4 cm-1 at 1650 cm-1.  For the corner detectors and at the
    highest frequency (shortest wavelength) there is a significant
    departure from the ideal, with a worst-case degradation to a
    FWHM of ~24 cm-1.  Because all of the response functions have
    the same area there is no loss in signal when viewing a smooth
    continuum scene like Mars.  However, there will be a slight
    loss in contrast of narrow spectral features due to broadening
    of the spectral width.  Because the self-apodization is
    considerable, the data will generally be used without further
    apodization.  Separate fast fourier transform (FFT) algorithms
    are used for the center and edge detectors in order to
    partially correct for the different spectral shifts introduced
    into these detectors.  As a result, the data generated by the
    two FFTs will have approximately the same frequency sampling.
 
 
   Table 1  TES Performance Characteristics
 
   Parameter                                Expected Performance
   --------------------------------------------------------------------
   NEDe in spectrometer channels            0.002 @ 270 K and 10 micron
   NEDT in spectrometer channels            0.04K @ 270 K and 10 micron
   NEDr in solar reflectance channel        0.1% of solar flux
   NEDT in thermal bolometric channel       0.1K @ 270K
   Spectral resolution                      5, 10 cm-1
   Spectral range                           200 to ~1600 cm-1
   Spatial resolution                       3 km
 
  (NEDT is the noise-equivalent delta temperature)
 
 
   Table 2  Design Parameters for the Thermal Emission Spectrometer
 
   Spectral Range
   --------------------------------------------------------------------
   interferometer                 200 to ~1600 cm-1 (6.0 -50 micron)
   radiometer                     5.5 to 100 micron and 0.3-2.7 micron
   Spectral resolution of         10 cm-1 and 5 cm-1
      interferometer
   Field of view (FOV)            16.6 mrad downtrack,
                                  24.9 mrad crosstrack
   Instantaneous Field of View    8.3 mrad square
      (IFOV)
   Telescope Aperture
      interferometer              15.2 cm diameter Cassegrain
      radiometer                  1.5 cm diameter off-axis reflecting
   Pointing mirror
      range                       90 forward, 90 aft
      step size                   ~ 0.25 mrad
   Detectors                      uncooled deuterated triglycine sulfate
                                  (DTGS) pyroelectric
      spectrometer channel:       6-element array; each 1.75 mm diam
                                    NEP = 3.01x10-11 W-Hz-1/2
                                    responsivity = 1000 V/W
      bolometer channels:         6-element array; each 1mm x 1mm
                                     NEP = 2 x10-11 W-Hz1/2
                                     responsivity = 1000 V/W
   Michelson mirror travel        +- 0.25 mm and +- 0.50 mm
   Mirror velocity                0.0295 cm/sec
   Neon fringe reference          703.2 nm
      wavelength
   Sample rate                    839 samples/sec/detector
   Cycle time per measurement     2 sec and 4 sec
   Number of samples per          1344
      interferogram
   Number of bits per sample      16
   Number of spectral samples     143, 286
   Number of bits per spectral    12
      sample
   Data bit rates                 668, 1664, 4992 bits/sec
   Size                           21.08 x 34.52 x 39.85 cm
   Mass                           14.47 kg
   Power                          10.6 Watts (ave.)
 
 
  Scientific Objectives
  =====================
    The scientific objectives of the Thermal Emission Spectrometer
    (TES) investigation include the following:
 
    (1) Determine the composition and distribution of surface
        materials.
 
    (2) Determine the composition, particle size, and spatial and
        temporal distribution of suspended dust.
 
    (3) Determine the location, temperature, height, and water
        abundance of H2O clouds.
 
    (4) Determine the composition, seasonal behavior, total energy
        balance, and physical properties of the polar caps.
 
    (5) Determine the particle size distribution of rocks and fines
        on the surface.
 
 
  Calibration
  ===========
    The TES instrument was radiometrically, spectrally, and
    spatially calibrated prior to delivery.  Three categories of
    calibration requirements were considered: absolute accuracy of
    all three bands, relative accuracy of spectral measurements
    within the spectrometer, and calibration stability over the
    lifetime of the instrument.  The spectrometer and thermal
    bolometric channels were calibrated in a thermal/vacuum chamber
    using blackbody reference sources operated over the expected
    Martian temperature range of 130 to &gt;310 K.  The calibration
    sequence was repeated for instrument temperatures over the
    operating temperature range.
 
    The solar reflectance channels were calibrated under ambient
    conditions using filament lamps traceable to National Institute
    of Standards and Technology (NIST) standards and a diffuser
    plate with known bidirectional reflectance distribution
    function properties.  Altering the distance from the lamps to
    the plate was used to vary the radiance over the expected
    dynamic range.  The absolute accuracy of the calibration was
    better than 5%.  This calibration was confirmed by measurements
    in the thermal/vacuum chamber over the expected instrument
    operating temperature range.
 
    The inflight radiometric calibration is performed using
    observations of space (zero level) and an internal blackbody
    (gain).  The instrument has an unobstructed view to space with
    the line of sight at 85 degrees from nadir in at least one
    direction, with an unobstructed half angle of 10.75 degrees on
    either side of this line of sight.  These calibration
    measurements allow the instrument response function and zero
    levels to be determined and removed from the measured spectra
    prior to transmission to Earth.  This calibration is performed
    internally to permit coadding of spectra from more than one
    detector and from more than one measurement.  The internal
    blackbody and lamp calibration sources will be viewed by
    rotation of the pointing mirror, providing a complete
    end-to-end system calibration.
 
 
  Operational Considerations
  ==========================
    None
 
 
  Detectors
  =========
    Each sensor array consists of uncooled deuterated triglycine
    sulfate (DTGS) pyroelectric detectors.  A narrow bandpass
    filter is used to isolate the emission line at 703.2 nm for
    fringe generation and the continuum is used for a
    quasi-white-light source for determination of zero path
    difference.  A silicon photodiode detector is used for each of
    these functions.
 
 
  Electronics
  ===========
    The outputs from all TES channels are digitized at 16 bits,
    processed, and formatted before being sent to the spacecraft
    Payload Data Subsystem (PDS).  The outputs of the
    interferometer receive the following processing within the
    instrument before transfer to the PDS:
 
    1) selectable apodization;
    2) Fast Fourier Transformation (FFT) of data from all six
       interferometer channels;
    3) correction for gain and offsets;
    4) data editing and aggregation;
    5) data compression; and
    6) formatting for the PDS.
 
 
  Filters
  =======
    None
 
 
  Optics
  ======
    The interferometer telescope is a reflecting Cassegrain
    configuration with a focal ratio of f/4 and an intermediate
    field stop which limits stray light from being admitted to the
    interferometer and aft optics sections of the optical system.
    The afocal output beam of the telescope is 1.524 cm in
    diameter.  After passing through the Michelson interferometer
    the energy is focused by an off-axis mirror on to a 2 x 3 array
    of field stops.  The focal ratio at the field stops is also
    f/4.  Behind each stop is a field lens operating at
    approximately f/1 and a pyroelectric detector.
 
    A separate 1.5-cm-diameter reflecting telescope, collimated
    with the main telescope and using the same pointing mirror, is
    used for the thermal and albedo radiometer channels.  The
    optical system consists of a single off-axis paraboloidal
    mirror operating at f/8.
 
 
  Location
  ========
    Payload deck of MGS (+Z panel), boresighted with MOC
 
 
  Operational Modes
  =================
    The overall science objectives of the TES experiment will be
    addressed during the standard mission through a variety of
    observation types.  These include:
 
    (1) nadir pointing observations of the surface and atmosphere
        collected along the spacecraft groundtrack,
 
    (2) surface mosaics constructed by observing a particular
        region forward, nadir, and then aft along the groundtrack,
 
    (3) limb observations produced by scanning the pointing mirror
        to and across the limb, and
 
    (4) emission phase functions produced by viewing a particular
        region at a limited set of emission angles fore and aft.
 
    In addition, the TES processor will operate in a wide variety
    of data collection and processing modes that will allow great
    flexibility in the types and data volume of observations that
    will be made.  Substantial on-board data processing is
    necessitated by data rate constraints.  A variety of observing
    modes will be used.  These will be based on:
 
    (1) combining outputs from selected combinations of detectors
        (spatial averaging),
 
    (2) retention of limited numbers of spectral points (spectral
        editing) and
 
    (3) averaging results over several instrument cycles (temporal
        averaging).
 
    Data modes will be selected, depending on position in the orbit
    and on scientific requirements, that limit the variable data
    flow into the internal TES buffer to an orbitally averaged
    level consistent with the telemetry rate.  Internal tables will
    be used to select between the possible operational modes.  For
    example, the full sampling rate can be utilized over the
    warmest region of the planet, whereas data can be spectrally
    and spatially averaged at night and over the poles to decrease
    the data volume while increasing the signal-to-noise ratio.
    Control of the instrument parameters and processor activities
    will be accomplished using an internal command language and
    internal tables to select between the possible operational
    modes.  These modes include control of the pointing mirror
    position and motion, spectral selection, spatial and temporal
    averaging and editing, and data compression.  The basic
    instrument parameters will be set for each two-second
    observation.  Sequences will be constructed to form a
    self-contained set of observations; for example, calibration
    observations followed by three minutes of nadir viewing.  Orbit
    Schedules will be constructed from a list of Sequences, each
    timed to begin at a specified time following the nighttime
    equator crossing.
 
    Two types of Schedules will run in parallel:
 
    1) a basic observing plan designed to be used repetitively; and
 
    2) a targeting Schedule to be used for specific, targeted
       observations that vary from orbit to orbit.
 
    Finally, a Mission Plan will be constructed and stored within
    the instrument.  It will contain the Schedules for the next 3
    to 18 days of operation.  Using this scheme the TES instrument
    can be controlled completely internally using minimum number of
    uplink commands, yet utilizing the full, inherent flexibility
    of a microprocessor-controlled instrument.
 
 
    Mapping Operations
    ------------------
      Because of the limited (9 km) cross-track FOV, the TES
      instrument will build up a global image using multiple
      orbits, with approximately 200 days required to obtain full
      coverage at the equator.  During the mission, the TES could
      observe each point on the equator three times and each point
      on the planet an average of 4.7 times.  Given the likelihood
      of dust obscuration during a substantial portion of the
      mission, this coverage may be significantly reduced.  It will
      therefore be necessary to acquire observations in a well
      defined, systematic manner.  Seasons of highest surface
      temperature will be chosen for surface compositional mapping,
      and opportunities provided by increased spacecraft data rate
      will be incorporated into the observing plan.  Observations
      of temporal phenomena, such as dust storms, polar cap growth
      and retreat, seasonal pressure variations, and atmospheric
      phenomena, will be incorporated into the basic plan and
      collected whenever possible.
 
 
    Nadir Observations
    ------------------
      The nominal TES operating mode will provide a nadir oriented
      view of the planet, utilizing all three of the cross-track
      IFOVs.  These observations will be assembled as part of the
      standard data reduction procedure into global maps of the
      surface observations.
 
 
    Emission Phase Angle Observations
    ---------------------------------
      Multiple emission angle observations will provide information
      on the scattering properties of the surface and atmosphere
      over regional areas.  Because of planetary rotation (0.24
      km/sec at the equator) it will not be possible to view
      exactly the same surface point at multiple emission angles on
      a single spacecraft revolution.  However, regional
      characteristics can be determined in one revolution and
      observations from different revolutions may be combined to
      refine surface photometric estimates.  Individual emission
      angle sequences will consist of 2-5 off-nadir views spaced at
      fixed angles.
 
 
    Surface Mosaics
    ---------------
      The TES instrument has the capability to construct mosaics up
      to 50 km wide by 110 km long from a single revolution with
      little loss of spatial resolution by utilizing the planetary
      rotation.  These observations will permit direct comparison
      with Mars Observing camera and Viking images, and will permit
      the study of regional features, such as dune fields, wind
      streaks, and polar lanes on a single orbit.
 
 
    Atmospheric Observations
    ------------------------
      A wide range of atmospheric observations will be accomplished
      using the TES instrument.  These utilize both limb scans and
      variable emission angle observations of the surface and
      atmosphere.  The observing strategy uses a combination of
      nadir sounding, fore and aft limb scans, and variable
      emission angle (nominally+-60 deg ) observations to allow
      retrieval of vertical temperature profiles, atmospheric
      aerosol characterization, determination of condensates in the
      north polar hood, measurement of water ice and vapor and
      possibly O3, pressure retrievals under high surface
      temperature conditions, and characterization of localized
      dust storms.
 
 
    Observing Strategy
    ------------------
      The TES flight software has been programmed with four default
      operating modes to allow data collection immediately upon
      instrument turn-on and in the event of an interruption in
      instrument commanding.  This illustrates the level of
      complexity and flexibility that can be programmed into the
      TES observing strategy.  A default mode has been designed to
      provide 28, uniformly spaced atmospheric limb observations,
      distributed in both fore and aft viewing directions.  In
      addition, it optimizes the data collection, with full
      spectral and spatial data obtained during the day, 6 x 9 km
      data at half spatial resolution collected over the poles, and
      12 x 9 km data at full spectral resolution collected at
      night.  Emission phase observations and limb occultation
      observations are also collected to permit characterization of
      polar ices, clouds, and the atmosphere.  Actual, mapping
      orbit observations will vary from this default case, in order
      to optimize seasonal viewing opportunities, but will probably
      maintain the basic structure outlined above.
 
 
  Subsystems
  ==========
    None
 
 
  Measured Parameters
  ===================
    Spectral radiance (spectrometer) - W cm-2 str-1/cm-1
    Integrated radiance (bolometer channels) - W cm-2 str-1
 
  Principal Investigator
  ======================
    Philip R. Christensen
    Arizona State University

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
