<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:xrs.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>XRAY SPECTROMETER for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adler, I., J.I. Trombka, J. Gerard, P. Lowman, R. Schamadebeck, H. Blodgett, E.
                   Eller, L. Yin, R. Lamothe, P. Gorenstein, and P. Bjorkholm, Apollo 15
                   Geochemical X-Ray Fluorescence Experiment: Preliminary Report, Science, Vol.
                   175, pp. 436-440, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ADLERETAL1972A</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adler, I., J. Gerard, J.I. Trombka, R. Schamadebeck, P. Lowman, H. Blodgett, L.
                   Yin, E. Eller, and R. Lamothe, The Apollo 15 X-Ray Fluorescence Experiment,
                   Proc. Lunar Sci Conf. 3rd, pp. 2157-2178, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ADLERETAL1972B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adler, I., J.I. Trombka, J. Gerard, P. Lowman, R. Schamadebeck, H. Blodgett, E.
                   Eller, L. Yin, R. Lamothe, G. Osswald, P. Gorenstein, P. Bjorkholm, H. Gursky,
                   and B. Harris, Apollo 16 Geochemical X-ray Fluorescence Experiment: Preliminary
                   Report, Science, Vol. 177, pp. 256-259, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ADLERETAL1972C</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Bielefeld, M., R. Reedy, A. Metzger, J. Trombka, and J. Arnold, Proc. Lunar
                   Sci. Conf. 7th, pp. 2661-2676, 1976.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BIELEFELDETAL1976</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Bruckner, J., M. Koerfer, H. Waenke, A.N.F. Schroeder, D. Filges, P.
                   Dragovitsch, P.A.J. Englert, R. Starr, J.I. Trombka, I. Taylor, D.M. Drake, and
                   E.R. Schunk, IEEE Trans. Nucl. Sci., NS-38, pp. 209-217, 1991.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BRUCKNERETAL1991</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Clark, B.E., J.F. Bell, F.P. Fanale, and D.J. O&apos;Connor, Results of the Seven
                   Color Asteroid Survey: Infrared spectral observations of ~50-km size S-, K-,
                   and M-type asteroids, Icarus, Vol. 113, pp. 387-402, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CLARKETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Goldsten, J.O., Johns Hopkins APL Technical Digest, Vol. 19, pp. 126-135, 1998.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GOLDSTEN1998</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Goldsten, J.O., R.L. McNutt, R.E. Gold, S.A. Gary, E. Fiore, S.E. Schneider,
                   J.R. Hayes, J.I. Trombka, S.R. Floyd, W.V. Boynton, S. Bailey, J. Bruckner,
                   S.W. Squyres, L.G. Evans, P.E. Clark, and R. Starr, Space Sciences Review, Vol.
                   82, pp. 169-216, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GOLDSTENETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Knoll, G.F., Radiation Detection And Measurement, Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, 1989.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KNOLL1989</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Starr, R., P.E. Clark, L.G. Evans, S.R. Floyd, T.P. McClanahan, J.I. Trombka,
                   J.O. Goldsten, R.H. Maurer, R.L. McNutt, Jr., and D.R. Roth, Radiation effects
                   in the Si-PIN detector on the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous Mission, Nuclear
                   Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A, Vol. 428, pp. 209-215,
                   1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.STARRETAL1999</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Trombka, J., S. Floyd, W. Boynton, S. Bailey, J. Bruckner, S. Squyres, L.
                   Evans, P. Clear, R. Starr, E. Fiore, R. Gold, J. Goldsten, and R. McNutt,
                   Compositional Mapping With The Near X-ray/Gamma-ray Spectrometer, J. Geophys.
                   Res., Vol. 102, pp. 23729-23750, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TROMBKAETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Yin, L, J. Trombka, I. Adler, and M. Bielefeld, X-ray Remote Sensing Techniques
                   For Geochemical Analysis Of Planetary Surfaces, Remote Geochemical Analysis:
                   Geochemical And Mineralogical Composition, C. Pieters and P. Englert (eds.),
                   Cambridge University Press, New York, NY, USA, pp. 199-212, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.YINETAL1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>XRAY SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
 
      The Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous mission (NEAR) was successfully
      launched on 17 February 1996.  NEAR was the first launch under
      NASA&apos;s Discovery Program, an initiative for small, low-cost
      planetary missions.  As the first spacecraft to orbit an asteroid,
      the NEAR mission will address fundamental questions about the
      processes and conditions relevant to planetary formation.
 
      The X-ray/Gamma-ray Spectrometer (XGRS) is one of several
      instruments on-board the NEAR spacecraft that will study Eros during
      one year of orbital operations beginning in February 2000. The X-ray
      and gamma-ray spectrometers that comprise the XGRS are independent,
      but complementary experiments.  In this document we focus on the X-Ray
      Spectrometer, its design, operation, calibration, and procedures for
      interpretation of the measurements to be made at Eros.
 
 
    History
    =======
      In February 1996, the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous (NEAR) mission
      was launched into space on a planned three-year cruise to the
      near-Earth asteroid, 433 Eros.  The NEAR spacecraft, the first in
      the Discovery mission program to be launched, was built by the John
      Hopkins University, Applied Physics Laboratory (APL).  The
      spacecraft will orbit Eros for one year and carries a group of
      remote sensing instruments including an X-ray and gamma-ray
      spectrometer system (XGRS).  Due to a problem with firing of the
      main rocket engine in December 1998, the rendezvous was delayed
      until February 2000.  The NEAR spacecraft will be the first
      spacecraft to orbit a body as small as Eros, which is estimated to
      be 33 km X 13 km X 13 km.
 
      From telescopic, radar, and other observations, it has been inferred
      that Eros is an S-type asteroid, one of the most common type of
      near-Earth asteroids.  It is not known whether S-type asteroids come
      from differentiated or undifferentiated parent bodies.  One of the
      prime mission science objectives is to obtain global elemental
      composition maps. These elemental composition results are needed
      with sufficient accuracy to enable comparison with major meteorite
      types. The results would also be used to assess the compositional
      heterogeneity of the asteroid and help to answer questions about
      differentiation.  The selection of X-ray and gamma-ray spectrometers
      for this mission was based on their ability to produce global
      elemental composition maps of the asteroid.  Gamma-ray measurements
      can determine the abundance of elements such as O, Si, Fe, Ti, Mg,
      K, Th, and U depending on the actual composition.
 
 
    X-Ray Spectrometer Overview
    ===========================
      The X-Ray Spectrometer (XRS) will measure characteristic X-ray
      emissions induced in the surface of the asteroid by the incident
      solar flux.  The K-alpha lines for the elements Mg, Al, Si, Ca, Ti,
      and Fe will be detected with spatial resolution on the order of 3 km
      when counting statistics are not a limiting factor.  These
      measurements can be used to obtain both qualitative and quantitative
      information on elemental composition.
 
      The X-ray spectrometer on the NEAR mission is a non-dispersive
      spectroscopic system.  In this approach, the incoming X-ray photon
      is absorbed by the detector material and a signal proportional to
      the absorbed energy is measured by the detector as a voltage pulse
      at the detector output.  An analog to digital conversion is then
      performed and the count is binned by &apos;pulse height&apos; or energy loss
      and a spectrum is obtained and telemetered to Earth.  From an
      analysis of the pulse height spectrum, elemental composition can be
      inferred.
 
      The choice among various types of X-ray detectors was strongly
      influenced by the constraints of the mission.  For the NEAR mission,
      the detectors were chosen for the sensitivity in the energy regions
      of scientific interest, while also being consistent with the cost,
      mass, power and reliability constraints of the mission.
 
      The most prominent fluorescent lines for the major elements Mg, Al,
      Si, Ca, Ti, and Fe are the K-alpha lines (1-10 keV).  The strength
      of these emissions from planetary surfaces is strongly dependent on
      the chemical composition of the surface as well as on the incident
      solar spectrum, but are of sufficient intensity to allow orbital
      measurement by detectors like those on the NEAR spacecraft.
 
      In addition to line fluorescence, solar X-rays also can be
      coherently and incoherently scattered from a planetary surface,
      contributing an unwanted background signal.  Astronomical X-ray sky
      sources, which could be sources of background, are eliminated at
      Eros, because the XRS is collimated to a 5-degree field of view and
      the asteroid completely fills the field of view when the spacecraft
      is below 100-km altitude.
 
      The solar flux from 1 to 10 keV, the energy region of interest, can
      be modeled with several prominent lines superposed on a continuum
      described by a fourth to sixth order power law (depending on the
      level of solar activity).  In modeling the solar output for the NEAR
      mission the best estimates of solar output anticipated near solar
      maximum have been used and range from approximately B1 to M1
      levels.  The solar intensity decreases by three to four orders of
      magnitude from 1 to 10 keV.  Fluorescent lines as well as the
      scatter-induced background, therefore, have greater intensity at
      lower energies.  As the level of solar activity increases,
      relatively more output occurs at higher energies, the slope of the
      spectrum becomes less steep, and the overall magnitude of the X-ray
      flux increases.  This process is called hardening.  Solar output is
      highly variable, and can typically change by an order of magnitude
      or more within minutes. Higher solar activity will yield better
      statistics, shorter integration times, and hence higher resolution
      maps, especially for heavier elements such as Fe.  Because of its
      variability, the Sun&apos;s output must be monitored in order to be able
      to obtain quantitative results.  An introduction to X-ray remote
      sensing techniques for geochemical analysis can be found in
      [YINETAL1993].
 
      Detectors
      ---------
       To detect X-rays in the 1 to 10 keV region, either solid state or
       gas proportional counter detectors can be used.  Cryogenically
       cooled Si(Li) detectors have good energy resolution in this energy
       region, but are ruled out by cost and mass limitations.  Recently,
       room temperature solid state detectors have been developed with
       reasonably good energy resolution, but only for detectors of
       limited size (~1 cm2).  Also, these detectors have no flight
       heritage.  The only detectors that satisfied all of the
       measurement and resource requirements for the NEAR mission are gas
       proportional counters.
 
       The asteroid-pointing detector package includes three large-area
       (25 cm2) sealed gas proportional counters with thin (25 ?m) Be
       windows.  The large area provides the necessary sensitivity to
       achieve the desired spatial resolution and the Be windows absorb
       the lower energy X-rays (below 1 keV) which would otherwise
       dominate the detector count rate.  The fill gas is P-10 (90% argon
       and 10% methane).  The Be window is supported by a rectangular Be
       support structure.  The detector housing is steel with a Be liner
       to absorb Fe line emission from the housing [GOLDSTENETAL1997].
 
       The sealed gas proportional counters chosen for this experiment
       are improved versions of instruments previously flown on Apollo 15
       and 16.  The energy resolution of current gas proportional
       counters is improved over those of the Apollo days, but is still
       not sufficient to resolve the low energy Mg, Al, and Si lines.  As
       with the Apollo missions it is necessary to use balanced filters
       to resolve these closely spaced lines [ADLERETAL1972A],
       [ADLERETAL1972B] and [ADLERETAL1972C].  Two of the detectors have
       thin absorption filters, 8.5  m thick, mounted externally.  A Mg
       filter on one detector attenuates the Al and Si lines, and an Al
       filter on the other detector attenuates the Si line.  The very
       steep absorption edges of the filters make the separation of the
       lower energy lines possible.  At higher energies, the filters are
       essentially transparent and the Ca and Fe lines are resolved
       directly by the detectors.  The third detector has no filter.  The
       energy resolution of these detectors is about 14.2% at 5.9 keV
       [TROMBKAETAL1997].
 
       Two sunward-pointing X-ray detectors positioned on the forward
       deck of the spacecraft monitor the incident solar flux.  The solar
       monitors experience very strong X-ray emissions directly from the
       sun, especially during solar flares, so the active area for a
       solar monitor needs to be only about 1 mm2.  One monitor is a
       proportional counter identical to the three asteroid pointing
       detectors, but with a specially designed graded shield that
       reduces its effective area to about 1 mm2 (Clark, Trombka, and
       Floyd, 1995 [CLARKETAL1995]).  The other solar monitor is a small
       Si-PIN photodiode.  This solid-state detector is mounted on a
       miniature thermo-electric cooler in a hermetic package 15-mm in
       diameter.  A 76 m thick Be window rejects the intense solar flux
       below 1 keV.  The Si-PIN solar monitor achieves an energy
       resolution of 600 eV FWHM at 5.9 keV.
 
       The accumulation times or integration periods for the XRS
       measurement can be adjusted by ground command and may vary from 1
       to 65535 seconds.  The default for orbital operations is 100
       seconds.  During each integration period the XRS collects four
       256-channel pulse height spectra: one for each of the three
       asteroid pointing detectors and one from either the proportional
       counter or the PIN solar monitor.  The two solar monitors may both
       be powered on at the same time, but telemetry limitations forced a
       design that allows only one of the solar monitors to be pulse
       height analyzed at a time.  Additional details of the detector
       design can be found in [GOLDSTENETAL1997].
 
       A collimator is used to restrict the X-ray spectrometer field of
       view to about 5 degrees.  In a 50-km orbit (on average about 40 km
       from the surface of the asteroid) this results in a spatial
       resolution of about 3 km.  The collimator is also useful in
       reducing the cosmic X-ray background.  The collimator uses a
       honeycomb design made of copper with 3% Be.  The K, L and M X-ray
       lines excited in the collimator by solar X-rays, cosmic rays and
       asteroidal X-rays do not interfere with the surface line
       emissions.
 
      Calibration Sources
      -------------------
       Three Fe-55 sources, mounted on a calibration rod, can be rotated,
       one at a time, into the field of view of the three asteroid
       pointing detectors to establish the energy calibration of the
       XRS.  Knowledge of the energy calibration of the XRS and how it
       changes over time is necessary to sum spectra obtained over the
       same region of the asteroid, but collected at different times
       during the mission.  The statistics in any one spectrum (typically
       about a 100-s accumulation) are insufficient to perform detailed
       analysis.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
