<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:msi.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MULTI-SPECTRAL IMAGER for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Hawkins, S. Edward III, E.H. Darlington, S.L. Murchie, K. Peacock, T.J. Harris,
                   C.B. Hersman, M.J. Elko, D.T. Prendergast, B.W. Ballard, R.E. Gold, J. Veverka,
                   and M.S. Robinson, Multi-spectral imager on the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous
                   Mission, Space Science Reviews, 82, 31-100, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.HAWKINSETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Murchie, S.L., M. Robinson, S.E. Hawkins III, A. Harch, P. Helfenstein, P.
                   Thomas, K. Peacock, W. Owen, G. Heyler, P. Murphy, E.H. Darlington, A. Keeney,
                   R. Gold, B. Clark, N. Izenberg, J.F. Bell III, W. Merline, J. Veverka, Icarus,
                   Vol. 140, No. 1, 66-91, 1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MURCHIEETAL1999</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MULTI-SPECTRAL IMAGER</name>
        <type>Imager</type> <!--RChen/EN was Camera-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  This catalog file contains excerpts from:
  [HAWKINSETAL1997]
 
  Additional MSI instrument information can be found in:
  [MURCHIEETAL1999]
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
  The Multi-Spectral Imager (MSI) on the Near-Earth Asteroid Rendezvous
  (NEAR) spacecraft uses a five-element refractive optical telescope,
  has a field of view of 2.93 x 2.25 degrees, a focal length of 167.35
  mm, and has a spatial resolution of 16.1 x 9.5 m at a range of 100 km.
  The spectral sensitivity of the instrument spans visible to near
  infrared wavelengths, and was designed to provide insight into the
  nature and fundamental properties of asteroids and comets. Seven
  narrow-band spectral filters were chosen to provide multicolor imaging
  and to make comparative studies with previous observations of S
  asteroids and measurements of the characteristic absorption in Fe
  minerals near 1 micron. An eighth filter with a much wider spectral
  passband will be used for optical navigation and for imaging faint
  objects, down to visual magnitude of +10.5. The camera has a fixed 1
  Hz frame rate and the signal intensities are digitized to 12 bits. The
  detector, a Thomson-CSF TH7866A Charge-Coupled Device, permits
  electronic shuttering which effectively varies the dynamic range over
  an additional three orders of magnitude. Communication with the NEAR
  spacecraft occurs via a MIL-STD-1553 bus interface, and a high speed
  serial interface permits rapid transmission of images to the
  spacecraft solid state recorder. On-board image processing consists of
  a multi-tiered data compression scheme. The instrument was extensively
  tested and calibrated prior to launch; some inflight calibrations have
  already been completed. For a detailed overview of the Multi-Spectral
  Imager and its objectives, design, construction, testing and
  calibration, see [HAWKINSETAL1997] Space Science Reviews 82, 31-100.
  The text in this data set catalog object has been extracted from this
  paper.
 
  Two major subassemblies make up the MSI instrument: a camera and a
  Data Processing Unit, or DPU. These two assemblies are physically
  separated by about 100 mm and are located on the aft deck of the NEAR
  spacecraft, with the camera&apos;s optical axis parallel to the X&apos;-axis of
  the spacecraft. A refractive optical telescope, a filter wheel, and a
  detector with its associated electronics are all part of the camera.
  The DPU provides a digital interface to the spacecraft and supplies
  power and the master timing to the camera.
 
 
  Camera Assembly
  ===============
  The camera specifications are summarized here:
 
  Mass:           Camera           3.7 kg
                  DPU              4.0 kg
  Power:          Camera           1.43 W
                  DPU              5.49 W
  FOV                              2.93 x 2.25 degrees
  Spectral Range                   400 - 1100 nm
  Refractive Optics                5 Elements
  Focal Length                     167.35 mm
  Clear Aperture (no cover)        18.6 cm^2
  Clear Aperture (with cover)      4.35 cm^2
  Frame Size                       537 x 244
  Frame Rate                       1 Hz
  Frame Size (no compression)      1.6 Mbits
  Quantization                     12 bits
  Exposure Control                 1 ms to 999 ms
  Filter Wheel                     8 Position
       Broadband (&apos;Clear&apos;)         700 nm
       Green                       550 nm
       Blue                        450 nm
       Red                         760 nm
       IR1                         950 nm
       IR2                         900 nm
       IR3                         1000 nm
       IR4                         1050 nm
 
 
  Data Processing Unit Assembly
  =============================
  The MSI Data Processing Unit (DPU) provides the necessary digital
  interface to the camera&apos;s FPD, and houses all of MSI&apos;s power
  converters, filter wheel control electronics, and the master clocking
  required by the camera. A microprocessor within the DPU receives
  commands from one of the two redundant spacecraft Command Telemetry
  Processors (CTPs). The CTP distributes commands, collects data from
  all instruments, and formats the data for recording and downlinking.
  Communication with the spacecraft takes place via a MIL-STD-1553 bus
  or alternatively through a high speed serial link (2 Mbits/s). Eight
  image buffers within the DPU allow temporary storage of the image
  data, permitting a variety of data compression algorithms to be
  applied to the data. Implementation of a multi-tiered compression
  scheme allows any algorithm to be applied to the data individually, or
  in combination. Both lossy and lossless compression algorithms are
  available. Images acquired and digitized by the camera are transferred
  to the DPU in parallel through a short harness.
 
  A 1 Hz timing signal from the spacecraft synchronizes commands from
  the DPU to the camera. Integration times may be commanded from 1 to
  999 ms, effectively varying the sensitivity of the instrument by
  nearly three orders of magnitude. Each full image is made up of 244 x
  537 pixels and contains a header of all the parameters associated with
  the image, including the time the image was taken, CCD temperature,
  exposure time, filter, data compression information, etc. The data are
  packetized within the DPU. In addition to the image data, each packet
  also includes information to locate its data within the overall image.
  This design minimizes data loss in the event of a single lost or
  corrupted packet.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
