<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rss.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>RADIO SCIENCE SUBSYSTEM for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Anderson, J.D., J.W. Armstrong, and E.L. Lau, Upper Limits for Gravitational
                   Radiation from Supermassive Coalescing Binaries, Astrophysical Journal, 408,
                   287-292, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ANDERSONETAL1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S.W., and R.G. Herrera, Radio Science Handbook, JPL D-7938, Volume 4,
                   Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 22 January 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ASMAR-HERRERA1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S. W., N. A. Renzetti, The Deep Space Network as an instrument for radio
                   science research, NASA Technical Reports Server, 1993STIN...9521456A, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ASMAR-RENZETTI1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S.W., R.G. Herrera, and T. Priest, Radio Science Handbook, JPL D-7938,
                   Volume 6, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ASMARETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Deep Space Network / Flight Project Interface Design Book, Document 810-5, Jet
                   Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.DSN810-5</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Estabrook, F.B., and H.D. Wahlquist, Response of Doppler Spacecraft Tracking to
                   Gravitational Radiation, Gen. Rel. Grav., 6, 439-447, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ESTABROOKETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   DSN Geometry and Spacecraft Visibility, Document 810-5, Rev. D, Vol. 1,
                   DSN/Flight Project Interface Design, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA,
                   1987.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GEO-10REVD</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Mars Global Surveyor Project, Telecommunications System Operations Reference
                   Handbook, Version 2.1 (MGS 542-257), JPL Document D-14027, Jet Propulsion
                   Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 1996.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.JPLD-14027</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Tyler, G.L., G. Balmino, D.P. Hinson, W.L. Sjogren, D.E. Smith, R. Woo, S.W.
                   Asmar, M.J. Connally, C.L. Hamilton, and R.A. Simpson, Radio Science
                   Investigations with Mars Observer, Journal of Geophysical Research, 97,
                   7759-7779, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TYLERETAL1992</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Woo, R., Spacecraft Radio Scintillation and Solar System Exploration, Wave
                   Propagation in Random Media (Scintillation), Society of Photo-Optical
                   Instrumentation Engineers, Bellingham, WA, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.WOO1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>RADIO SCIENCE SUBSYSTEM</name>
        <type>Atmospheric Sciences</type> <!--RChen/EN was Radio Science-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
      The Near-Earth Asteroid Rendezvous (NEAR) Radio Science
      investigations utilized instrumentation with elements on the
      spacecraft and at the NASA Deep Space Network (DSN).  Much of
      this was shared equipment, being used for routine
      telecommunications as well as for Radio Science.  The
      performance and calibration of both the spacecraft and
      tracking stations directly affected the radio science data
      accuracy, and they played a major role in determining the
      quality of the results.  The spacecraft part of the radio
      science instrument is described immediately below; that is
      followed by a description of the DSN (ground) part of the
      instrument.
 
 
    Instrument Specifications - Spacecraft
    ======================================
      The Near-Earth Asteroid Rendezvous spacecraft telecommunications
      subsystem served as part of a radio science subsystem for
      investigations of asteroids 253 Mathilde and 433 Eros.  Many
      details of the subsystem are unknown; its &apos;build date&apos; is taken to
      be 1995-02-01, the date on which acceptance testing began at
      Motorola.
 
      Instrument Id                  : RSS
      Instrument Host Id             : NEAR
      Pi Pds User Id                 : UNK
      Instrument Name                : RADIO SCIENCE SUBSYSTEM
      Instrument Type                : RADIO SCIENCE
      Build Date                     : 1995-02-01
      Instrument Mass                : UNK
      Instrument Length              : UNK
      Instrument Width               : UNK
      Instrument Height              : UNK
      Instrument Manufacturer Name   : Motorola
 
 
    Instrument Overview - Spacecraft
    ================================
      The spacecraft radio system was constructed around a
      redundant pair of X-band Cassini Transponders.
      Other components included two redundant power amplifiers,
      two redundant diplexers, two redundant microstrip patch low-gain
      antennas (LGA), one microstrip patch medium-gain antenna (MGA)
      providing a fan beam and one high-gain antenna (HGA) dish with
      a diameter of 1.5 m.
 
 
      The X-band capability reduced plasma effects on radio
      signals by a factor of 10 compared with previous S-band
      systems, but absence of a dual-frequency capability (both
      S- and X-band) meant that plasma effects could not be
      estimated and removed from radio data.
 
      The spacecraft was capable of X-band uplink commanding and
      simultaneous X-band downlink telemetry.  The transponder
      generated a downlink signal in either a &apos;coherent&apos; or a
      &apos;non-coherent&apos; mode, also known as the &apos;two-way&apos; and
      &apos;one-way&apos; modes, respectively.  When operating in the
      coherent mode, the transponder behaved as a conventional
      transponder; its transmitted carrier frequency was derived
      coherently from the received uplink carrier frequency with a
      &apos;turn-around ratio&apos; of 880/749.  The nominal coherent and
      noncoherent downlink frequencies were 8438.1 MHz and 8435 MHz
      respectively.
 
      The HGA was a 1.5 m diameter dish of a Cassegrain design that was
      directed in the spacecraft&apos;s +Z direction.  The gain was 40 dBic
      at 8.4 GHz (on Z axis).  The 3 dB beamwith was 1.7 degrees. The
      MGA had a maximum gain of 18 dBic at 8.4 GHz (on Z axis) with a 3
      dB beamwith of 8 x 40 degrees.  The two LGAs were mounted forward
      and aft with their axes pointing in the +Z and -Z directions
      respectively.  These LGAs had a gain of +5 to -10 dBic at 8.4 GHz
      over the hemispheric field of view.  The MGA had a single
      polarization while the HGA and the two LGAs had dual, selectable,
      circular polarizations.
 
      NEAR telemetry data were sent to Earth at rates between
      9 bits per second (bps) and 26.5 kilobits per second (kbps).
      Uplink data rates were either 7 or 125 bps.
 
 
 
    Science Objectives
    ==================
      The science objectives of this investigation were to determine the
      mass of Eros to better than 0.1%, to determine the bulk density of
      Eros to an accuracy level commensurate with the accuracy of the
      volume determination (~1%), and to investigate the interior
      homogeneity of the asteroid by determining high order gravity
      fields from the shape models and comparing these models with those
      determined directly from the spacecraft tracking data.  Additional
      science objectives included the determination of the asteroid&apos;s
      moment of inertia matrix and its rotation state, placing upper
      limits upon any outgassing that may have occurred during its 100-
      year observational history, and determining the masses and orbits
      of any satellites discovered in orbit about Eros.
 
      During the 1997 June 27 NEAR spacecraft flyby of asteroid 253
      Mathilde, the Doppler and range tracking data was used to solve
      for the mass of this asteroid.  In combination with the volume
      estimate provided by the imaging team, the asteroid&apos;s bulk density
      (1.3 g/cm3) was determined [YEOMANSETAL1997].
 
      The radio science objectives of this mission were more extensive
      than traditional gravity science for large solar system bodies and
      there were additional challenges to be overcome to meet
      those objectives.  For example, the figure of Eros was
      very irregular and traditional spherical harmonics were no
      longer the obvious choice for gravity field analyses.  In
      addition, the rotation state of the asteroid was not well known
      prior to the spacecraft&apos;s arrival and the spacecraft orbits about
      the asteroid were often near the plane-of-sky as seen from the
      Earth, thus limiting the power of the Doppler data to define the
      gravity field of Eros.  Because of these technical challenges
      and additional ones dictated by the short lead time before launch
      and the modest budget associated with Discovery class missions,
      the NEAR radio science team relied upon experienced personnel
      who had already been tasked with navigating the NEAR spacecraft
      during the approach and orbiting phases of the mission.  The
      success with which the NEAR Radio Science Team met its
      objectives depended upon a very close cooperative effort with the
      JPL Navigation Team.
 
 
    Operational Considerations - Spacecraft
    =======================================
      Descriptions given here are for nominal performance.  The
      spacecraft transponder system comprised redundant units,
      each with slightly different characteristics.  As
      transponder units age, their performance changes slightly.
      Their performance also depends upon factors which were not
      always under the control of the NEAR Project.
 
 
    Calibration Description - Spacecraft
    ====================================
      No information available.
 
 
    Platform Mounting Descriptions - Spacecraft
    ===========================================
      The spacecraft +Z axis vector was aligned with the HGA boresight
      perpendicular to the top surface of the spacecraft.  The +Y
      axis vector ran through the power switching electronics box
      and the +X axis completed the orthogonal, right-handed,
      rectangular coordinate system.
 
      The axes of the two low gain antennas were in the +Z and -Z
      directions.  The MGA boresight was along the +Z axis.
 
 
    Investigators
    =============
      Team Leader for the NEAR Radio Science Team was D.K. Yeomans
      of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL).  Members of the Team
      included Jon D. Giorgini (JPL), Alex Konopliv (JPL) and
      Jean-Pierre Barriot (CNES, France).  Addition collaborative
      efforts were provided by members of the JPL navigation team
      including B.G. Williams, J.K. Miller, P. Antreasian, C. Helfrich,
      J.D. Giorgini and mission design personnel from the Johns Hopkins
      University&apos;s Applied Physics Laboratory (R. Farquhar, D. Dunham,
      and J. McAdams).
 
    Instrument Section / Operating Mode Descriptions - Spacecraft
    =============================================================
      The NEAR radio system consisted of two sections, which
      could be operated in the following modes:
 
      Section      Mode
      -------------------------------------------
      Oscillator   two-way (coherent)
                   one-way (non-coherent)
      RF output    low-gain antenna (choice from two)
                   medium-gain antenna
                   high-gain antenna
 
 
 
    Instrument Overview - DSN
    =========================
      Three Deep Space Communications Complexes (DSCCs) (near
      Barstow, CA; Canberra, Australia; and Madrid, Spain) comprise
      the DSN tracking network.  Each complex is equipped with
      several antennas [including at least one each 70-m, 34-m High
      Efficiency (HEF), and 34-m Beam WaveGuide (BWG)], associated
      electronics, and operational systems.  Primary activity
      at each complex is radiation of commands to and reception of
      telemetry data from active spacecraft.  Transmission and
      reception is possible in several radio-frequency bands, the
      most common being S-band (nominally a frequency of 2100-2300 MHz
      or a wavelength of 14.2-13.0 cm) and X-band (7100-8500 MHz or
      4.2-3.5 cm).  Transmitter output powers of up to 400 kW are
      available.
 
      Ground stations have the ability to transmit coded and uncoded
      waveforms which can be echoed by distant spacecraft.  Analysis
      of the received coding allows navigators to determine the
      distance to the spacecraft; analysis of Doppler shift on the
      carrier signal allows estimation of the line-of-sight
      spacecraft velocity.  Range and Doppler measurements are used
      to calculate the spacecraft trajectory and to infer gravity
      fields of objects near the spacecraft.
 
      Ground stations can record spacecraft signals that have
      propagated through or been scattered from target media.
      Measurements of signal parameters after wave interactions with
      surfaces, atmospheres, rings, and plasmas are used to infer
      physical and electrical properties of the target.
 
      Principal investigators vary from experiment to experiment.
      See the corresponding section of the spacecraft instrument
      description or the data set description for specifics.
 
      The Deep Space Network is managed by the Jet Propulsion
      Laboratory of the California Institute of Technology for the
      U.S.  National Aeronautics and Space Administration.
      Specifications include:
 
      Instrument Id                  : RSS
      Instrument Host Id             : DSN
      Pi Pds User Id                 : N/A
      Instrument Name                : RADIO SCIENCE SUBSYSTEM
      Instrument Type                : RADIO SCIENCE
      Build Date                     : N/A
      Instrument Mass                : N/A
      Instrument Length              : N/A
      Instrument Width               : N/A
      Instrument Height              : N/A
      Instrument Manufacturer Name   : N/A
 
    Subsystems - DSN
    ================
      The Deep Space Communications Complexes (DSCCs) are an integral
      part of Radio Science instrumentation, along with the spacecraft
      Radio Frequency Subsystem.  Their system performance directly
      determines the degree of success of Radio Science
      investigations, and their system calibration determines the
      degree of accuracy in the results of the experiments.  The
      following paragraphs describe the functions performed by the
      individual subsystems of a DSCC.
 
      Each DSCC includes a set of antennas, a Signal Processing
      Center (SPC), and communication links to the Jet Propulsion
      Laboratory (JPL).  The general configuration is illustrated
      below; antennas (Deep Space Stations, or DSS -- a term carried
      over from earlier times when antennas were individually
      instrumented) are listed in the table.
 
          --------   --------   --------   --------   --------
         : DSS 25 : : DSS 27 : : DSS 14 : : DSS 15 : : DSS 16 :
         :34-m BWG: :34-m HSB: :  70-m  : :34-m HEF: :  26-m  :
          --------   --------   --------   --------   --------
              :            :     :             :          :
              :            v     v             :          v
              :           ---------            :     ---------
               ---------&gt;:GOLDSTONE:&lt;----------     :EARTH/ORB:
                         : SPC  10 :&lt;--------------&gt;:   LINK  :
                          ---------                  ---------
                         :   SPC   :&lt;--------------&gt;:   26-M  :
                         :  COMM   :         ------&gt;:   COMM  :
                          ---------         :        ---------
                              :             :            :
                              v             :            v
             ------       ---------         :        ---------
            : NOCC :&lt;---&gt;:   JPL   :&lt;-------        :         :
             ------      : CENTRAL :                :   GSFC  :
             ------      :   COMM  :                : NASCOMM :
            : MCCC :&lt;---&gt;: TERMINAL:&lt;--------------&gt;:         :
             ------       ---------                  ---------
                                                      ^     ^
                                                      :     :
                   CANBERRA (SPC 40) &lt;----------------      :
                                                            :
                     MADRID (SPC 60) &lt;----------------------
 
                          GOLDSTONE     CANBERRA      MADRID
             Antenna        SPC 10       SPC 40       SPC 60
            --------      ---------     --------     --------
            26-m            DSS 16       DSS 46       DSS 66
            34-m HEF        DSS 15       DSS 45       DSS 65
            34-m BWG        DSS 24       DSS 34       DSS 54
                            DSS 25
                            DSS 26
            34-m HSB        DSS 27
                            DSS 28
            70-m            DSS 14       DSS 43       DSS 63
            Developmental   DSS 13
 
 
      Subsystem interconnections at each DSCC are shown in the
      diagram below, and they are described in the sections that
      follow.  The Monitor and Control Subsystem is connected to all
      other subsystems; the Test Support Subsystem can be.
 
       -----------   ------------------   ---------   ---------
      :TRANSMITTER: :                  : : TRACKING: : COMMAND :
      : SUBSYSTEM :-: RECEIVER/EXCITER :-:SUBSYSTEM:-:SUBSYSTEM:-
       -----------  :                  :  ---------   ---------  :
             :      :     SUBSYSTEM    :       :           :     :
       -----------  :                  :  ---------------------  :
      : MICROWAVE : :                  : :      TELEMETRY      : :
      : SUBSYSTEM :-:                  :-:      SUBSYSTEM      :-
       -----------   ------------------   ---------------------  :
             :                                                   :
       -----------    -----------    ---------   --------------  :
      :  ANTENNA  :  :  MONITOR  :  :   TEST  : :    DIGITAL   : :
      : SUBSYSTEM :  :AND CONTROL:  : SUPPORT : :COMMUNICATIONS:-
       -----------   : SUBSYSTEM :  :SUBSYSTEM: :   SUBSYSTEM  :
                      -----------    ---------   --------------
 
 
      DSCC Monitor and Control Subsystem
      ----------------------------------
        The DSCC Monitor and Control Subsystem (DMC) is part of the
        Monitor and Control System (MON) which also includes the
        ground communications Central Communications Terminal and the
        Network Operations Control Center (NOCC) Monitor and Control
        Subsystem.  The DMC is the center of activity at a DSCC.  The
        DMC receives and archives most of the information from the
        NOCC needed by the various DSCC subsystems during their
        operation.  Control of most of the DSCC subsystems, as well
        as the handling and displaying of any responses to control
        directives and configuration and status information received
        from each of the subsystems, is done through the DMC.  The
        effect of this is to centralize the control, display, and
        archiving functions necessary to operate a DSCC.
        Communication among the various subsystems is done using a
        Local Area Network (LAN) hooked up to each subsystem via a
        network interface unit (NIU).
 
        DMC operations are divided into two separate areas: the
        Complex Monitor and Control (CMC) and the Link Monitor and
        Control (LMC).  The primary purpose of the CMC processor for
        Radio Science support is to receive and store all predict
        sets transmitted from NOCC such as Radio Science, antenna
        pointing, tracking, receiver, and uplink predict sets and
        then, at a later time, to distribute them to the appropriate
        subsystems via the LAN.  Those predict sets can be stored in
        the CMC for a maximum of three days under normal conditions.
        The CMC also receives, processes, and displays event/alarm
        messages; maintains an operator log; and produces tape labels
        for the DSP.  Assignment and configuration of the LMCs is
        done through the CMC; to a limited degree the CMC can perform
        some of the functions performed by the LMC.  There are two
        CMCs (one on-line and one backup) and three LMCs at each DSCC
        The backup CMC can function as an additional LMC if
        necessary.
 
        The LMC processor provides the operator interface for monitor
        and control of a link -- a group of equipment required to
        support a spacecraft pass.  For Radio Science, a link might
        include the DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem (DSP) (which,
        in turn, can control the SSI), or the Tracking Subsystem.
        The LMC also maintains an operator log which includes
        operator directives and subsystem responses.  One important
        Radio Science specific function that the LMC performs is
        receipt and transmission of the system temperature and signal
        level data from the PPM for display at the LMC console and
        for inclusion in Monitor blocks.  These blocks are recorded
        on magnetic tape as well as appearing in the Mission Control
        and Computing Center (MCCC) displays.  The LMC is required to
        operate without interruption for the duration of the Radio
        Science data acquisition period.
 
        The Area Routing Assembly (ARA), which is part of the Digital
        Communications Subsystem, controls all data communication
        between the stations and JPL.  The ARA receives all required
        data and status messages from the LMC/CMC and can record them
        to tape as well as transmit them to JPL via data lines.  The
        ARA also receives predicts and other data from JPL and passes
        them on to the CMC.
 
 
      DSCC Antenna Mechanical Subsystem
      ---------------------------------
        Multi-mission Radio Science activities require support from
        the 70-m, 34-m HEF, and 34-m BWG antenna subnets.  The
        antennas at each DSCC function as large-aperture collectors
        which, by double reflection, cause the incoming radio
        frequency (RF) energy to enter the feed horns.  The large
        collecting surface of the antenna focuses the incoming energy
        onto a subreflector, which is adjustable in both axial and
        angular position.  These adjustments are made to correct for
        gravitational deformation of the antenna as it moves between
        zenith and the horizon; the deformation can be as large as
        5 cm.  The subreflector adjustments optimize the channeling
        of energy from the primary reflector to the subreflector
        and then to the feed horns.  The 70-m and 34-m HEF antennas
        have &apos;shaped&apos; primary and secondary reflectors, with forms
        that are modified paraboloids.  This customization allows
        more uniform illumination of one reflector by another.  The
        BWG reflector shape is ellipsoidal.
 
        On the 70-m antennas, the subreflector directs
        received energy from the antenna onto a dichroic plate, a
        device which reflects S-band energy to the S-band feed horn
        and passes X-band energy through to the X-band feed horn.  In
        the 34-m HEF, there is one &apos;common aperture feed,&apos; which
        accepts both frequencies without requiring a dichroic plate.
        In the 34-m BWG, a series of small mirrors (approximately 2.5
        meters in diameter) directs microwave energy from the
        subreflector region to a collection area at the base of
        the antenna -- typically in a pedestal room.  A retractable
        dichroic reflector separates S- and X-band on some BWG
        antennas or X- and Ka-band on others.  RF energy to be
        transmitted into space by the horns is focused by the
        reflectors into narrow cylindrical beams, pointed with high
        precision (either to the dichroic plate or directly to the
        subreflector) by a series of drive motors and gear trains
        that can rotate the movable components and their support
        structures.
 
        The different antennas can be pointed by several means.  Two
        pointing modes commonly used during tracking passes are
        CONSCAN and &apos;blind pointing.&apos; With CONSCAN enabled and a
        closed loop receiver locked to a spacecraft signal, the
        system tracks the radio source by conically scanning around
        its position in the sky.  Pointing angle adjustments are
        computed from signal strength information (feedback) supplied
        by the receiver.  In this mode the Antenna Pointing Assembly
        (APA) generates a circular scan pattern which is sent to the
        Antenna Control System (ACS).  The ACS adds the scan pattern
        to the corrected pointing angle predicts.  Software in the
        receiver-exciter controller computes the received signal
        level and sends it to the APA.  The correlation of scan
        position with the received signal level variations allows the
        APA to compute offset changes which are sent to the ACS.
        Thus, within the capability of the closed-loop control
        system, the scan center is pointed precisely at the apparent
        direction of the spacecraft signal source.  An additional
        function of the APA is to provide antenna position angles and
        residuals, antenna control mode/status information, and
        predict-correction parameters to the Area Routing Assembly
        (ARA) via the LAN, which then sends this information to JPL
        via the Ground Communications Facility (GCF) for antenna
        status monitoring.
 
        During periods when excessive signal level dynamics or low
        received signal levels are expected (e.g., during an
        occultation experiment), CONSCAN should not be used.  Under
        these conditions, blind pointing (CONSCAN OFF) is used, and
        pointing angle adjustments are based on a predetermined
        Systematic Error Correction (SEC) model.
 
        Independent of CONSCAN state, subreflector motion in at least
        the z-axis may introduce phase variations into the received
        Radio Science data.  For that reason, during certain
        experiments, the subreflector in the 70-m and 34-m HEFs may
        be frozen in the z-axis at a position (often based on
        elevation angle) selected to minimize phase change and signal
        degradation.  This can be done via Operator Control Inputs
        (OCIs) from the LMC to the Subreflector Controller (SRC)
        which resides in the alidade room of the antennas.  The SRC
        passes the commands to motors that drive the subreflector to
        the desired position.
 
        Pointing angles for all antenna types are computed by
        the NOCC Support System (NSS) from an ephemeris provided by
        the flight project.  These predicts are received and archived
        by the CMC.  Before each track, they are transferred to the
        APA, which transforms the direction cosines of the predicts
        into AZ-EL coordinates.  The LMC operator then downloads the
        antenna predict points to the antenna-mounted ACS computer
        along with a selected SEC model.  The pointing predicts
        consist of time-tagged AZ-EL points at selected time intervals
        along with polynomial coefficients for interpolation between
        points.
 
        The ACS automatically interpolates the predict points,
        corrects the pointing predicts for refraction and
        subreflector position, and adds the proper systematic error
        correction and any manually entered antenna offsets.  The ACS
        then sends angular position commands for each axis at the
        rate of one per second.  In the 70-m and 34-m HEF, rate
        commands are generated from the position commands at the
        servo controller and are subsequently used to steer the
        antenna.
 
        When not using binary predicts (the routine mode for
        spacecraft tracking), the antennas can be pointed using
        &apos;planetary mode&apos; -- a simpler mode which uses right ascension
        (RA) and declination (DEC) values.  These change very slowly
        with respect to the celestial frame.  Values are provided to
        the station in text form for manual entry.  The ACS
        quadratically interpolates among three RA and DEC points
        which are on one-day centers.
 
        A third pointing mode -- sidereal -- is available for
        tracking radio sources fixed with respect to the celestial
        frame.
 
        Regardless of the pointing mode being used, a 70-m antenna
        has a special high-accuracy pointing capability called
        &apos;precision&apos; mode.  A pointing control loop derives the
        main AZ-EL pointing servo drive error signals from a two-
        axis autocollimator mounted on the Intermediate Reference
        Structure.  The autocollimator projects a light beam to a
        precision mirror mounted on the Master Equatorial drive
        system, a much smaller structure, independent of the main
        antenna, which is exactly positioned in HA and DEC with shaft
        encoders.  The autocollimator detects elevation/cross-
        elevation errors between the two reference surfaces by
        measuring the angular displacement of the reflected light
        beam.  This error is compensated for in the antenna servo by
        moving the antenna in the appropriate AZ-EL direction.
        Pointing accuracies of 0.004 degrees (15 arc seconds) are
        possible in &apos;precision&apos; mode.  The &apos;precision&apos; mode is not
        available on 34-m antennas -- nor is it needed, since their
        beamwidths are twice as large as on the 70-m antennas.
 
 
      DSCC Antenna Microwave Subsystem
      --------------------------------
        70-m Antennas: Each 70-m antenna has three feed cones
        installed in a structure at the center of the main reflector.
        The feeds are positioned 120 degrees apart on a circle.
        Selection of the feed is made by rotation of the
        subreflector.  A dichroic mirror assembly, half on the S-band
        cone and half on the X-band cone, permits simultaneous use of
        the S- and X-band frequencies.  The third cone is devoted to
        R&amp;D and more specialized work.
 
        The Antenna Microwave Subsystem (AMS) accepts the received S-
        and X-band signals at the feed horn and transmits them
        through polarizer plates to an orthomode transducer.  The
        polarizer plates are adjusted so that the signals are
        directed to a pair of redundant amplifiers for each
        frequency, thus allowing simultaneous reception of signals in
        two orthogonal polarizations.  For S-band these are two Block
        IVA S-band Traveling Wave Masers (TWMs); for X-band the
        amplifiers are Block IIA TWMs.
 
        34-m HEF Antennas:  The 34-m HEF uses a single feed for both
        S- and X-band.  Simultaneous S- and X-band receive as well as
        X-band transmit is possible thanks to the presence of an S/X
        &apos;combiner&apos; which acts as a diplexer.  For S-band, RCP or LCP
        is user selected through a switch so neither a polarizer nor
        an orthomode transducer is needed.  X-band amplification
        options include two Block II TWMs or an HEMT Low Noise
        Amplifier (LNA).  S-band amplification is provided by an FET
        LNA.
 
        34-m BWG Antennas: These antennas use feeds and low-noise
        amplifiers (LNA) in the pedestal room, which can be switched
        in and out as needed.  Typically the following modes are
        available:
           1. downlink non-diplexed path (RCP or LCP) to LNA-1, with
              uplink in the opposite circular polarization;
           2. downlink non-diplexed path (RCP or LCP) to LNA-2, with
              uplink in the opposite circular polarization
           3. downlink diplexed path (RCP or LCP) to LNA-1, with
              uplink in the same circular polarization
           4. downlink diplexed path (RCP or LCP) to LNA-2, with
              uplink in the same circular polarization
        For BWG antennas with dual-band capabilities (e.g., DSS 25)
        and dual LNAs, each of the above four modes can be used in a
        single-frequency or dual-frequency configuration.  Thus, for
        antennas with the most complete capabilities, there are
        sixteen possible ways to receive at a single frequency
        (2 polarizations, 2 waveguide path choices, 2 LNAs, and 2
        bands).
 
 
      DSCC Receiver-Exciter Subsystem
      -------------------------------
        The Receiver-Exciter Subsystem is composed of three groups of
        equipment: the closed-loop receiver group, the open-loop
        receiver group, and the RF monitor group.  This subsystem is
        controlled by the Receiver-Exciter Controller (REC) which
        communicates directly with the DMC for predicts and OCI
        reception and status reporting.
 
        The exciter generates the S-band signal (or X-band for the
        34-m HEF only) which is provided to the Transmitter Subsystem
        for the spacecraft uplink signal.  It is tunable under
        command of the Digitally Controlled Oscillator (DCO) which
        receives predicts from the Metric Data Assembly (MDA).
 
        The diplexer in the signal path between the transmitter and
        the feed horn for all three antennas (used for simultaneous
        transmission and reception) may be configured such that it is
        out of the received signal path (in listen-only or bypass
        mode) in order to improve the signal-to-noise ratio in the
        receiver system.
 
        Closed Loop Receivers: The Block V receiver-exciter at the
        70-m stations allows for two receiver channels, each capable
        of L-Band (e.g., 1668 MHz frequency or 18 cm wavelength),
        S-band, or X-band reception, and an S-band exciter for
        generation of uplink signals through the low-power or
        high-power transmitter.
 
        The closed-loop receivers provide the capability for rapid
        acquisition of a spacecraft signal and telemetry lockup.  In
        order to accomplish acquisition within a short time, the
        receivers are predict driven to search for, acquire, and
        track the downlink automatically.  Rapid acquisition
        precludes manual tuning though that remains as a backup
        capability.  The subsystem utilizes FFT analyzers for rapid
        acquisition.  The predicts are NSS generated, transmitted to
        the CMC which sends them to the Receiver-Exciter Subsystem
        where two sets can be stored.  The receiver starts
        acquisition at uplink time plus one round-trip-light-time or
        at operator specified times.  The receivers may also be
        operated from the LMC without a local operator attending
        them.  The receivers send performance and status data,
        displays, and event messages to the LMC.
 
        Either the exciter synthesizer signal or the simulation
        (SIM) synthesizer signal is used as the reference for the
        Doppler extractor in the closed-loop receiver systems,
        depending on the spacecraft being tracked (and Project
        guidelines).  The SIM synthesizer is not ramped; instead it
        uses one constant frequency, the Track Synthesizer Frequency
        (TSF), which is an average frequency for the entire pass.
 
        The closed-loop receiver AGC loop can be configured to one
        of three settings: narrow, medium, or wide.  It will be
        configured such that the expected amplitude changes are
        accommodated with minimum distortion.  The loop bandwidth
        (2BLo) will be configured such that the expected phase
        changes can be accommodated while maintaining the best
        possible loop SNR.
 
        Open-Loop Receivers: The Radio Science Open-Loop Receiver
        (OLR) is a dedicated four channel, narrow-band receiver which
        provides amplified and downconverted video band signals to
        the DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem (DSP); it sometimes
        goes by the designation &apos;RIV&apos;.
 
        The OLR utilizes a fixed first Local Oscillator (LO) frequency
        and a tunable second LO frequency to minimize phase
        noise and improve frequency stability.  The OLR consists of
        an RF-to-IF downconverter located at the feed , an IF
        selection switch (IVC), and a Radio Science IF-VF
        downconverter (RIV) located in the SPC.  The RF-IF
        downconverters in the 70-m antennas are equipped for four IF
        channels: S-RCP, S-LCP, X-RCP, and X-LCP.  The 34-m HEF
        stations are equipped with a two-channel RF-IF: S-band and
        X-band.  The 34-m BWG stations vary in their capabilities.
        The IVC switches the IF input among the antennas.
 
        The RIV contains the tunable second LO, a set of video
        bandpass filters, IF attenuators, and a controller (RIC).
        The LO tuning is done via DSP control of the POCA/PLO
        combination based on a predict set.  The POCA is a
        Programmable Oscillator Control Assembly and the PLO is a
        Programmable Local Oscillator (commonly called the DANA
        synthesizer).  The bandpass filters are selectable via the
        DSP.  The RIC provides an interface between the DSP and the
        RIV.  It is controlled from the LMC via the DSP.  The RIC
        selects the filter and attenuator settings and provides
        monitor data to the DSP.  The RIC could also be manually
        controlled from the front panel in case the electronic
        interface to the DSP is lost.
 
        RF Monitor -- SSI and PPM: The RF monitor group of the
        Receiver-Exciter Subsystem provides spectral measurements
        using the Spectral Signal Indicator (SSI) and measurements of
        the received channel system temperature and spacecraft signal
        level using the Precision Power Monitor (PPM).
 
        The SSI provides a local display of the received signal
        spectrum at a dedicated terminal at the DSCC and routes these
        same data to the DSP which routes them to NOCC for remote
        display at JPL for real-time monitoring and RIV/DSP
        configuration verification.  These displays are used to
        validate Radio Science Subsystem data at the DSS, NOCC, and
        Mission Support Areas.  The SSI configuration is controlled
        by the DSP and a duplicate of the SSI spectrum appears on the
        LMC via the DSP.  During real-time operations the SSI data
        also serve as a quick-look science data type for Radio
        Science experiments.
 
        The PPM measures system noise temperatures (SNT) using a
        Noise Adding Radiometer (NAR) and downlink signal levels
        using the Signal Level Estimator (SLE).  The PPM accepts its
        input from the closed-loop receiver.  The SNT is measured by
        injecting known amounts of noise power into the signal path
        and comparing the total power with the noise injection &apos;on&apos;
        against the total power with the noise injection &apos;off.&apos; That
        operation is based on the fact that receiver noise power is
        directly proportional to temperature; thus measuring the
        relative increase in noise power due to the presence of a
        calibrated thermal noise source allows direct calculation of
        SNT.  Signal level is measured by calculating an FFT to
        estimate the SNR between the signal level and the receiver
        noise floor where the power is known from the SNT
        measurements.
 
        There is one PPM controller at the SPC which is used to
        control all SNT measurements.  The SNT integration time can
        be selected to represent the time required for a measurement
        of 30K to have a one-sigma uncertainty of 0.3K or 1%.
 
 
      DSCC Transmitter Subsystem
      --------------------------
        The Transmitter Subsystem accepts the S-band frequency
        exciter signal from the Receiver-Exciter Subsystem exciter
        and amplifies it to the required transmit output level.  The
        amplified signal is routed via the diplexer through the feed
        horn to the antenna and then focused and beamed to the
        spacecraft.
 
        The Transmitter Subsystem power capabilities range from 18 kw
        to 400 kw.  Power levels above 18 kw are available only at
        70-m stations.
 
 
      DSCC Tracking Subsystem
      -----------------------
        The Tracking Subsystem primary functions are to acquire and
        maintain communications with the spacecraft and to generate
        and format radiometric data containing Doppler and range.
 
        The DSCC Tracking Subsystem (DTK) receives the carrier
        signals and ranging spectra from the Receiver-Exciter
        Subsystem.  The Doppler cycle counts are counted, formatted,
        and transmitted to JPL in real time.  Ranging data are also
        transmitted to JPL in real time.  Also contained in these
        blocks is the AGC information from the Receiver-Exciter
        Subsystem.  The Radio Metric Data Conditioning Team (RMDCT)
        at JPL produces an Archival Tracking Data File (ATDF) which
        contains Doppler and ranging data.
 
        In addition, the Tracking Subsystem receives from the CMC
        frequency predicts (used to compute frequency residuals and
        noise estimates), receiver tuning predicts (used to tune the
        closed-loop receivers), and uplink tuning predicts (used to
        tune the exciter).  From the LMC, it receives configuration
        and control directives as well as configuration and status
        information on the transmitter, microwave, and frequency and
        timing subsystems.
 
        The Metric Data Assembly (MDA) controls all of the DTK
        functions supporting the uplink and downlink activities.  The
        MDA receives uplink predicts and controls the uplink tuning
        by commanding the DCO.  The MDA also controls the Sequential
        Ranging Assembly (SRA).  It formats the Doppler and range
        measurements and provides them to the GCF for transmission to
        NOCC.
 
        The Sequential Ranging Assembly (SRA) measures the round trip
        light time (RTLT) of a radio signal traveling from a ground
        tracking station to a spacecraft and back.  From the RTLT,
        phase, and Doppler data, the spacecraft range can be
        determined.  A coded signal is modulated on an uplink carrier
        and transmitted to the spacecraft where it is detected and
        transponded back to the ground station.  As a result, the
        signal received at the tracking station is delayed by its
        round trip through space and shifted in frequency by the
        Doppler effect due to the relative motion between the
        spacecraft and the tracking station on Earth.
 
 
      DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem (DSP)
      ----------------------------------------
        The DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem (DSP) located at the
        SPC digitizes and records the narrowband output data from the
        RIV.  It consists of a Narrow Band Occultation Converter
        (NBOC) containing Analog-to-Digital Converters (ADCs), a
        ModComp CLASSIC computer processor called the Spectrum
        Processing Assembly (SPA), and several magnetic tape drives.
        Magnetic tapes containing DSP output are known as Original
        Data Records (ODRs).
 
        The DSP was originally operated through the LMC.  During
        1996-97 a remote operations capability was developed by the
        JPL Radio Science systems Group so that the DSP could be
        operated from JPL.
 
        Using the SPA-Radioscience (SPA-R) software, the DSP allows
        for real-time frequency and time offsets (while in RUN mode)
        and, if necessary, snap tuning between the two frequency
        ranges transmitted by the spacecraft: coherent and
        non-coherent.  The DSP receives Radio Science frequency
        predicts from the CMC, allows for multiple predict set
        archiving (up to 60 sets) at the SPA, and allows for manual
        predict generation and editing.  It accepts configuration and
        control data from the LMC (or remote operations console),
        provides display data to the LMC (or remote operations
        console), and transmits the signal spectra from the SSI as
        well as status information to NOCC and the Project Mission
        Support Area (MSA) via the GCF data lines.  The DSP records
        the digitized narrowband samples and the supporting header
        information (i.e., time tags, POCA frequencies, etc.) on
        9-track magnetic tapes in 6250 or 1600 bpi GCR format and/or
        on a local disk for later transmission to JPL.
 
        Through the DSP-RIC interface the DSP controls the RIV filter
        selection and attenuation levels.  It also receives RIV
        performance monitoring via the RIC.  In case of failure of
        the DSP-RIC interface, the RIV can be controlled manually
        from the front panel.
 
        All the RIV and DSP control parameters and configuration
        directives are stored in the SPA in a macro-like file called
        an &apos;experiment directive&apos; table.  A number of default
        directives exist in the DSP for the major Radio Science
        experiments.  Operators can create their own table entries.
 
        Items such as verification of the configuration of the prime
        open-loop recording subsystem, the selection of the required
        predict sets, and proper system performance prior to the
        recording periods will be checked in real-time at JPL via the
        NOCC displays using primarily the remote SSI display at NOCC
        and the NRV displays.  Because of this, transmission of the
        DSP/SSI monitor information is enabled prior to the start of
        recording.  The specific run time and tape recording times
        will be identified in the Sequence of Events (SOE) and/or DSN
        Keyword File.
 
        The DSP can be used to duplicate ODRs.  It also has the
        capability to play back a certain section of the recorded
        data after conclusion of the recording periods.
 
 
      DSCC Frequency and Timing Subsystem
      -----------------------------------
        The Frequency and Timing Subsystem (FTS) provides all
        frequency and timing references required by the other DSCC
        subsystems.  It contains four frequency standards of which
        one is prime and the other three are backups.  Selection of
        the prime standard is done via the CMC.  Of these four
        standards, two are hydrogen masers followed by clean-up loops
        (CUL) and two are cesium standards.  These four standards all
        feed the Coherent Reference Generator (CRG) which provides
        the frequency references used by the rest of the complex.  It
        also provides the frequency reference to the Master Clock
        Assembly (MCA) which in turn provides time to the Time
        Insertion and Distribution Assembly (TID) which provides UTC
        and SIM-time to the complex.
 
        JPL&apos;s ability to monitor the FTS at each DSCC is limited to
        the MDA calculated Doppler pseudo-residuals, the Doppler
        noise, the SSI, and to a system which uses the Global
        Positioning System (GPS).  GPS receivers at each DSCC receive
        a one-pulse-per-second pulse from the station&apos;s (hydrogen
        maser referenced) FTS and a pulse from a GPS satellite at
        scheduled times.  After compensating for the satellite signal
        delay, the timing offset is reported to JPL where a database
        is kept.  The clock offsets stored in the JPL database are
        given in microseconds; each entry is a mean reading of
        measurements from several GPS satellites and a time tag
        associated with the mean reading.  The clock offsets provided
        include those of SPC 10 relative to UTC (NIST), SPC 40
        relative to SPC 10, etc.
 
 
    Optics - DSN
    ============
      Performance of DSN ground stations depends primarily on size of
      the antenna and capabilities of electronics.  These are
      summarized in the following set of tables.  Note that 64-m
      antennas were upgraded to 70-m between 1986 and 1989.
      Beamwidth is half-power full angular width.  Polarization is
      circular; L denotes left circular polarization (LCP), and R
      denotes right circular polarization (RCP).
 
                           DSS S-Band Characteristics
 
                                         70-m     34-m     34-m
           Transmit                                BWG      HEF
           --------                     -----    -----    -----
           Frequency (MHz)              2110-    2025-     N/A
                                         2120     2120
           Wavelength (m)               0.142    0.142     N/A
           Ant Gain (dBi)                62.7     56.1     N/A
           Beamwidth (deg)              0.119      N/A     N/A
           Polarization                L or R   L or R     N/A
           Tx Power (kW)               20-400       20     N/A
 
           Receive
           -------
           Frequency (MHz)              2270-    2270-    2200-
                                         2300     2300     2300
           Wavelength (m)               0.131    0.131    0.131
           Ant Gain (dBi)                63.3     56.7     56.0
           Beamwidth (deg)              0.108      N/A     0.24
           Polarization                 L &amp; R   L or R   L or R
           System Temp (K)                 20       31       38
 
                           DSS X-Band Characteristics
 
                                         70-m     34-m     34-m
           Transmit                                BWG      HEF
           --------                     -----    -----    -----
           Frequency (MHz)               8495    7145-    7145-
                                                  7190     7190
           Wavelength (m)               0.035    0.042    0.042
           Ant Gain (dBi)                74.2     66.9       67
           Beamwidth (deg)                         N/A    0.074
           Polarization                L or R   L or R   L or R
           Tx Power (kW)                  360       20       20
 
           Receive
           -------
           Frequency (MHz)              8400-    8400-    8400-
                                         8500     8500     8500
           Wavelength (m)               0.036    0.036    0.036
           Ant Gain (dBi)                74.2     68.1     68.3
           Beamwidth (deg)              0.031      N/A    0.063
           Polarization                 L &amp; R    L &amp; R    L &amp; R
           System Temp (K)                 20       30       20
 
           NB: X-band 70-m transmitting parameters are given
               at 8495 MHz, the frequency used by the Goldstone
               planetary radar system.  For telecommunications, the
               transmitting frequency would be in the range 7145-7190
               MHz, the power would typically be 20 kW, and the gain
               would be about 72.6 dB (70-m antenna).  When ground
               transmitters are used in spacecraft radio science
               experiments, the details of transmitter and antenna
               performance rarely impact the results.
 
 
    Electronics - DSN
    =================
 
      DSCC Open-Loop Receiver (RIV)
      -----------------------------
        The open loop receiver block diagram shown below is for the
        RIV system at 70-m and 34-m HEF and BWG antenna sites.
        Input signals at both S- and X-band are mixed to approximately
        300 MHz by fixed-frequency local oscillators near the antenna
        feed.  Based on a tuning prediction file, the POCA controls
        the DANA synthesizer, the output of which (after
        multiplication) mixes the 300 MHz IF to 50 MHz for
        amplification.  These signals in turn are down converted and
        passed through additional filters until they yield output with
        bandwidths up to 45 kHz.  The Output is digitally sampled and
        either written to magnetic tape or electronically transferred
        for further analysis.
 
          S-Band                                          X-Band
         2295 MHz                                        8415 MHz
          Input                                            Input
            :                                                :
            v                                                v
           ---     ---                              ---     ---
          : X :&lt;--:x20:&lt;--100 MHz        100 MHz--&gt;:x81:--&gt;: X :
           ---     ---                              ---     ---
            :                                                :
         295:                                                :315
         MHz:                                                :MHz
            v                                                v
           ---     --                 33.1818       ---     ---
          : X :&lt;--:x3:&lt;------           MHz ------&gt;:x11:--&gt;: X :
           ---     --        :115          :        ---     ---
            :                :MHz          :                 :
            :                :             :                 :
          50:      71.8181  ---           ---                :50
         MHz:         MHz-&gt;: X :         : X :&lt;-10MHz        :MHz
            v               ---           ---                v
           ---               ^             ^                ---
          : X :&lt;--60 MHz     :             :      60 MHz--&gt;: X :
           ---               :   approx    :                ---
            :        9.9     : 43.1818 MHz :      9.9        :
            :        MHz      -------------       MHz        :
            :         :             ^              :         :
          10:         v             :              v         :10
         MHz:        ---       ----------         ---        :MHz
            :------&gt;: X :     :   DANA   :       : X :&lt;------:
            :        ---      :Synthesizr:        ---        :
            :         :        ----------          :         :
            v         v             ^              v         v
         -------   -------          :           -------   -------
        :Filters: :Filters:    ----------      :Filters: :Filters:
        :3,4,5,6: :  1,2  :   :   POCA   :     :  1,2  : :3,4,5,6:
         -------   -------    :Controller:      -------   -------
            :         :        ----------          :         :
          10:         :0.1                      0.1:         :10
         MHz:         :MHz                      MHz:         :MHz
            v         v                            v         v
           ---       ---                          ---       ---
10 MHz --&gt;: X :     : X :&lt;------ 0.1 MHz -------&gt;: X :     : X :&lt;--
           ---       ---                          ---       ---    :
            :         :                            :         :  10 MHz
            v         v                            v         v
         Output     Output                      Output     Output
 
 
        Reconstruction of the antenna frequency from the frequency of
        the signal in the recorded data can be achieved through use
        of one of the following formulas.  Filters are defined below.
 
   FSant=3*SYN+1.95*10**9+3*(790/11)*10**6+Frec        (Filter 4)
        =3*SYN+1.95*10**9+3*(790/11)*10**6-Fsamp+Frec  (Filters 1-3,5,6)
 
   FXant=11*SYN + 7.940*10**9 +   Fsamp - Frec        (Filter 4)
        =11*SYN + 7.940*10**9 - 3*Fsamp + Frec        (Filters 1,2,3,6)
 
       where
           FSant,FXant  are the antenna frequencies of the incoming
                         signals at S and X bands, respectively,
           SYN          is the output frequency of the DANA
                         synthesizer, commonly labeled the readback
                         POCA frequency on data tapes,
           Fsamp        is the effective sampling rate of the digital
                         samples, and
           Frec         is the apparent signal frequency in a spectrum
                              reconstructed from the digital samples.
 
              NB: For many of the filter choices (see below) the
                  Output is that of a bandpass filter.  The sampling
                  rates in the table below are sufficient for the
                  bandwidth but not the absolute maximum frequency,
                  and aliasing results.  The reconstruction
                  expressions above are appropriate ONLY when the
                  sample rate shown in the tables below is used.
 
 
    Filters - DSN
    =============
 
      DSCC Open-Loop Receiver (RIV)
      -----------------------------
        Nominal filter center frequencies and bandwidths for the RIV
        Receivers are shown in the table below.  Recommended sampling
        rates are also given.
 
                            S-Band                    X-Band
                   ------------------------  -------------------------
                   Output   3 dB   Sampling  Output   3 dB    Sampling
         Filter    Center   Band     Rate    Center   Band      Rate
                    Freq    Width            Freq     Width
                    (Hz)    (Hz)     (sps)   (Hz)     (Hz)      (sps)
         ------    ------  ------  --------  ------  ------   --------
            1         150      82      200      550      82        200
            2         750     415     1000     2750     415       1000
            3        3750    2000     5000    13750    2000       5000
            4        1023    1700     5000     3750    6250      15000
            5       75000   45000   100000   275000   45000     100000
            6       37500   20000    50000   137500   20000      50000
 
 
    Detectors - DSN
    ===============
 
      DSCC Open-Loop Receivers
      ------------------------
        Open-loop receiver output is detected in software by the
        radio science investigator.
 
 
      DSCC Closed-Loop Receivers
      --------------------------
        Nominal carrier tracking loop threshold noise bandwidth at
        both S- and X-band is 10 Hz.  Coherent (two-way) closed-loop
        system stability is shown in the table below:
 
            integration time            Doppler uncertainty
                 (secs)               (one sigma, microns/sec)
                 ------               ------------------------
                    10                            50
                    60                            20
                  1000                             4
 
 
    Calibration - DSN
    =================
      Calibrations of hardware systems are carried out periodically
      by DSN personnel; these ensure that systems operate at required
      performance levels -- for example, that antenna patterns,
      receiver gain, propagation delays, and Doppler uncertainties
      meet specifications.  No information on specific calibration
      activities is available.  Nominal performance specifications
      are shown in the tables above.  Additional information may be
      available in [DSN810-5].
 
      Prior to each tracking pass, station operators perform a series
      of calibrations to ensure that systems meet specifications for
      that operational period.  Included in these calibrations is
      measurement of receiver system temperature in the configuration
      to be employed during the pass.  Results of these calibrations
      are recorded in (hard copy) Controller&apos;s Logs for each pass.
 
      The nominal procedure for initializing open-loop receiver
      attenuator settings is described below.  In cases where widely
      varying signal levels are expected, the procedure may be
      modified in advance or real-time adjustments may be made to
      attenuator settings.
 
 
      Open-Loop Receiver Attenuation Calibration
      ------------------------------------------
        The open-loop receiver attenuator calibrations are performed
        to establish the output of the open-loop receivers at a level
        that will not saturate the analog-to-digital converters.  To
        achieve this, the calibration is done using a test signal
        generated by the exciter/translator that is set to the peak
        predicted signal level for the upcoming pass.  Then the
        output level of the receiver&apos;s video band spectrum envelope
        is adjusted to the level determined by equation (3) below (to
        five-sigma).  Note that the SNR in the equation (2) is in dB
        while the SNR in equation (3) is linear.
 
          Pn = -198.6 + 10*log(SNT) + 10*log(1.2*Fbw)              (1)
 
          SNR = Ps - Pn                               (SNR in dB)  (2)
 
          Vrms = sqrt(SNR + 1)/[1 + 0.283*sqrt(SNR)]  (SNR linear) (3)
 
           where    Fbw = receiver filter bandwidth (Hz)
                    Pn  = receiver noise power (dBm)
                    Ps  = signal power (dBm)
                    SNT = system noise temperature (K)
                    SNR = predicted signal-to-noise ratio
 
 
    Operational Considerations - DSN
    ================================
      The DSN is a complex and dynamic &apos;instrument.&apos; Its performance
      for Radio Science depends on a number of factors from equipment
      configuration to meteorological conditions.  No specific
      information on &apos;operational considerations&apos; can be given here.
 
 
    Operational Modes - DSN
    =======================
 
      DSCC Antenna Mechanical Subsystem
      ---------------------------------
        Pointing of DSCC antennas may be carried out in several ways.
        For details see the subsection &apos;DSCC Antenna Mechanical
        Subsystem&apos; in the &apos;Subsystem&apos; section.  Binary pointing is
        the preferred mode for tracking spacecraft; pointing
        predicts are provided, and the antenna simply follows those.
        With CONSCAN, the antenna scans conically about the optimum
        pointing direction, using closed-loop receiver signal
        strength estimates as feedback.  In planetary mode, the
        system interpolates from three (slowly changing) RA-DEC
        target coordinates; this is &apos;blind&apos; pointing since there is
        no feedback from a detected signal.  In sidereal mode, the
        antenna tracks a fixed point on the celestial sphere.  In
        &apos;precision&apos; mode, the antenna pointing is adjusted using an
        optical feedback system.  It is possible on most antennas to
        freeze z-axis motion of the subreflector to minimize phase
        changes in the received signal.
 
 
      DSCC Receiver-Exciter Subsystem
      -------------------------------
        The diplexer in the signal path between the transmitter and
        the feed horns on all antennas may be configured so
        that it is out of the received signal path in order to
        improve the signal-to-noise ratio in the receiver system.
        This is known as the &apos;listen-only&apos; or &apos;bypass&apos; mode.
 
 
      Closed-Loop vs. Open-Loop Reception
      -----------------------------------
        Radio Science data can be collected in two modes: closed-
        loop, in which a phase-locked loop receiver tracks the
        spacecraft signal, or open-loop, in which a receiver samples
        and records a band within which the desired signal presumably
        resides.  Closed-loop data are collected using Closed-Loop
        Receivers, and open-loop data are collected using Open-Loop
        Receivers in conjunction with the DSCC Spectrum Processing
        Subsystem (DSP).  See the Subsystems section for further
        information.
 
 
      Closed-Loop Receiver AGC Loop
      -----------------------------
        The closed-loop receiver AGC loop can be configured to one of
        three settings: narrow, medium, or wide.  Ordinarily it is
        configured so that expected signal amplitude changes are
        accommodated with minimum distortion.  The loop bandwidth is
        ordinarily configured so that expected phase changes can be
        accommodated while maintaining the best possible loop SNR.
 
 
      Coherent vs. Non-Coherent Operation
      -----------------------------------
        The frequency of the signal transmitted from the spacecraft
        can generally be controlled in two ways -- by locking to a
        signal received from a ground station or by locking to an
        on-board oscillator.  These are known as the coherent (or
        &apos;two-way&apos;) and non-coherent (&apos;one-way&apos;) modes, respectively.
        Mode selection is made at the spacecraft, based on commands
        received from the ground.  When operating in the coherent
        mode, the transponder carrier frequency is derived from the
        received uplink carrier frequency with a &apos;turn-around ratio&apos;
        typically of 240/221.  In the non-coherent mode, the
        downlink carrier frequency is derived from the spacecraft
        on-board crystal-controlled oscillator.  Either closed-loop
        or open-loop receivers (or both) can be used with either
        spacecraft frequency reference mode.  Closed-loop reception
        in two-way mode is usually preferred for routine tracking.
        Occasionally the spacecraft operates coherently while two
        ground stations receive the &apos;downlink&apos; signal; this is
        sometimes known as the &apos;three-way&apos; mode.
 
 
      DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem (DSP)
      ----------------------------------------
        The DSP can operate in four sampling modes with from 1 to 4
        input signals.  Input channels are assigned to ADC inputs
        during DSP configuration.  Modes and sampling rates are
        summarized in the tables below:
 
        Mode   Analog-to-Digital Operation
        ----   ----------------------------
          1    4 signals, each sampled by a single ADC
          2    1 signal, sampled sequentially by 4 ADCs
          3    2 signals, each sampled sequentially by 2 ADCs
          4    2 signals, the first sampled by ADC #1 and the second
                           sampled sequentially at 3 times the rate
                            by ADCs #2-4
 
             8-bit Samples               12-bit  Samples
            Sampling  Rates              Sampling  Rates
         (samples/sec per ADC)        (samples/sec per ADC)
         ---------------------        ---------------------
                 50000
                 31250
                 25000
                 15625
                 12500
                 10000                        10000
                  6250
                  5000                         5000
                  4000
                  3125
                  2500
                                               2000
                  1250
                  1000                         1000
                   500
                   400
                   250
                   200                          200
 
        Input to each ADC is identified in header records by a Signal
        Channel Number (J1 - J4).  Nominal channel assignments are
        shown below.
 
             Signal Channel Number        Receiver
                                           Channel
             ---------------------      -------------
                      J1                    X-RCP
                      J2                    S-RCP
                      J3                    X-LCP
                      J4                    S-LCP
 
 
    Location - DSN
    ==============
      Station locations are documented in [GEO-10REVD].  Geocentric
      coordinates are summarized here.
 
                            Geocentric  Geocentric  Geocentric
      Station              Radius (km) Latitude (N) Longitude (E)
      ---------            ----------- ------------ -------------
      Goldstone
        DSS 13 (34-m R&amp;D)  6372.125125  35.0660185   243.2055430
        DSS 14 (70-m)      6371.993286  35.2443527   243.1104638
        DSS 15 (34-m HEF)  6371.966540  35.2403133   243.1128069
        DSS 24 (34-m BWG)  6371.973553  35.1585349   243.1252079
        DSS 25 (34-m BWG)  6371.983060  35.1562594   243.1246384
        DSS 26 (34-m BWG)  6371.993032  35.1543411   243.1269849
 
      Canberra
        DSS 34 (34-m BWG)  6371.693561 -35.2169868   148.9819620
        DSS 43 (70-m)      6371.689033 -35.2209234   148.9812650
        DSS 45 (34-m HEF)  6371.675906 -35.2169652   148.9776833
 
      Madrid
        DSS 45 (34-m BWG)  6370.025429  40.2357708   355.7459008
        DSS 63 (70-m)      6370.051221  40.2413537   355.7519890
        DSS 65 (34-m HEF)  6370.021697  40.2373325   355.7485795
 
 
    Measurement Parameters - DSN
    ============================
 
      Open-Loop System
      ----------------
        Output from the Open-Loop Receivers (OLRs), as sampled and
        recorded by the DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem (DSP), is
        a stream of 8- or 12-bit quantized voltage samples.  The
        nominal input to the Analog-to-Digital Converters (ADCs) is
        +/-10 volts, but the precise scaling between input voltages
        and output digitized samples is usually irrelevant for
        analysis; the digital data are generally referenced to a
        known noise or signal level within the data stream itself --
        for example, the thermal noise output of the radio receivers
        which has a known system noise temperature (SNT).  Raw
        samples comprise the data block in each DSP record; a header
        record (presently 83 16-bit words) contains ancillary
        information such as:
 
         time tag for the first sample in the data block
         RMS values of receiver signal levels and ADC outputs
         POCA frequency and drift rate
 
 
      Closed-Loop System
      ------------------
        Closed-loop data are recorded in Archival Tracking Data Files
        (ATDFs), as well as certain secondary products such as the
        Orbit Data File (ODF).  The ATDF Tracking Logical Record
        contains 150 entries including status information and
        measurements of ranging, Doppler, and signal strength.
 
 
    ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS - DSN
    ================================
      ACS      Antenna Control System
      ADC      Analog-to-Digital Converter
      AGC      Automatic Gain Control
      AMS      Antenna Microwave System
      APA      Antenna Pointing Assembly
      ARA      Area Routing Assembly
      ATDF     Archival Tracking Data File
      AUX      Auxiliary
      AZ       Azimuth
      bps      bits per second
      BWG      Beam WaveGuide (antenna)
      CDU      Command Detector Unit
      CMC      Complex Monitor and Control
      CNES     Centre National d&apos;Etudes Spatiales
      CONSCAN  Conical Scanning (antenna pointing mode)
      CRG      Coherent Reference Generator
      CUL      Clean-up Loop
      DANA     a type of frequency synthesizer
      dB       deciBel
      dBic     dB relative to isotropic, circularly polarized radiator
      dBm      dB relative to one milliwatt
      DCO      Digitally Controlled Oscillator
      DEC      Declination
      deg      degree
      DMC      DSCC Monitor and Control Subsystem
      DOR      Differential One-way Ranging
      DSCC     Deep Space Communications Complex
      DSN      Deep Space Network
      DSP      DSCC Spectrum Processing Subsystem
      DSS      Deep Space Station
      DTK      DSCC Tracking Subsystem
      E        east
      EIRP     Effective Isotropic Radiated Power
      EL       Elevation
      FET      Field Effect Transistor
      FFT      Fast Fourier Transform
      FTS      Frequency and Timing Subsystem
      GCF      Ground Communications Facility
      GHz      Gigahertz
      GPS      Global Positioning System
      HA       Hour Angle
      HEF      High-Efficiency (as in 34-m HEF antennas)
      HEMT     High Electron Mobility Transistor (amplifier)
      HGA      High-Gain Antenna
      HSB      High-Speed BWG
      IF       Intermediate Frequency
      IVC      IF Selection Switch
      JPL      Jet Propulsion Laboratory
      K        Kelvin
      Ka-Band  approximately 32 GHz
      KaBLE    Ka-Band Link Experiment
      kbps     kilobits per second
      kHz      kiloHertz
      km       kilometer
      kW       kilowatt
      LAN      Local Area Network
      LCP      Left-Circularly Polarized
      LGA      Low-Gain Antenna
      LGR      Low-Gain Receive (antenna)
      LGT      Low-Gain Transmit (antenna)
      LMA      Lockheed Martin Astronautics
      LMC      Link Monitor and Control
      LNA      Low-Noise Amplifier
      LO       Local Oscillator
      m        meters
      MCA      Master Clock Assembly
      MCCC     Mission Control and Computing Center
      MDA      Metric Data Assembly
      MGA      Medium Gain Antenna
      MHz      Megahertz
      MON      Monitor and Control System
      MSA      Mission Support Area
      N        north
      NAR      Noise Adding Radiometer
      NBOC     Narrow-Band Occultation Converter
      NEAR     Near-Earth Asteroid Rendezvous
      NIST     SPC 10 time relative to UTC
      NIU      Network Interface Unit
      NOCC     Network Operations and Control System
      NRV      NOCC Radio Science/VLBI Display Subsystem
      NSS      NOCC Support System
      OCI      Operator Control Input
      ODF      Orbit Data File
      ODR      Original Data Record
      ODS      Original Data Stream
      OLR      Open Loop Receiver
      OSC      Oscillator
      PDS      Planetary Data System
      POCA     Programmable Oscillator Control Assembly
      PPM      Precision Power Monitor
      RA       Right Ascension
      REC      Receiver-Exciter Controller
      RCP      Right-Circularly Polarized
      RF       Radio Frequency
      RIC      RIV Controller
      RIV      Radio Science IF-VF Converter Assembly
      RMDCT    Radio Metric Data Conditioning Team
      RMS      Root Mean Square
      RSS      Radio Science Subsystem
      RTLT     Round-Trip Light Time
      S-band   approximately 2100-2300 MHz
      sec      second
      SEC      System Error Correction
      SIM      Simulation
      SLE      Signal Level Estimator
      SNR      Signal-to-Noise Ratio
      SNT      System Noise Temperature
      SOE      Sequence of Events
      SPA      Spectrum Processing Assembly
      SPC      Signal Processing Center
      sps      samples per second
      SRA      Sequential Ranging Assembly
      SRC      Sub-Reflector Controller
      SSI      Spectral Signal Indicator
      TID      Time Insertion and Distribution Assembly
      TLM      Telemetry
      TSF      Tracking Synthesizer Frequency
      TWM      Traveling Wave Maser
      TWNC     Two-Way Non-Coherent
      TWTA     Traveling Wave Tube Amplifier
      UNK      unknown
      USO      UltraStable Oscillator
      UTC      Universal Coordinated Time
      VCO      Voltage-Controlled Oscillator
      VF       Video Frequency
      X-band   approximately 7800-8500 MHz

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
