<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nis.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>NEAR INFRARED SPECTROMETER for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Acuna, M., C.T. Russell, L.J. Zanetti, and B.J. Anderson, The NEAR Magnetic
                   Field Investigation: Science Objectives at Asteroid Eros 433 and Experimental
                   Approach, Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol. 102(E10), pp. 23751-23760, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ACUNAETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   unk
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CHENG1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Farquhar, R.W., D. Dunham, and J. McAdams, NEAR Mission Overview and Trajectory
                   Design, Journal of Astronautical Science, Vol. 43, pp. 353-371, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.FARQUHARETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Izenberg, N.R., K. Peacock, J. Warren, S.L. Murchie, and J.F. Bell III,
                   In-flight calibration of NEAR&apos;s near infrared spectrometer, Proceedings of the
                   1998 SDL/USU Symposium on Infrared Radiometric Sensor Calibration, Space
                   Dynamics Laboratory, Utah State University, Logan, UT, USA, 1998.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.IZENBERGETAL1998</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   JHU/APL, NEAR Near Infrared Spectrograph/Magnetometer DPU Software Requirement
                   Specification, JHU/APL pub. 7357-9001 Rev. A, JHU/APL Space Department, Laurel,
                   MD, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.NISAPLSRS1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Peacock, K., Calibration of the Near Infrared Spectrograph, Proceedings of the
                   1997 SDL/USU Symposium on Infrared Radiometric Sensor Calibration, Space
                   Dynamics Laboratory, Utah State University, Logan, UT, USA, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.PEACOCK1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Trombka, J.I., W.V. Boynton, J. Bruckner, S.W. Squyres, P.E. Clark, R.
                   Starr, L.G. Evans, S.R. Floyd, E. Fiore, R.E. Gold, J.O. Goldsten, R.L.
                   McNutt, Jr., and S.H. Bailey, Journal of Geophysical Research 102, 23729,
                   1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TROMBKAETAL1997B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Veverka, J., J.F. Bell III, P. Thomas, A. Harch, S.L. Murchie, S.E. Hawkins
                   III, J. Warren, E.H. Darlington, K. Peacock, C. Chapman, L. McFadden, M. Malin,
                   and M. Robinson, An Overview Of The Near Multispectral Imager - Near-infrared
                   Spectrometer Investigation, J. Geophys. Res., Vol. 102, pp. 23709-23727, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.VEVERKAETAL1997A</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Veverka, J., P. Thomas, A. Harch, B. Clark, J.F. Bell III, B. Carcich, J.
                   Joseph, C. Chapman, W. Merline, M. Robinson, M. Malin, L. McFadden, S.L.
                   Murchie, S.E. Hawkins III, R. Farquhar, N.R. Izenberg, and A. Cheng, Near&apos;s
                   Flyby Of 253 Mathilde: Images of a C Asteroid, Science, Vol. 278, pp.
                   2109-2114, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.VEVERKAETAL1997B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   unk
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.VEVERKAETAL1999</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Veverka, J., P.C. Thomas, J.F. Bell III, M. Bell, B. Carcich, B. Clark, A.
                   Harch, J. Joseph, P. Martin, M. Robinson, S. Murchie, N. Izenberg, E. Hawkins,
                   J. Warren, R. Farquhar, A. Cheng, D. Dunham, C. Chapman, W.J. Merline, L.
                   McFadden, D. Wellnitz, M. Malin, W.M. Owen Jr., J.K. Miller, B.G. Williams, and
                   D.K. Yeomans, Imaging Of Asteroid 433 Eros During Near&apos;s Flyby Reconnaissance,
                   Science, Vol. 285, pp. 562-564, 1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.VEVERKAETAL1999A</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Warren, J., K. Peacock, E.H. Darlington, S.L. Murchie, S. Oden, J. Hayes, J.F.
                   Bell III, S. Krein, and A. Mastandrea, Near-infrared spectrometer for the Near
                   Earth Asteroid Rendezvous mission, Space Science Review, Vol. 82, pp. 101-167,
                   1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.WARRENETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Yeomans, D., A.S. Konopliv, and J.-P. Barriot, The NEAR Radio Science
                   Investigations, Journal of Geophysical Research, 102(E10), 23775, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.YEOMANSETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Yeomans, D.K., P.G. Antreasian, A. Cheng, D.W. Dunham, R.W. Farquhar, R.W.
                   Gaskell, J.D. Giorgini, C.E. Helfrich, A.S. Konopliv, J.V. McAdams, J.K.
                   Miller, W.M. Owen, Jr., P.C. Thomas, J. Veverka, and B.G. Williams, Estimating
                   the mass of asteroid 433 Eros during the NEAR spacecraft flyby, Science, 285,
                   pp. 560-561, 1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.YEOMANSETAL1999</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Zuber, M., D.E. Smith, A.F. Cheng, and T.D. Cole, The NEAR Laser Ranging
                   Investigation, Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol. 102, pp. 23761-23773, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ZUBERETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>NEAR INFRARED SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
    Launched on February 17, 1996, the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous
    (NEAR) spacecraft will go into orbit around the asteroid 433 Eros on
    February 14, 2000. The first launch of the Discovery class missions,
    NEAR will study this S-class asteroid up close, determining its
    geological characteristics, physical properties and composition
    [CHENG1997]. The reflected-light spectral data gathered by the Near
    Infrared Spectrometer (NIS) is a key component of an integrated
    strategy for the study of Eros. This strategy also includes high
    resolution imaging from the multispectral imager (MSI)
    [VEVERKAETAL1997A], elemental abundance measurements from the
    X-ray/gamma-ray spectrometer (XGRS) [TROMBKAETAL1997B], magnetic
    field data from the magnetometer (MAG) [ACUNAETAL1997], topographic
    data from the NEAR laser rangefinder (NLR) [ZUBERETAL1997], and mass
    and gravity data from the on-board radio science experiment
    [YEOMANSETAL1997]. NIS will conduct spectral mapping of Eros by
    measuring reflected sunlight in the wavelength range from 800 to
    2600 nm. Reflectance spectra of Eros will be used to identify the
    surface mineral assemblages, to constrain the origin and evolution
    of the surface, and, in combination with other NEAR data, to explore
    the links between asteroids and meteorites.
 
    NEAR has traveled a circuitous path on its way to its orbital
    encounter with Eros [FARQUHARETAL1995], including a swing through
    the inner main asteroid belt that allowed a flyby of the C-type
    asteroid 253 Mathilde, a gravity-assist swingby of Earth, and an
    unplanned initial flyby of Eros itself following an aborted
    orbit-insertion burn [YEOMANSETAL1999], [VEVERKAETAL1999]. Due to
    inadequate power margins at the relatively large heliocentric
    distance during the target-of-opportunity encounter with Mathilde on
    June 27, 1997, NIS was not turned on at that time
    [VEVERKAETAL1997B]. The NIS instrument&apos;s protective cover was not
    opened until later in 1997, allowing observations of the on-board
    calibration target (caltarget) and of the Earth and Moon during the
    January 23, 1998 swingby maneuver. NIS first observed Eros in late
    December 1998 [VEVERKAETAL1999A]. Data from the Eros flyby provided
    a valuable opportunity to evaluate instrument performance.
    Observations of Eros will resume on final approach in early 2000 and
    continue throughout the mission as the orbit is changed in steps
    from 500 to 35 km radius.
 
    NIS was designed to fulfill four key NEAR measurement requirements
    [VEVERKAETAL1997A]:  1) Map the mineralogical composition of Eros
    using reflected sunlight 1) Map the distribution and abundance of
    minerals at scales as small as 300 meters 1) Complement high
    resolution MSI images and low resolution XGRS elemental distribution
    maps for definitive identification of rock types composing Eros&apos;
    surface 1)  Provide information on the physical and textural
    properties of these surface materials
 
    In order to fulfill these requirements, the instrument&apos;s behavior
    must be characterized both from rigorous preflight calibration and
    testing and from in-flight observations over the mission lifetime.
    This paper reviews the data and techniques used to calibrate the
    NIS, and discusses initial in-flight results for observations by NIS
    during the cruise, Earth swingby, and Eros flyby phases of the NEAR
    mission. The calibration of the instrument will be refined
    throughout the mission. Table two in the NIS calibration paper contains
    the science rationale for the phases and can be found in the
    NIS/DOCUMENT/INSTRUMENT/CALPAPER directory.
 
 
  Instrument Description
  ========================
    NIS is composed of a grating infrared spectrometer, a scan mirror,
    two passively cooled detector modules, a mounting bracket,
    spectrometer electronics, and a data processing unit (DPU) that
    controls both the NIS and the NEAR magnetometer. NIS has a one-time
    deployable opaque cover, which was opened on September 24, 1997,
    three months after the Mathilde flyby [VEVERKAETAL1997B].
 
  Hardware
  --------
    The NIS design (Fig. 1) is copied from an earlier Applied Physics
    Laboratory (APL) spectrometer - the Defense Meteorological Satellite
    Special Sensor Ultraviolet Spectrographic Imager (SSUSI) - and
    modified for an infrared wavelength range. [WARRENETAL1997] detail
    the design characteristics, engineering, and construction of the
    instrument. A gold-coated scan mirror controls the direction of
    viewing over a range of 140 degrees. Light reflected from the scan
    mirror passes through a 20 x 25-mm aperture stop and is imaged by a
    telescope mirror at a slit. The field of view is selectable at the
    slit to &apos;narrow&apos; (0.38 degrees x 0.76 degrees) or &apos;wide&apos; (0.76
    degrees x 0.76 degrees) settings. A shutter actuates the narrow
    slit, with the smaller slit opening coming down over the fixed wide
    slit. The two slits provide field-of-view sizes of 0.65 x 1.3 km or
    1.3 x 1.3 km from 100 km distance. A second shutter can be actuated
    to completely block the slit for dark current measurements. After
    passing through the slit, light is dispersed and re- imaged off a
    gold toroidal diffraction grating (a Rowland circle configuration
    spectrometer) and hits a dichroic beamsplitter mounted at 45 degrees
    to the beam which transmits or reflects the energy to fall on two
    32- element linear detector arrays. Reflected 2nd order wavelengths
    (804-1506 nm) fall on a germanium (Ge) array. Each Ge channel has a
    bandwidth of 21.6 nm.  The germanium detector has a selectable gain
    of 1x or 10x. Transmitted 1st order wavelengths (1348-2732 nm) go to
    an indium-gallium-arsenide (InGaAs) array with 43.1 nm channel
    bandwidth. [WARRENETAL1997] calibrated the central wavelengths of
    all NIS channels at three operational temperatures (-7 degrees C,
    -17 degrees C, and -23 degrees C) and found best-fit Ge spectral
    calibration given by:
 
    lambda (nm) = 794.6 + 21.61*n        (Equation 1)
 
    where n is Ge element number 1-32. The uncertainty of the wavelength
    calibration over the range of temperatures examined is +/-0.5 nm.
    InGaAs element center wavelengths are given by:
 
    lambda (nm) = 43.11*n - 50.8        (Equation 2)
 
    where n is InGaAs element number 33-64. The temperature-dependent
    wavelength uncertainty is approximately +/-3.5 nm.
 
    The lower two channels of the InGaAs detector (channels 33 and 34,
    at 1372 and 1315 nm respectively) are below the transition
    wavelength of the dichroic beamsplitter, and therefore always
    register very low signal. The upper 3 channels (channels 62-64 at
    2622, 2665, and 2708 nm) are near or in detector cutoff, making the
    effective upper bound for good signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) around
    2500 nm for the signal level expected at Eros. Additionally, two
    InGaAs channels (47 and 57, at 1975 nm and 2406 nm) have been
    extremely noisy since manufacture and do not produce easily usable
    data. Default operations for NIS utilize the narrow slit, providing
    a critically sampled spectral resolution of 22 nm in the Ge
    detector, and 44 nm in the InGaAs detector. The wide slit
    configuration provides half the spectral resolution (44 nm and 88 nm
    respectively), but passes twice the light and therefore has a higher
    SNR.
 
    The NIS scan mirror can rotate the line of sight over 350 steps in
    0.4-degree increments in the spacecraft Z-X&apos; plane. The +Z axis is
    perpendicular to the plane of NEAR&apos;s solar panels, and +X&apos; is the
    boresight of the instruments.  Mirror position 0 (nominal caltarget
    observation geometry) is 30 degrees towards the Z-axis from the
    boresight. The boresight is aligned with mirror position 75.
    Position 300 points in the -Z (anti-Sun) direction.
 
    For optimum performance the detectors are operated near -35 degrees
    C, maintained by passive cooling or active heaters, depending on the
    thermal environment. A solar-illuminated gold calibration plaque
    (caltarget) is mounted to the instrument for radiometric stability
    calibration.  Table I summarizes the NIS specifications. More
    detailed descriptions of the NIS instrument design are presented in
    [PEACOCK1997] and [WARRENETAL1997].
 
  Flight Software
  ---------------
    In-flight NIS data are acquired through the use of command sequences
    to the instrument that specify ten instrument parameters
    [NISAPLSRS1995], [IZENBERGETAL1998] as follows:  1. Spectrometer
    sequence ID (0-15). Sixteen sequences can be uploaded and stored
    while the instrument is powered. Sequences 0, 1, and 2 are
    hard-coded, but can be redefined.  2. Repeats: the number of times
    the commanded observations will repeat.  3. Seconds between
    repeats.  4. Number of observations. This is the number taken during
    a single repeat of the sequence.  5. Calibration interval
    (1-65535).  Number of observations before acquisition of dark
    spectra. This is used to interleave shutter-closed dark observations
    with data observations.  6. Number of seconds to co-add spectral
    data in each observation (0-63).  7. Number of rest spectra (0-63).
    Used when interleaved darks are taken, between spectra acquisition
    and dark acquisition.  8. Number of co-added seconds of dark signal
    for interleaved dark spectrum.  9. Number of scan mirror steps
    between observations (sign indicates direction).  10. Seconds
    between observations.
 
    For the purposes of the software discussion, a &apos;spectrum&apos; is the
    result of a one-second integration of the instrument as it gathers
    data.  An &apos;observation&apos; is 0-63 consecutive one-second spectra
    summed together. The example sequence ( 15  3  5  10  5  16  2  4 2
    2 ) is interpreted as follows: Sequence ID is 15. The sequence will
    repeat three times, each iteration to contain 10 observations
    consisting of 16 co-added spectra of accumulated data. The
    calibration interval of five means that every 5th observation
    (numbers 5 and 10 in each repeat) will instead co-add 10 spectra of
    the target, then rest 2 seconds while the shutter closes, then take
    four co-added spectra of dark signal. After each accumulated
    observation, the scan mirror will move +2 steps and the instrument
    will rest two seconds. During each repeat, the mirror will move 20
    steps. Each repeat is separated by five seconds to allow the mirror
    to return to the start position. This example sequence would
    generate 30 NIS observations of the target, and 6 dark
    observations.  Choice of the wide or narrow NIS slit, the high or
    low Ge detector gain, and the starting NIS scan mirror position are
    specified through separate commands to the instrument.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
