<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:grs.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>GAMMA RAY SPECTROMETER for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adler, I., J.I. Trombka, J. Gerard, P. Lowman, R. Schamadebeck, H. Blodgett, E.
                   Eller, L. Yin, R. Lamothe, P. Gorenstein, and P. Bjorkholm, Apollo 15
                   Geochemical X-Ray Fluorescence Experiment: Preliminary Report, Science, Vol.
                   175, pp. 436-440, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ADLERETAL1972A</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adler, I., J. Gerard, J.I. Trombka, R. Schamadebeck, P. Lowman, H. Blodgett, L.
                   Yin, E. Eller, and R. Lamothe, The Apollo 15 X-Ray Fluorescence Experiment,
                   Proc. Lunar Sci Conf. 3rd, pp. 2157-2178, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ADLERETAL1972B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Adler, I., J.I. Trombka, J. Gerard, P. Lowman, R. Schamadebeck, H. Blodgett, E.
                   Eller, L. Yin, R. Lamothe, G. Osswald, P. Gorenstein, P. Bjorkholm, H. Gursky,
                   and B. Harris, Apollo 16 Geochemical X-ray Fluorescence Experiment: Preliminary
                   Report, Science, Vol. 177, pp. 256-259, 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ADLERETAL1972C</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Bielefeld, M., R. Reedy, A. Metzger, J. Trombka, and J. Arnold, Proc. Lunar
                   Sci. Conf. 7th, pp. 2661-2676, 1976.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BIELEFELDETAL1976</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Boynton, W.V., J.I. Trombka, W.C. Feldman, J.R. Arnold, P. Englert, A.E.
                   Metzger, R.C. Reedy, S.W. Squyres, H. Waenke, S.H. Bailey, J. Bruckner, J.L.
                   Callas, D.M. Drake, P. Duke, L.G. Evans, E.L. Haines, F.C. McCloskey, H. Mills,
                   C. Shinohara, and R. Starr, Science Applications Of The Mars Observer Gamma Ray
                   Spectrometer, J. Geophys. Res., Vol. 97, pp. 7681-7698, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BOYNTONETAL1992</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Boynton, W.V., L.G. Evans, R.C. Reedy, and J.I. Trombka, The Composition Of
                   Mars And Comets By Remote And In-situ Gamma-ray Spectrometry, Remote
                   Geochemical Analysis: Geochemical And Mineralogical Composition, C. Pieters and
                   P. Englert (eds.), Cambridge University Press, New York, NY, USA pp. 395-412,
                   1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BOYNTONETAL1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Bruckner, J., M. Koerfer, H. Waenke, A.N.F. Schroeder, D. Filges, P.
                   Dragovitsch, P.A.J. Englert, R. Starr, J.I. Trombka, I. Taylor, D.M. Drake, and
                   E.R. Schunk, IEEE Trans. Nucl. Sci., NS-38, pp. 209-217, 1991.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BRUCKNERETAL1991</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Clark, B.E., J.F. Bell, F.P. Fanale, and D.J. O&apos;Connor, Results of the Seven
                   Color Asteroid Survey: Infrared spectral observations of ~50-km size S-, K-,
                   and M-type asteroids, Icarus, Vol. 113, pp. 387-402, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CLARKETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Evans, L.G., R.C. Reedy, and J.I. Trombka, Introduction to Planetary Remote
                   Sensing, Remote Geochemical Analysis: Elemental and Mineralogical Composition,
                   C. Pieters and P. Englert (eds.), University of Cambridge, Cambridge, England,
                   pp. 167-198, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.EVANSETAL1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Evans, L.G., P.E. Clark, and J.I. Trombka, Acta Astron., Vol. 35, pp. 79-88,
                   1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.EVANSETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Goldsten, J.O., Johns Hopkins APL Technical Digest, Vol. 19, pp. 126-135, 1998.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GOLDSTEN1998</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Goldsten, J.O., R.L. McNutt, R.E. Gold, S.A. Gary, E. Fiore, S.E. Schneider,
                   J.R. Hayes, J.I. Trombka, S.R. Floyd, W.V. Boynton, S. Bailey, J. Bruckner,
                   S.W. Squyres, L.G. Evans, P.E. Clark, and R. Starr, Space Sciences Review, Vol.
                   82, pp. 169-216, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GOLDSTENETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Knoll, G.F., Radiation Detection And Measurement, Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, 1989.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KNOLL1989</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Starr, R., P.E. Clark, L.G. Evans, S.R. Floyd, T.P. McClanahan, J.I. Trombka,
                   J.O. Goldsten, R.H. Maurer, R.L. McNutt, Jr., and D.R. Roth, Radiation effects
                   in the Si-PIN detector on the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous Mission, Nuclear
                   Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A, Vol. 428, pp. 209-215,
                   1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.STARRETAL1999</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Trombka, J., S. Floyd, W. Boynton, S. Bailey, J. Bruckner, S. Squyres, L.
                   Evans, P. Clear, R. Starr, E. Fiore, R. Gold, J. Goldsten, and R. McNutt,
                   Compositional Mapping With The Near X-ray/Gamma-ray Spectrometer, J. Geophys.
                   Res., Vol. 102, pp. 23729-23750, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TROMBKAETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Yin, L, J. Trombka, I. Adler, and M. Bielefeld, X-ray Remote Sensing Techniques
                   For Geochemical Analysis Of Planetary Surfaces, Remote Geochemical Analysis:
                   Geochemical And Mineralogical Composition, C. Pieters and P. Englert (eds.),
                   Cambridge University Press, New York, NY, USA, pp. 199-212, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.YINETAL1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>GAMMA RAY SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
 
      The Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous mission (NEAR) was successfully
      launched on 17 February 1996.  NEAR was the first launch under
      NASA&apos;s Discovery Program, an initiative for small, low-cost
      planetary missions.  As the first spacecraft to orbit an asteroid,
      the NEAR mission will address fundamental questions about the
      processes and conditions relevant to planetary formation.
 
      The X-ray/Gamma-ray Spectrometer (XGRS) is one of several
      instruments on-board the NEAR spacecraft that will study Eros during
      one year of orbital operations beginning in February 2000. The X-ray
      and gamma-ray spectrometers that comprise the XGRS are independent,
      but complementary experiments.  In this paper we focus on the Gamma Ray
      Spectrometer, its design, operation, calibration, and procedures for
      interpretation of the measurements to be made at Eros.
 
 
    History
    =======
      In February 1996, the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous (NEAR) mission
      was launched into space on a planned three-year cruise to the
      near-Earth asteroid, 433 Eros.  The NEAR spacecraft, the first in
      the Discovery mission program to be launched, was built by the John
      Hopkins University, Applied Physics Laboratory (APL).  The
      spacecraft will orbit Eros for one year and carries a group of
      remote sensing instruments including an X-ray and gamma-ray
      spectrometer system (XGRS).  Due to a problem with firing of the
      main rocket engine in December 1998, the rendezvous was delayed
      until February 2000.  The NEAR spacecraft will be the first
      spacecraft to orbit a body as small as Eros, which is estimated to
      be 33 km X 13 km X 13 km.
 
      From telescopic, radar, and other observations, it has been inferred
      that Eros is an S-type asteroid, one of the most common type of
      near-Earth asteroids.  It is not known whether S-type asteroids come
      from differentiated or undifferentiated parent bodies.  One of the
      prime mission science objectives is to obtain global elemental
      composition maps. These elemental composition results are needed
      with sufficient accuracy to enable comparison with major meteorite
      types. The results would also be used to assess the compositional
      heterogeneity of the asteroid and help to answer questions about
      differentiation.  The selection of X-ray and gamma-ray spectrometers
      for this mission was based on their ability to produce global
      elemental composition maps of the asteroid.  Gamma-ray measurements
      can determine the abundance of elements such as O, Si, Fe, Ti, Mg,
      K, Th, and U depending on the actual composition.
 
 
    Gamma-Ray Spectrometer Overview
    ===============================
      The gamma-ray spectrometer (GRS) on the NEAR mission is a
      non-dispersive system.  For this type of detector, the incident
      gamma-ray photon is absorbed in the detector material and a signal
      proportional to the energy absorbed is measured as a voltage from
      the detector output.  An analog-to-digital conversion is performed
      and the resulting count is binned by &apos;pulse height&apos; or energy loss
      in memory.  From an analysis of the pulse height spectra, elemental
      composition can be inferred.
 
      The choice among various types of gamma-ray detectors was made early
      in the planning for NEAR, the first Discovery mission of low-cost,
      rapid delivery planetary missions.  While cooled solid-state
      detectors dominate laboratory measurements due to their inherent
      better energy resolution, this was not the case for this space
      mission. A NEAR GRS design was selected that could meet the required
      sensitivity in the energy region 0.1-10 MeV, while being consistent
      with the cost, mass, power, and reliability constraints of the
      mission.
 
      Gamma-ray photons in the energy region 0.1-10 MeV are emitted by
      excited nuclei and have discrete energies characteristic of that
      element.  The excitation of nuclei can come from the radioactive
      decay of very-long lived radioisotopes in planetary materials, such
      as 40K, 238U, and 232Th.  For other elements in space, excitation is
      provided by cosmic-ray bombardment.  Except for periods of time
      during and immediately after major solar flares, this excitation is
      caused mainly by galactic cosmic rays (GCR) [EVANSETAL1993].
 
      GCR are nuclear particles, mainly protons and helium nuclei (alpha
      particles), with a broad range in energy, but typically of order a
      GeV and a nearly isotropic flux of about 2-3 particles/cm2-s.  These
      particles generate nuclear cascades on striking dense matter.  The
      cascade particles most effective in generating gamma rays are
      neutrons.  The high-energy neutrons produced in this manner can
      undergo further nuclear collisions.  They may excite stable nuclei
      to higher energy levels by inelastic scatter.  The resulting
      de-excitation of the nucleus can result in the emission of a gamma
      ray and is termed an inelastic scatter reaction; (n,n&apos;gamma).
      Neutrons may also lose energy by elastic scatter until their energy
      is comparable to the thermal energy of a nucleus at a given
      temperature.  These thermal neutrons can be captured by a nucleus
      and the resulting decay to the ground state of this new isotope, can
      produce a capture gamma ray; (n,gamma).  The intensity of gamma rays
      emitted by a particular element and for a particular process depends
      on the concentration of that element, the reaction cross-section for
      the process, and the number of neutrons available with the
      appropriate energy.  The inelastic scatter reactions have a large
      cross-section for all common nuclei at energies above the reaction
      threshold energy.  Therefore, all the most abundant elements give a
      useful yield of gamma rays from this process.  Thermal neutron
      cross-sections vary by orders-of-magnitude and yields for neutron
      capture gamma rays for the most abundant elements also vary widely
      [EVANSETAL1993].  Material containing large concentrations of
      elements with large neutron capture cross-sections can alter the
      thermal flux and lead to a flux depression of neutron capture
      gamma-rays.
 
      The neutron cascade penetrates into a planetary surface to a depth
      of hundreds of g/cm2, a few meters into the regolith on an object
      like an asteroid with no atmosphere.  Gamma rays are scattered (with
      loss of characteristic energy) or absorbed on a distance scale of
      tens of g/cm2.  This indicates that only those gamma rays generated
      in the first tens of g/cm2 can be detected on the surface or from
      orbit, and the important part of the neutron equilibrium
      distribution in the planetary body is that near the surface.  The
      moderation and thermalization of the neutrons depend strongly on the
      composition of the near surface material, particularly on the
      hydrogen and carbon content, if any.  Gamma-ray detectors on the
      surface or in an orbiting spacecraft can measure the discrete energy
      gamma rays and determine the elements that emitted these gamma rays
      [BOYNTONETAL1992], [BOYNTONETAL1993], [TROMBKAETAL1997].
 
      Besides the characteristic gamma rays emerging from the asteroid
      surface, there will be a number of other sources of gamma rays that
      will be a background from which the gamma rays of interest will have
      to be separated.  Some of these sources of background produce
      discrete lines and some appear as part of a continuum.  Based on
      previous spaceflight experience, the major background components
      measured in orbit are: partial energy deposition in the detector
      (Compton effect); cosmic-ray activation of the detector and
      materials surrounding the detector; characteristic gamma rays
      emitted from the surface material, but scattered before emerging
      from the asteroid; cosmic-ray activation and natural radioactivity
      in the spacecraft; and gamma emission from astrophysical sources
      [BIELEFELDETAL1976].
 
      Detectors
      ---------
       Most current non-dispersive gamma-ray detectors utilize either
       inorganic scintillation material, such as sodium iodide (NaI) or
       bismuth germinate (BGO), or solid state material, such as
       high-purity germanium (Ge).  The Ge detectors have significantly
       better energy resolution than scintillation detectors and are
       generally favored for laboratory measurements.  For example, the
       typical energy resolution (expressed as the full-width at half-
       maximum, FWHM, of the peak) for a Ge detector is 2 keV measured at
       1332 keV from a 60Co calibration source.  A similar FWHM for a NaI
       detector is 80 keV at 1332 keV.  In addition, the Ge detector has
       a much better peak-to-Compton ratio, typically about 50 compared
       to 2 for a NaI detector [KNOLL1989].  These two factors give a Ge
       detector a decided advantage in resolving peaks close in energy
       and detecting peaks in the presence of significant continuum.
       Figure 1 shows measurement spectra of an extended soil sample
       irradiated by a neutron generator collected by both Ge and NaI
       detectors.  Identification by element of some of the prominent
       gamma-ray peaks in the spectrum is indicated.
 
       While Ge detectors improve detection capability, they also require
       operation at cryogenic temperatures (typically &lt;100 K) and suffer
       serious degradation in performance when exposed to cosmic
       radiation over long periods of time [BRUCKNERETAL1991].  Typically
       Ge detectors on planetary missions (such as Mars Observer) are
       designed with anneal capability to offset the expected resolution
       degradation during spaceflight. These limitations of a Ge detector
       along with the added cost and complexity reduced some of the
       advantages that might be expected for this mission. The question
       that had to be answered for the NEAR mission was: Could a
       scintillation detector meet the mission science requirements for
       elemental sensitivity?
 
       Analysis during the preliminary design phase of the NEAR mission
       indicated that a scintillation detector could meet the science
       objectives of the mission [EVANSETAL1995].  Experience in both
       U.S. and Russian planetary missions and in the oil well-logging
       industry have shown that good results could be obtained using
       scintillation detectors for such elements as K, Th, O, H, Mg, Si,
       and Fe.  In addition, proposed design changes were expected to
       greatly improve detector performance over scintillators that have
       previously flown in space.
 
       NaI was chosen as the scintillator for NEAR because it has the
       best energy resolution of common scintillation materials in
       combination with a photomultiplier tube (PMT).  These systems are
       rugged and have been used successfully on space flight missions
       for many years [EVANSETAL1993].
 
       The pulse height spectrum obtained when monoenergetic gamma rays
       are detected has a shape determined by the gamma-ray energy and
       the characteristics of the detector.  Important factors are: (1)
       the relative magnitude of the photoelectric,  Compton, and
       pair-production cross-sections as a function of energy, and (2)
       the statistical fluctuations and losses involved in collecting the
       signal generated in the detector [KNOLL1989].  A measurement
       reflects the amount of energy that is lost in the detector and
       transferred as kinetic energy to electrons.  At energies where the
       photoelectric absorption dominates, the kinetic energy imparted to
       a secondary electron is equal to the gamma-ray energy minus the
       electron binding energy.  This energy can be reclaimed, in a
       sense, by the absorption of the X-rays produced by photoelectric
       absorption.  At higher energies, when Compton scattering becomes
       more important, the gamma ray may lose part of its energy to the
       detector and escape the crystal or may then be photo absorbed.
       The gamma ray will lose all or part of its energy in the detector
       and possible escape with diminished energy.  This generates a
       continuum that adds to the background up to the energy of the
       initial gamma ray minus the minimum scattered energy.
 
       At energies above 1022 keV, electron-positron pair production
       becomes possible.  The electron eventually loses all its kinetic
       energy in the detector while the positron annihilate with another
       electron producing two 511 keV photons.  The energy of these
       photons can either be absorbed in the detector or can escape.
       Therefore, three peaks will be created: (1) pair production with
       eventual absorption of both 511 keV photons to give a peak at the
       initial gamma-ray energy; (2) pair production with the absorption
       of one 511 photon and the escape of the other giving a peak at the
       initial gamma-ray energy minus 511 keV; and (3) pair production
       with the escape of both 511 keV photons giving a peak at the
       initial gamma-ray energy minus 1022 keV.
 
       Cosmic-ray interactions in the spacecraft produce gamma-rays
       characteristic of the spacecraft materials.  These gamma rays
       would constitute an unwanted background signal and could
       potentially degrade the science return of the mission.  Gamma-ray
       detectors of previous missions have often used a boom to move the
       gamma-ray detector away from the spacecraft reducing substantially
       the spacecraft background.  On Mars Observer, for example, the
       gamma-ray detector was mounted on a boom that could be extended 6
       meters from the spacecraft.  The NEAR detector had to be body
       mounted on the lower deck along with all the other instruments.
       This required some other method of reducing the spacecraft
       background.
 
       Plastic scintillators are very effective charged particle shields,
       but higher density materials are needed to shield gamma rays.
       Passive shielding is not practical because of the large volume and
       mass of material needed to absorb the cosmic rays and the
       secondary radioactive products produced in the shield. An active
       collimator is used to reduce the charged particle, spacecraft and
       cosmic gamma-ray background as well as the Compton continuum.
       Charged particles or photons that interact in the shield produce a
       corresponding output signal.  This signal can be used to trigger
       an anti-coincidence system to reject any counts in the central
       detector that are in coincidence with the shield within some time
       window.  Bismuth Germinate (BGO) was chosen for the NEAR shield.
       It has a density of 7.13 g/cm2 which makes it especially effective
       for gamma ray interactions.
 
       As useful as the NEAR shield would be to reduce the detector
       background, significant information on the gamma-ray flux from the
       asteroid could be lost.  The first and second escape peaks
       produced in the central detector will be mostly eliminated in the
       anti-coincidence spectrum.  For a small central detector like the
       NEAR design, this loss would be unacceptable since the escape
       peaks would have many more counts than the full-energy peak for
       many energies of interest.  For example, at 6 MeV, calculations
       indicate that 85% of all the counts would be in the escape peaks
       and only 15% in the full-energy peak.  The NEAR design recovers
       these peaks with two additional NaI spectra; one in coincidence
       with 511 keV and one in coincidence with 1022 keV energy
       deposition in the BGO shield.  Calibrations with the NEAR detector
       indicates the effectiveness of this design.
 
       Analysis of the coincidence window spectra during calibrations
       showed that not only photons generated by pair production were
       collected in the coincidence spectra.  Any photons that Compton
       scattered in the central detector and then deposited 511 or 1022
       keV in the shield were also collected.  This was confirmed for
       energies where no pair production was possible (for incident
       energies less than 1022 keV), but the first coincidence spectrum
       showed a peak at the incident energy minus 511 keV.  Thus, the
       number of counts in the peaks for both coincidence spectra were
       greater than that expected by calculations of efficiency for just
       pair production [TROMBKAETAL1997].  Subsequent calculations
       that modeled the coincidence process in the central detector and
       the shield to understand these measurements showed results similar
       to the measured efficiencies.  This will be discussed further
       below.
 
       A radioactive source for energy calibration was not included in
       the NEAR design. It was expected that enough discrete lines from
       background sources would be measured in the spectra that the
       energy calibration could be monitored.  The strongest of these
       would be the 511 keV line due to electron/positron annihilation in
       the spacecraft and materials surrounding the detector.  Other
       gamma rays from cosmic ray interactions in the scintillation
       materials would be expected.  Measurements taken during the cruise
       portion of the mission confirmed these predictions and will be
       discussed below.
 
       A picture of the NEAR GRS detector is shown in Figure 2 and a
       cross-section diagram in shown in Figure 3.  A complete
       description of the GRS hardware is given in [GOLDSTENETAL1997] and
       [GOLDSTEN1998].  The central detector is a 2.54 cm X 7.62 cm right
       circular cylinder of NaI(Tl).  A 3 cm diameter metal ceramic PMT
       is attached to the NaI in the asteroid facing direction.  The
       shield is a BGO cup with outside dimensions of 8.9 cm X 14 cm.  A
       7.6 cm diameter metal ceramic PMT is attached to the BGO.  The
       measured energy resolution at 662 keV (from 137Cs) was 8.7% for
       the NaI detector and 14% for the BGO.  The energy range of both
       detectors could be controlled by changing the high-voltage setting
       for each detector, but was nominally 0.1-10 MeV.
 
       A generalized block diagram of the GRS detection scheme is shown
       in Figure 4 [GOLDSTENETAL1997].  An incoming photon is absorbed by
       the detector material and produces an output signal proportional
       to the energy absorbed.  The detector signal is amplified,
       filtered, and its peak value measured using an analog-to-digital
       converter.  A data processor collects the measurements and bins
       them according to the energy absorbed into a pulse-height
       spectrum.  Five 1024-channel spectra are collected
       simultaneously.  These are: the NaI raw spectrum, with no
       coincidence or anti-coincidence rejection; the BGO raw spectrum;
       the NaI spectrum measured in anti-coincidence with the BGO; the
       NaI spectrum measured in coincidence within a window around 511
       keV in the BGO detector;  the NaI spectrum measured in coincidence
       within a window around 1022 keV in the BGO detector.  In addition
       two 21 channel spectra are collected from the BGO detector in
       coincidence with the NaI and in the windows specified around the
       511 keV and 1022 keV energies.
 
       Temperature and voltage stability are extremely important to
       maintain system performance.  The light outputs of the NaI and BGO
       detectors vary significantly with temperature.  The detectors are
       thermally isolated and wrapped with operational heaters to
       stabilize the temperature to within 0.25 degC.  The signal gains
       of the PMTs are not particularly sensitive to temperature, but are
       very sensitive to voltage variations.  The XGRS uses an external
       feedback control system to produce ultra-stable high-voltage
       outputs from the on-board high-voltage power supplies
       [GOLDSTENETAL1997].  No gain changes due to temperature or
       high-voltage variation were observed during cruise.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
