<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nlr.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>NEAR LASER RANGEFINDER for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Cheng, A.F., A. Santo, K. Heeres, J. Landshof, R. Farquhar, et al., Near-Earth
                   Asteroid Rendezvous: Mission Overview, Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol.
                   102, pp. 23695-23708, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CHENGETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Cole, T., M. Boies, A. El-Dinary, A.F. Cheng, M. Zuber, and D.E. Smith, The
                   Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous Laser Altimeter, Space Science Reviews, Vol. 82,
                   pp. 217-253, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.COLEETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Gardner, C.S., Ranging performance of satellite laser altimeters, IEEE Trans
                   Geoscience and Remote Sensing, Vol. 30, pp. 1061-1072, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GARDNER1992</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Smith, D.E., M.T. Zuber, S.C. Solomon, R.J. Phillips, J.W. Head, J.B. Garvin,
                   W.B. Banerdt, D.O. Muhleman, G.H. Pettengill, G.A. Neumann, F.G. Lemoine, J.B.
                   Abshire, O. Aharonson, C.D. Brown, S.A. Hauck, A.B. Ivanov, P.J. Mcgovern, H.J.
                   Zwally, and T.C. Duxbury, The Global Topography of Mars and Implications for
                   Surface Evolution, Science, Vol. 284, pp. 1495-1503, 1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.SMITHETAL1999B</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Zuber, M.T., D.E. Smith, S.C. Solomon, D.O. Muhleman, J.W. Head, J.B. Garvin,
                   J.B. Abshire, and J.L. Bufton, The Mars Observer Laser Altimeter Investigation,
                   J. Geophys. Res., 97, 7781-7797, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ZUBERETAL1992</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Zuber, M., D.E. Smith, F.G. Lemoine, and G. Neumann, The Shape and Internal
                   Structure of the Moon from the Clementine Mission, Science, Vol. 266, pp.
                   1839-1843, 1994.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ZUBERETAL1994</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Zuber, M., D.E. Smith, A.F. Cheng, and T.D. Cole, The NEAR Laser Ranging
                   Investigation, Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol. 102, pp. 23761-23773, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ZUBERETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>NEAR LASER RANGEFINDER</name>
        <type>Altimeter</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  NEAR Laser Rangefinder Instrument Overview
  ==========================================
    NLR is a direct-detection, time-of-flight laser altimeter that
    determines the range from the NEAR spacecraft to the surface of Eros
    by measuring the round-trip travel time of laser pulses with 0.312 m
    range resolution (single count). It employs direct, incoherent
    detection using an all solid-state, diode-pumped laser transmitter,
    a Cassegrain receiver telescope, and a receiver electronics package
    that incorporates an IR-enhanced, silicon Avalanche Photo Diode
    (APD) with thresholding and timing electronics. Figure 1 shows the
    NLR flight hardware and its principal subsystems.
 
    NLR is the first laser altimeter to employ continuous, in-flight
    calibration using a fiber-optic delay assembly (FODA), which is a
    spooled, 109.5-m fused silica fiber-optic cable. Part of each
    optical pulse formed within the laser resonator is injected into the
    FODA, which is connected to the baffle system in front of the
    receiver telescope. Using a 45 deg elliptical mirror, the delayed
    optical signal is directly introduced into the receiver. This allows
    end-to-end calibration for each emitted pulse even when no target
    surface is available.
 
    The laser transmitter (Fig. 1) is a diode-pumped, solid-state (DPSS)
    Cr:Nd:YAG using an active, lithium niobate (LiNbO3) Q-switch to
    control the formation of the laser pulse. Such Q-switched Nd:YAG
    DPSS lasers provide high reliability and were used in the Clementine
    [ZUBERETAL1994] and Mars Global Surveyor [ZUBERETAL1992];
    [SMITHETAL1999B] laser altimeters. The laser transmitter thermal
    design minimizes thermal excursions of the optical resonator
    assembly, using thermostatically controlled heaters and thermal
    isolation from the spacecraft. The laser pulse repetition rate (PRF)
    can be selected from among 1/8 Hz, 1 Hz, 2 Hz, and 8 Hz, but firing
    at 1 Hz PRF will be the nominal mode of operation at Eros.
 
    NLR is a bistatic system, with the transmitter separate from the
    receiver.  The transmission of the laser optical pulse is
    accomplished using a 62 mm Galilean refractive telescope (Fig. 1).
    The large output aperture significantly reduces the transmitter beam
    divergence. The receiver (Fig. 1) uses an 8.89 cm diameter, gold-
    coated aluminum Dall-Kirkham telescope to focus back-scattered laser
    energy onto the APD detector.  The APD is implemented in a trans-
    impedance circuit that automatically compensates for thermal
    variations. Detected signals from the APD are amplified, passed
    through a 30 MHz Bessel filter and sent to a commandable comparator
    to generate the digital stop pulse that is used to determine the
    time-of-flight (TOF).
 
    The TOF system measures the time from laser firing, as indicated by
    the laser transmitter start pulse, to the first receiver stop pulse
    (from the FODA calibration signal) and to the second stop pulse
    produced from the backscattered laser light returning from the
    target. The Bessel filter integrates the analog pulses to maximize
    the probability of detection for returned pulses that have been
    stretched in time (&apos;dilated&apos;) by scattering from the rough, tilted
    target surface. The filter also attenuates high frequency electronic
    noise. The comparator tests whether the filtered analog signal
    exceeds a commandable threshold voltage; when this occurs, the
    digital stop pulse is generated. The threshold level used by the
    comparator is set by ground command or autonomously through an auto-
    acquisition sequence. After the two TOF counters are stopped, a
    digital processing unit (DPU) reads the count values and formats
    them into science data packets together with instrument status and
    housekeeping information.
 
    Table. 1 NLR Characteristics
    PARAMETER                       MEASUREMENT
    max. range (altitude)              327 km
    range accuracy                     &lt; 6 m
    range resolution                   0.312 m
    pulse energy                       15.3 mJ @ 1.064 um
    energy jitter                      &lt; 1 % rms knowledge
    pulse-width                        15 ns
    pulse-width jitter                 0.82 ns rms knowledge
    wavelength spread                  +- 1 nm
    pulse frequency                    1/8, 1, 2, 8 Hz
    T-0 mask                           0 to 511.5 usec, delta = 500 ns
    range gate                         81ns to 42.7us, delta = 41.7 ns
    TEM00 (% Gaussian fit)             91 %  (TEM00 mode-like)
    divergence (1/e2 -points)          235 urad
    calibration power jitter           +- 5 %
    calibration timing jitter          &lt; 31.2 cm
    thermal control                    &lt; +- 2 degC
    shots (lifetime)                   ~10^9
    effective RX aperture, f/#         7.62 cm, f/3.4
    spectral receiver bandwidth        &lt; 7 nm
    temporal receiver bandwidth        30 MHz
    APD dark noise voltage             150 uVrms
    APD hybrid responsivity            770 kV/W
    optical receiver FOV               2900 urad
    threshold levels                   16mV*2^n, for n = 0,1,.,7
    data rates                         51 and 6.4 bps
    boresight shift, TX-to-RX          345 urad
 
 
  Operation
  =========
    The measured laser pulse characteristics are summarized in Table 1
    (data from [COLEETAL1997]). The temporal, spatial (near- and far-
    field), and pulse energy characteristics were measured during NLR
    flight system development.  Pulse energy measurements of the
    transmitter beam and FODA port output were measured using NIST-
    traceable equipment accurate to +5%. Measured near-field spatial
    beam distributions included beam diameter (1/e2), modal structure,
    and energy distribution characteristics. Far-field measurements
    included beam divergence, jitter, and wander.  The receiver sees two
    optical pulses per transmitted pulse. The first arrives ~558 ns
    after laser firing and is the calibration pulse routed through the
    FODA. Detection of this pulse stops the calibration counter, and the
    calibration counts value (&apos;Calibration&apos; in Table A1, see Appendix)
    is reported for each shot when operating at 1/8 Hz, 1 Hz or 8 Hz,
    but not when operating at 2 Hz. The next detected return is the
    surface backscattered pulse, whose detection stops the range
    counter. The range count value (&apos;Range&apos; in Table A1) is always
    reported for each laser shot.
 
    NLR&apos;s receiver is a leading-edge detector, meaning that a stop pulse
    is generated as soon as the optically produced signal (the filtered,
    analog voltage from the calibration pulse or the target return)
    exceeds a threshold level (&apos;Threshold Voltage&apos; in Table A1). The
    time at which this signal crosses the threshold determines the
    measured TOF, which therefore depends on the threshold value
    (threshold-driven &apos;range walk&apos;). This threshold can be commanded to
    any of eight values (Table 1), although no calibration signal is
    detected at the highest value.  Figure 2 shows the sequence of
    events that occur with each laser shot. After the fire command, the
    laser pulse is generated after a time delay that varies from 170 ?s
    to 190 ?s. The firing time delay varies slowly on ten-minute time
    scales. The emitted optical pulse generates the start pulse for the
    two TOF counters.
 
    The calibration pulse is received about 0.558 ?s after firing, and
    the laser return from the target is received much later, at a time
    determined by the range (the range counter overflows after 2.18 ms).
    The NLR receiver is `blanked&apos;, or prevented from detecting a pulse,
    for a time interval T0 after the fire command. This T-0 mask (see
    Table 1) is set by ground command with a default value of 180.498
    ?s. In-flight tests have shown that this default value, as well as
    values half as large, are sufficient to suppress any electronic
    noise from firing.  The value of T0 is adjusted by two parameters
    returned in the NLR data; the first is called &apos;T-0 COUNT&apos; and is
    represented here by the symbol ?, while the second is called &apos;Range
    gate&apos; and is represented by the symbol rg. This &apos;Range gate&apos;
    parameter does not define a range gate in the usual sense of a brief
    time interval, during which the receiver is active, encompassing the
    time of the expected range return. Rather, the NLR receiver becomes
    active once the time T0 has elapsed, and it remains active until two
    stop pulses are generated, one from the calibration return and one
    from the target.
 
    The relation between T0 and the commandable parameters ? and rg is
    where T0 is in units of ?s, and where ? and rg are both integers in
    the range [0, 1023].  The NLR timing shown in Fig 2 applies to
    normal operation at any of the four PRF values.  NLR also includes
    two special failure modes of operation, that can be used in the
    event of failures involving either the start pulse or the
    calibration pulse. In the former case, the FAILSAFE mode starts the
    TOF counters at the final value of the &apos;T-0 COUNT&apos; countdown. In the
    latter case, the ONESTOP mode causes NLR to use the first received
    stop pulse as the range pulse from the target. As of September,
    1999, the start and calibration pulses are functioning nominally,
    and there is no plan to use either FAILSAFE or ONESTOP.  NLR has two
    additional special operating modes designed to enable autonomous
    operation without excessive ground commanding. The first is called
    &apos;AUTO ACQUIRE&apos;, in which NLR uses the calibration pulse to find a
    threshold voltage above the noise level in the receiver. NLR fires
    16-shot bursts at each of the eight possible values for the voltage
    threshold (listed in Table 1), which are labeled TH = 0 through TH =
    7. The results of all pre-launch and in-flight tests through
    September, 1999 have shown that AUTO ACQUIRE sets the threshold at
    TH = 3. The second special operating mode is called &apos;CALIBRATE&apos;, in
    which NLR autonomously sets the value of ?. During &apos;CALIBRATE&apos;, NLR
    increments ? until it finds as large a value as possible that still
    assures detection of a valid calibration pulse.
 
    Fig 2 shows that if ? becomes too large, the time T0 that the
    receiver is blanked will include the arrival time of the calibration
    pulse, which cannot then be detected. As of September, 1999 there is
    no plan to use CALIBRATE during asteroid operations because the
    default values of ? and rg are completely satisfactory.  The timing
    of NLR events relative to other NEAR spacecraft events is shown in
    Figure 3. All spacecraft events are coordinated by synchronization
    pulses sent over the Mil-Std-1553 data bus at each one second
    interval of mission elapsed time (MET) under control of the command
    and telemetry processor (CTP). These one second intervals are
    referred to as &apos;major frames&apos;. Every major frame is divided into 8
    minor frames (Fig 3) numbered 0 through 7, each lasting 125 ms. The
    NLR DPU controls instrument timing which is locked to the receipt of
    the MET synchronization pulses once per second from the CTP. NLR
    fires the laser in specific minor frames, depending on the PRF mode
    as shown in Table 2. In all cases, laser firing occurs within ~3 ms
    of the start of the minor frame(s) shown in Table 2.
 
    Table 2. NLR firing times
 
    PRF Mode  MinorFrame(s)
 
    1/8Hz          0
    1  Hz          0
    2  Hz          0,4
    8  Hz          all
 
    NLR can sustain continuous firing at 1/8 Hz, 1 Hz, or 2 Hz PRF for
    indefinite periods. However, because of thermal limitation NLR
    cannot fire indefinitely at 8 Hz. In the 8 Hz mode, NLR fires 16
    shots in two seconds, after which NLR is quiescent for 14 s. Hence,
    in this mode NLR fires an average of one pulse per second.  An
    important NLR science objective is to correlate the laser altimetry
    data with imaging data from the NEAR Multispectral Imager (MSI), as
    discussed by [ZUBERETAL1997]. To accomplish this objective, it is
    necessary to determine the boresight offset between the NLR and the
    MSI.
 
    Both instruments have been designed to enable a direct measurement
    of the boresight offset, by using MSI to image the laser spot over
    the darkside of Eros. To obtain sufficient signal in the image, NLR
    is operated at 8 Hz to produce 8 shots during the maximum imager
    exposure time of 999 ms. The relative timing of NLR operation and
    MSI image exposures is shown in Fig 3. The MET synchronization
    pulses at NLR and at MSI are time-aligned within a few ms. During
    the maximum MSI exposure, the first NLR shot occurs ~80 ms after the
    start of the exposure, and the last occurs ~44 ms before the end.
    NLR Data collection The current plan is to leave NLR powered on
    throughout the prime mission phase in Eros orbit, firing laser
    pulses whenever the instruments are pointed at Eros for data
    acquisition (all NEAR instruments can observe Eros simultaneously).
    NEAR will point its instruments at Eros for approximately 16 hours
    per day, and it will point its high gain antenna at Earth for
    approximately 8 hours per day to downlink data. During downlink
    periods, NLR will not be pointed at the asteroid but will remain
    powered on. If NLR is operated at its 1 Hz nominal PRF mode, it will
    obtain a total of ~2x107 range measurements during the year-long
    prime mission and generate up to ~1.7 Gbit of data. The NLR
    investigation will begin ranging to Eros once the spacecraft
    descends to within 300 km range from the asteroid in early March,
    2000.
 
    The NLR investigation will control spacecraft pointing for the first
    two weeks in May, 2000, while the spacecraft is in an approximately
    circular, 50 km polar orbit. Most of the NLR data will be acquired
    while nadir pointing, i.e., with NLR pointed to the Eros center of
    mass. Figure 4 shows the ground coverage for 1 week of nadir-pointed
    observations in this orbit. The footprints of successive laser shots
    at 1 Hz PRF will be significantly overlapping while NLR is nadir-
    pointed during most of the 50 km orbit, except when NEAR is directly
    over an elongated end of Eros ([ZUBERETAL1997]; [COLEETAL1997]). The
    footprint diameter is 7 m at an altitude of 30 km and normal
    incidence. The sub-spacecraft point on Eros moves at 3-5 m/s. Even
    one week of nadir-pointed observations will yield a data set well
    suited for determining global shape, size, and rotation state
    [ZUBERETAL1997].  Although each NLR track is densely sampled in the
    50 km orbit, Figure 4 shows that the successive tracks are spaced
    more than a kilometer apart at the equator of Eros.
 
    The NLR investigation plans to allocate a portion of the 50 km orbit
    time to cross-track scanning of NLR, using spacecraft maneuvers, to
    obtain a more uniform areal coverage of Eros.  Since the laser
    footprints are overlapping or nearly so at 1 Hz PRF while nadir
    pointed in the 50 km orbit, NLR operations through the first half of
    the rendezvous year will use the 1 Hz mode. Due to a spacecraft
    interface error, the spacecraft overcurrent protection for NLR must
    be switched off when NLR fires at 2 Hz. Nevertheless, NLR may be
    operated in the 2 Hz mode late in the rendezvous year, from the 35
    km circular orbit.
 
    Note
 
    All NLR data after 6/22/00 (2000 204) will appear in the version 7
    NLR format, which is the same as the version 6 normal format (ID =
    4) EXCEPT for the field labeled &apos;CALIBRATION_WORD_1&apos; which has been
    changed.
 
    &apos;CALIBRATION_WORD_1&apos; will take the following values:
    in AutoAcq, &apos;first cal&apos; = 30
    in 1 Hz, &apos;first cal&apos; = 584 (first shot in minor frame 4, at packet
             MET plus 0.5 second)
    in 2 Hz, &apos;first cal&apos; = 364 (usually) but 804 is possible. If 364,
             the first shot was in minor frame 2 (at packet MET plus
             0.25 second). Otherwise, the first shot was in minor frame
             6.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
