<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mag.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MAGNETOMETER for NEAR</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Acuna, M., C.T. Russell, L.J. Zanetti, and B.J. Anderson, The NEAR Magnetic
                   Field Investigation: Science Objectives at Asteroid Eros 433 and Experimental
                   Approach, Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol. 102(E10), pp. 23751-23760, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ACUNAETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Cheng, A.F., A. Santo, K. Heeres, J. Landshof, R. Farquhar, et al., Near-Earth
                   Asteroid Rendezvous: Mission Overview, Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol.
                   102, pp. 23695-23708, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.CHENGETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Kivelson, M., L. Bargatze, K. Khurana, D. Southwood, R. Walker, and P. Coleman,
                   Magnetic Field Signatures Near Galileo&apos;s Closest Approach to Gaspra, Science,
                   Vol. 261, pp. 331-334, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KIVELSONETAL1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Kivelson, M.G., Z. Wang, S. Joy, K.K. Khurana, C. Polanskey, D.J. Southwood,
                   and R.J. Walker, Solar wind interaction with small bodies: 2. What can
                   Galileo&apos;s detection of magnetic rotations tell us about Gaspra and Ida,
                   Advances in Space Research, Vol. 16, Issue 4, pp. 59-68, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KIVELSONETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Lohr, D.A., L.J. Zanetti, B.J. Anderson, T.A. Potemra, J.R. Hayes, R.E. Gold,
                   R.M. Henshaw, F.F. Mobley, D.B. Holland, M.H. Acuna, and J.L. Sheifele, Near
                   Magnetic Field Investigation, Instrumentation, Spacecraft Magnetics and Data
                   Access, Science Reviews, Vol. 82, pp. 255-281, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.LOHRETAL1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Wang, Z., Kivelson, M.G., S. Joy, K.K. Khurana, C. Polanskey, D.J.
                   Southwood, R.J. Walker, Solar wind interaction with small bodies. 2: What
                   can Galileo&apos;s detection of magnetic rotations tell us about Gaspra and
                   Ida, Advances in Space Research (ISSN 0273-1177), vol. 16, no. 4, p.
                   (4)59-(4)68, 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.WANGETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MAGNETOMETER</name>
        <type>Magnetometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    The Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous (NEAR) mission is the first in the
    Discovery Program of low cost planetary and space science missions.
    Its objective is to characterize the S-type near-Earth asteroid 433
    Eros to determine its composition and structure to help understand the
    origin of Eros in particular and near-Earth asteroids in general.
    After achieving rendezvous, NEAR will orbit the asteroid for one year
    conducting extensive observations using infrared and visible
    spectroscopic imaging, X-ray and gamma-ray fluorescence spectroscopy,
    laser ranging and in-situ magnetic field measurements
    [CHENGETAL1997].  The magnetic field experiment (MAG) will be used to
    characterize the magnetization intensity and geometry of 433 Eros as
    described in detail by [ACUNAETAL1997].  This paper describes the
    in-flight calibration activities for MAG including analyses of
    spacecraft magnetic fields and the post-reception processing steps
    developed to remove these effects to yield valid data for scientific
    study. Because Eros is immersed in the magnetized plasma of the solar
    wind, the performance requirements of the MAG instrument are related
    to the orbit distances and the solar wind perturbation signatures
    associated with the asteroid.  During the one year rendezvous, the
    NEAR spacecraft will execute a variety of orbits at Eros to optimize
    the imaging, composition and ranging measurements.  The planned orbit
    radii will range from 400 km down to 35 km, as low as 15 km from the
    asteroid surface.  For NEAR to directly sample Eros&apos; magnetic field,
    the field would have to stand off the solar wind dynamic pressure
    which will average ~2.5 nPa at perihelion (1.13 AU) and ~1 nPa at
    aphelion (1.78 AU), corresponding to magnetic field strengths of 80 nT
    and 50 nT at perihelion and aphelion, respectively.  The goal for MAG
    is to achieve 10% accuracy in a direct detection of Eros&apos; magnetic
    field which is therefore provided by an accuracy of 5 nT.  This is a
    factor of more than 50 less demanding than for space probes designed
    for solar wind studies.
 
    Achieving better than 5 nT accuracy is important for several reasons.
    Signatures of the solar wind interaction due to whistler waves should
    be present near the asteroid [WANGETAL1995] but are expected to be
    only a few nT in magnitude.  Such indirect observations were used to
    infer the magnetic character of Gaspra [KIVELSONETAL1993] and Ida
    [KIVELSONETAL1995].  In addition, if Eros presents a small obstacle, &lt;
    100 km in size, to the solar wind, one expects kinetic plasma
    interactions to play a prominent role in the interaction because solar
    wind protons have gyroradii of ~50 km.  Thus, the solar wind-Eros
    interaction may not be well described by magnetohydrodynamics (MHD)
    and detecting magnetic signatures of a kinetic interaction is highly
    desirable to evaluate the nature of the interaction.  Signatures of a
    kinetic effects are likely to be a few nT or smaller.
 
    Reasonable efforts within cost and schedule constraints were therefore
    made to achieve noise levels below 5 nT.  It turned out that the net
    dynamic magnetic field of the spacecraft field is roughly 10 times
    larger than this (the static field is roughly 190 nT) so that a
    thorough characterization of spacecraft magnetic fields was required.
    A detailed model of the spacecraft magnetic contamination was
    developed that makes extensive use of spacecraft engineering data and
    describes dynamic as well as static field sources.  The spacecraft
    contamination field is subtracted from the measurements in ground
    processing.  Because a detailed magnetic survey of the NEAR spacecraft
    was not performed on the ground, the analysis was performed using data
    obtained during cruise.  This paper documents the methods and results
    of this analysis showing that the ultimate accuracy of the magnetic
    field data returned from NEAR is 1-2 nT in each axis.  The NEAR
    magnetic fields experiment will therefore return direct measurements
    Eros&apos; magnetic field, if its magnetic moment is sufficiently large, as
    well as signatures of the solar wind interaction.
 
 
  Instrument Description
  ========================
    The NEAR magnetometer is described in detail by [LOHRETAL1997] and
    essential instrument characteristics are summarized in Table 1.  The
    instrument consists of a triaxial fluxgate sensor, drive and sense
    electronics with separate 20-bit A/D converters for each axis.  The
    instrument includes eight ranges covering full scale sensitivities
    from +-4 nT to +-65,000 nT.  Pre-flight sensor calibration provided
    absolute gain and cross talk calibration to 0.5% of full scale in each
    range.  Range control can be selected to be either manual or
    automatic.  Automatic range control provides transition to less
    sensitive ranges when any one axis exceeds 87.5% of full scale for
    0.25 seconds and shifts to a higher sensitivity when the field on all
    three axes falls below 17% of full scale continuously for 1 minute.
    This ensures that the instrument will follow rapid increases in field
    strength without toggling between ranges.
 
    The internal instrument sampling is fixed and variable output rates
    are accomplished by a combination of digital filtering and
    subsampling.  The analog voltage outputs are anti-alias filtered with
    a combination of a single pole analog Butterworth low pass filter, 3dB
    attenuation at 10.7 Hz, at the input of each A/D and an IIR filter
    built into the A/D, 3 dB attenuation at 16.7 Hz.  The analog signals
    are sampled continuously by the A/D converters at 20 samples/sec and
    output to the instrument data processing unit (DPU) via gate arrays.
    The same DPU serves both MAG and the Near Infrared Spectrometer (NIS)
    instruments.  Subsequent digital filtering, range control, noise
    rejection, time tagging, formatting and other pre-processing and logic
    control are performed in the DPU.  Intrinsic instrument sensor noise
    is about 1pT.  Time tagging is provided to 0.05 second accuracy and
    the internal timing latency of the instrument including both analog
    delays and digital processing is 0.64 seconds.  Additional known
    latencies are introduced by the on-board digital filters.
 
    To accommodate the data collection strategies of NEAR, the instrument
    sample rate is commandable from 0.01 to 20 samples/sec.  Digital
    filtering commensurate with the output rate is applied for rates down
    to 1 sample/sec.  The filtering calculations are performed on the
    internal 20 bit resolution data.  To avoid integer roundoff
    calculations in the filtering, the data are padded with 5 zeroes and
    the resulting 25 bit integers are carried forward in the 32-bit
    processor.  The output is rounded to 16-bit resolution providing
    digitization step sizes from 0.2pT to 2nT.  To avoid undesirably long
    averaging and to ensure that data are not smeared significantly in
    position relative to Eros, sample rates from 0.5 samples/sec to 0.01
    samples/sec are sub-samples of the 0.5 Hz filtered time series.
    During cruise the instrument is operated in range 3 at the 0.01
    samples/second rate and checkouts (Section 3.1 below) consisting of a
    calibration with the internal bias current, 20 sample/second data
    collection (5 minutes) and anti-alias filter turn-off are performed
    approximately weekly as spacecraft operations allow.  The sampling
    rate at rendezvous will be 1 sample/second and checkouts performed
    weekly as during cruise.
 
    Table 1. NEAR magnetometer characteristics.
    Tri-axial Fluxgate:
            15 kHz drive/30 kHz sense
            1 pT intrinsic rms noise
            Linearity: &lt;1 part in 104
            Selectable electronics calibration bias current
            Survival heater -15-C set point.
            Sensor body mounted on antenna x cm above top deck.
    Sampling:
            20/second internal
            Separate 20 bit A/D for each axis
            Output: 16 bit resolution
            10 Hz anti-alias filter, 3-pole Butterworth
    Ranges: eight selectable
            Range    Full scale (nT)    Resolution, LSB (nT)
            0             +-4                    (a)
            1            +-16                    (a)
            2            +-64                  0.002
            3           +-256                  0.008
            4          +-1,024                 0.031
            5          +-4,096                 0.125
            6         +-16,384                 0.500
            7         +-65,536                 2.000
    Software:
            RTX-2010RH, 32 bit, FORTH language
            Output sample rates:
               Sub-sampled 1/2 Hz filter: 0.01,0.02,0.05,0.1,0.2,0.5/s
               Filtered (fNyquist=1/2 rate):  1, 2, 5, 10/s
               No digital filtering:  20/s
            Filtering:
               Butterworth IIR, 25 bit resolution
               0.5, 1.0, 2.5, 5.0 Hz fNyquist
            Ranging:
               Automatic:  max/min F.S.:  87.5%/17%
               Manual
            Other:
               Noise rejection, range offsets, sample synch. pulse.
    Resources:
            Mass, power:   1.5 Kg, 1.7 W (not including DPU)
            Data rate:  65 bits/sample, 5.6 Mbits/day at 1/s
 
    (a) Limited by intrinsic 1 pT instrument noise.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
