<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
	xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
	 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 	xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rexis.orex</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>The Regolith X-Ray Imaging Spectrometer (REXIS) onboard the OSIRIS-REx spacecraft</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-03-14</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>Initial version</description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.orex</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                R.A. Masterson, M. Chodas, L. Bayley, B. Allen, J. Hong, P. Biswas, C. McMenamin, K. Stout, 
                E. Bokhour, H. Bralower, D. Carte, S. Chen, M. Jones, S.Kissel, H. Schmidt, M. Smith, G. Sondecker, 
                L.F. Lim, D.S. Lauretta, J. Grindlay, and R.P. Binzel, Regolith X-Ray Imaging Spectrometer 
                (REXIS) Aboard the OSIRIS-REx Asteroid Sample Return Mission, Space Science Reviews, 2018, submitted
            </reference_text>
            <description>The OVIRS instrument paper.</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Instrument>
        <name>REXIS</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type>
        <description>The Regolith X-ray Imaging Spectrometer (REXIS) will provide an X-ray map of Bennu, complementing
        core OSIRIS-REx mission science. REXIS has been selected as an education and public outreach element
        of the OSIRIS-REx mission investigation after a competitive selection process. As a Student Collaboration
        Experiment (SCE), REXIS will be incorporated into the OSIRIS-REx spacecraft on a non-impact basis and
        will remain clearly separable from the rest of the OSIRIS-REx investigation. Data analysis will be handled
        as a student project, available to both Harvard and MIT students, for credit or non-credit within the MIT
        curriculum, and within the MIT Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program (UROP). 
        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
