<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:orad.p12</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>ORBITING RADAR for P12</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.p12::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Pioneer Venus Orbiter Radar Mapper (ORAD) user&apos;s manual,
                   Hughes Aircraft Company, Ref. No. D4232, December 1977.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.HACREF1977</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Pettengill, G.H., D.F. Horwood, and C.H. Keller, Pioneer
                   Venus Orbiter Radar Mapper: design and operation, IEEE
                   Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens., GE-18, 28-32, 1980.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.PETTENGILLETAL1980A</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>ORBITING RADAR</name>
        <type>Radio-Radar</type> <!--RChen/EN was RADAR. No obvious choice-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
    INSTRUMENT: ORBITING RADAR
    SPACECRAFT: PIONEER VENUS ORBITER
 
 
    Instrument Information
    ======================
      Instrument Id                  : ORAD
      Instrument Host Id             : P12
      Pi Pds User Id                 : PFORD
      Instrument Name                : ORBITING RADAR
      Instrument Type                : RADAR MAPPER
      Build Date                     : 1977
      Instrument Mass                : 9.700000
      Instrument Length              : 0.240000
      Instrument Width               : 0.305000
      Instrument Height              : 0.165000
      Instrument Serial Number       : 5970-02
      Instrument Manufacturer Name   : HUGHES AIRCRAFT
 
 
    Instrument Description
    ======================
      The Pioneer Venus radar mapper consisted of a 38 cm antenna and
      a radar transmitter/receiver, and was flown on the Pioneer 12
      orbiter.  It functioned continuously from December 5th 1978
      until March 23 1981 when it was switched off because spacecraft
      periapsis had risen to such an extent that no further useful
      data could be obtained.  The antenna could be rotated in one
      plane by means of a stepping motor that was commanded by the
      radar system.  During a periapsis pass, the antenna was moved
      so that it pointed to the nadir at some point during each 12
      second spacecraft rotation period.  The radar was loaded from
      the ground with approximately 200 commands before each mapping
      pass, and then operated automatically.  The commands included
      interpolation coefficients that set the altimeter range window,
      the receiver band-pass filter, and the receiver gain.  The
      instrument was capable of making up to 8 observations during
      each 12 second period: space calibration, 1 or 4 altimetry
      measurements, 0, 1 or 2 imaging measurements, and a planet
      calibration.  The number of altimetry and image measurements
      depended on spacecraft altitude and the downlink bandwidth
      allotted to the radar instrument.  Initial altimetry and
      imaging data processing was performed on-board.  Altimetry
      echoes were detected, sampled, and correlated against the
      transmitted waveform, a shift-register sequence, and sub-summed
      for repeated pulses.  Imaging echoes were detected, sampled,
      and Fourier transformed to achieve azimuth resolution.
 
 
    Science Objectives
    ==================
      The radar mapper was designed to obtain a near global picture
      of the topography, meter-scale surface slopes and reflectivity
      of Venus.  Constraints imposed by the choice of orbit limited
      the radar coverage to a latitude band lying between 74 degrees
      N and 61 degrees S completely around the planet.  In addition
      to the altimetry objectives, the experiment sought an image of
      the radar scattering properties of the surface at oblique
      incidence.  Sensitivity limited the imaged region to a band
      around the planet lying between 45 degrees N and 10 degrees S.
      Altimetric error was less than 200 meters; altimetric surface
      &apos;footprint&apos; size varied from about 10 km in diameter at a
      spacecraft altitude of 200 km, to 50 km at a maximum altitude
      of 4700 km.  Imaging resolution varied from 20 to 40 km,
      depending on spacecraft altitude.
 
 
    Operational Considerations
    ==========================
      (1) Shortly after it began operating, a failure was observed in
      telemetry from the instrument that affected all altimetric and
      imaging data.  This was traced to a circuit failure in the data
      formatter sub-system, and was totally eliminated by operating
      the radar on a shortened duty cycle, viz.  that all power to
      the radar was switched off except for a 2 hour period each day.
      This proved entirely successful, although about 36 days of data
      were lost while the problem was being diagnosed.  (2) It was
      originally intended that, when the radar was performing 4
      altimetry measurements per spacecraft rotation period, they
      should be made with varying receiver frequencies, thereby
      &apos;squinting&apos; the altimeter footprints ahead of, and behind, the
      nadir point.  This proved to be unwise, since the squinted
      echoes had very low signal strength, so, after approximately 3
      months of operation, the radar was commanded no to vary the
      receiver frequency and the 4 altimeter measurements represented
      essentially the same surface footprint.
 
 
    Calibration Description
    =======================
      The instrument was calibrated by means of a radar target
      simulator that was specially built by Hughes, and end-to-end
      tests of the radar system were conducted on several occasions,
      including the on-stand test shortly prior to launch.  The
      results were published in the Hughes instrument manual.  In
      Venus orbit, the instrument was calibrated once per 12 second
      spacecraft rotation period by recording the receiver voltage at
      that time when the antenna pointed to the zenith, i.e.  to cold
      sky.
 
 
    Section &apos;ALT&apos;
    =============
      Total Fovs                     : 0
      Data Rate                      : 24.000000
      Sample Bits                    : 10
 
 
      &apos;ALT&apos; Detectors
      ---------------
        PVORADANT
 
 
      &apos;ALT&apos; Electronics
      -----------------
        PVORADCTL
 
 
      In modes
      --------
        HAA
        IM1
        IM2
 
 
      &apos;ALT&apos; Section Parameter &apos;RADAR ECHO POWER&apos;
      ------------------------------------------
        That part of the transmitted power scattered by the target
        and received by the radar antenna.
 
        Instrument Parameter Name      : RADAR ECHO POWER
        Sampling Parameter Name        : TIME
        Instrument Parameter Unit      : WATTS
        Minimum Sampling Parameter     : 0.009000
        Maximum Sampling Parameter     : 0.030000
        Sampling Parameter Interval    : 0.000004
        Sampling Parameter Resolution  : 0.000004
        Sampling Parameter Unit        : SECOND
 
 
    Section &apos;IMG&apos;
    =============
      Total Fovs                     : 0
      Data Rate                      : 309.000000
      Sample Bits                    : 10
 
 
      &apos;IMG&apos; Detectors
      ---------------
        PVORADANT
 
 
      &apos;IMG&apos; Electronics
      -----------------
        PVORADCTL
 
 
      In modes
      --------
        IM1
        IM2
 
 
      &apos;IMG&apos; Section Parameter &apos;RADAR ECHO POWER&apos;
      ------------------------------------------
        That part of the transmitted power scattered by the target
        and received by the radar antenna.
 
        Instrument Parameter Name      : RADAR ECHO POWER
        Sampling Parameter Name        : TIME
        Instrument Parameter Unit      : WATTS
        Minimum Sampling Parameter     : 0.009000
        Maximum Sampling Parameter     : 0.030000
        Sampling Parameter Interval    : 0.000128
        Sampling Parameter Resolution  : 0.000128
        Sampling Parameter Unit        : SECOND
 
 
    Section &apos;RAD&apos;
    ============
      Total Fovs                     : 1
      Data Rate                      : 1.300000
 
 
      &apos;RAD&apos; Detectors
      ---------------
        PVORADANT
 
 
      &apos;RAD&apos; Electronics
      -----------------
        PVORADCTL
 
 
      In modes
      --------
        HAA
        IM1
        IM2
 
 
      &apos;RAD&apos; Section FOV Shape &apos;ELLIPSOIDAL&apos;
      -------------------------------------
        Section Id                     : RAD
        Fovs                           : 1
        Horizontal Pixel Fov           : 29.000000
        Vertical Pixel Fov             : 25.000000
        Horizontal Fov                 : 29.000000
        Vertical Fov                   : 25.000000
 
 
      &apos;RAD&apos; Section Parameter &apos;RADIANCE&apos;
      ----------------------------------
        Radiance is the amount of energy per time per projected area
        per steradian.
 
        Instrument Parameter Name      : RADIANCE
        Sampling Parameter Name        : TIME
        Instrument Parameter Unit      : WATTS/AREA/STERADIANS
        Minimum Instrument Parameter   : 0.010000
        Maximum Instrument Parameter   : 10.230000
        Noise Level                    : 0.050000
        Sampling Parameter Interval    : 12.000000
        Sampling Parameter Unit        : SECOND
 
 
    Instrument Detector &apos;PVORADANT&apos;
    ===============================
      Detector Type                  : ANTENNA
      Detector Aspect Ratio          : 1.000000
      Minimum Wavelength             : 170000.000000
      Maximum Wavelength             : 170000.000000
      Nominal Operating Temperature  : 298.000000
 
 
      Description
      -----------
        Transmitter and receiver use the same detector: a 13 cm
        linearly polarized short-backfire antenna.  The 3dB one-way
        beamwidth is 29 degrees in the E-plane and 25 degrees in the
        H plane.  In normal operation, the E-field is tangent to the
        Venus surface and the H-field is normal to the Venus surface.
        The antenna is mounted on the periphery of the instrument
        bay, at an azimuth of 45 degrees relative to the spacecraft
        X-axis.  It is articulated in one direction and moves under
        control of a stepping motor commanded by the radar command
        processor.
 
 
      Sensitivity
      -----------
        Measured antenna gain was 17 dB.  The first sidelobe was 16
        dB less than peak, and the sidelobe level at 90 degrees was
        29 dB relative to peak.  3dB beamwidth was 29 degrees for the
        E-plane and 25 degrees for the H-plane.
 
 
    Instrument Electronics &apos;PVORADCTL&apos;
    ==================================
 
      Description
      -----------
        The radar electronics consisted of a series of closely
        coupled sub-units: (a) RF sub-system, consisting of receiver,
        transmitter, up- and down-converters, and digital frequency
        synthesizer, (b) Synchronizer sub-system, containing a
        command processor, ephemeris generator to calculate the
        range-gate settings, timing circuits, and electronics to
        control the antenna stepping motor, (c) Radar Processor
        sub-system, that detects, samples, and formats the echoes,
        and (d) Power Supply sub-system.
 
 
    Instrument Mode &apos;HAA&apos;
    =====================
      Data Path Type                 : REALTIME
      Instrument Power Consumption   : 30.000000
 
 
      In sections
      -----------
        ALT
        RAD
 
 
      Description
      -----------
        High-altitude altimetry mode.  Above 700 km altitude, the
        altimeter is making a single range measurement per 12 second
        spacecraft rotation period.
 
 
    Instrument Mode &apos;HAA&apos;
    =====================
      Data Path Type                 : REALTIME
      Instrument Power Consumption   : 30.000000
 
 
      In sections
      -----------
        ALT
        RAD
 
 
      Description
      -----------
        High-altitude altimetry mode.  Above 700 km altitude, the
        altimeter is making a single range measurement per 12 second
        spacecraft rotation period.
 
 
    Instrument Mode &apos;IM1&apos;
    =====================
      Data Path Type                 : REALTIME
      Instrument Power Consumption   : 30.000000
 
 
      In sections
      -----------
        ALT
        IMG
        RAD
 
 
      Description
      -----------
        Altimetry and single-sided imaging mode.  Below 700 km
        altitude, the altimeter is making 4 range measurements, and
        the SAR is making a map on one side, for each 12 second
        spacecraft rotation period.
 
 
    Instrument Mode &apos;IM1&apos;
    =====================
      Data Path Type                 : REALTIME
      Instrument Power Consumption   : 30.000000
 
 
      In sections
      -----------
        ALT
        IMG
        RAD
 
 
      Description
      -----------
        Altimetry and single-sided imaging mode.  Below 700 km
        altitude, the altimeter is making 4 range measurements, and
        the SAR is making a map on one side, for each 12 second
        spacecraft rotation period.
 
 
    Instrument Mode &apos;IM2&apos;
    =====================
      Data Path Type                 : REALTIME
      Instrument Power Consumption   : 30.000000
 
 
      In sections
      -----------
        ALT
        IMG
        RAD
 
 
    Instrument Mode &apos;IM2&apos;
    =====================
      Data Path Type                 : REALTIME
      Instrument Power Consumption   : 30.000000
 
 
      In sections
      -----------
        ALT
        IMG
        RAD
 
 
    Mounted On Platform &apos;PIONEER VENUS ORBITER&apos;
    ===========================================
 
      Description
      -----------
        Please see Spacecraft Description.
 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
