<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:pal.vwt</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Venus Wind Tunnel</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-12-18</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Initial version under new LID naming convention.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:laboratory.pal</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_facility</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
        
    <Instrument>
        <name>Venus Wind Tunnel</name>
        <type>Atmospheric Sciences</type>
        <subtype>Wind Tunnel</subtype>
        <description>
One of several wind tunnels operated by Arizona State University at the Planetary Aeolian Laboratory at NASA Ames Research 
Laboratory, Moffett Field, CA, Building N242. This wind tunnel is no longer in operation - It was refit as the Titan Wind 
Tunnel in 2010.
 
A wind tunnel capable of simulating the aeolian environment on Venus at NASA Ames Research Center as part of the Aeolian 
Consortium. The tunnel began operation in 1982 and consisted of a closed-circuit wind tunnel approximately 6 m long by 
3 m wide. The experiment test section is about 700 cm long by 20 cm in diameter. The working fluid in the tunnel was carbon
dioxide; for venusian simulations, the tunnel operated at 35 bar pressure, which at ambient temperature produces the same 
fluid density (the critical parameter for most aeolian processes) for carbon dioxide as at 90 bar and 735 K, the nominal 
venusian environment. The tunnel was used primarily for conducting particle threshold experiments, studying ripple dynamics, 
and determining particle fluxes and velocities.
        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
