<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.sch"
 schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context
 xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1
  https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:meca_elec.phx</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MECA COMMON ELECTRONICS for PHX</title>
        <information_model_version>1.10.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-05-23</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>Changed logical_identifier from meca_elec__phx to meca_elec.phx</description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.phx</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Hecht, M.H., J. Marshall, W.T. Pike, U. Staufer, D. Blaney, D. Braendlin, S.
                   Gautsch, W. Goetz, H.-R. Hidber, H.U. Keller, W.J. Markiewicz, A. Mazer, T.P.
                   Meloy, J.M. Morookian, C. Mogensen, D. Parrat, P.H. Smith, H. Sykulska, R.J.
                   Tanner, A. Tonin, S. Vijendran, M. Weilert, P.M. Woida, Microscopy capabilities
                   of the Microscopy, Electrochemistry, and Conductivity Analyzer (MECA),
                   submitted to J. Geophys. Res., 2008.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.HECHTETAL2008</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Kounaves, S.P. M.H. Hecht, S.J. West, J.M. Morookian, S.M.M. Young, R. Quinn,
                   P. Grunthaner, X. Wen, M. Weilert, C. Cable, A. Fisher, K. Gospodinova, J.
                   Kapit, S. Stroble, P.-C. Hsu, B.C. Clark, D.W. Ming, and P. Smith, The 2007
                   Phoenix Mars Scout Lander MECA Wet Chemistry Laboratory, J. Geophys. Res., in
                   press, 2008.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KOUNAVESETAL2008</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Zent, A., M.H. Hecht, D. Cobos, G. Cardell, M.C. Foote, S.E. Woods, M. Mehta.
                   The Thermal Electrical Conductivity Probe (TECP) for Phoenix, J. Geophys. Res.,
                   in press, 2008.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ZENTETAL2008</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MECA COMMON ELECTRONICS</name>
        <type>Regolith Properties</type> <!--RChen/EN was Electronics-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
    The MECA instrument suite on the Phoenix spacecraft returns 15
    distinct unchannelized telemetry types, of which three are common to
    all the component instruments (microscopes, chemistry laboratories, and
    thermal and electrical properties probe). These are types 4
    (CME_STATUS), 5 (POWER_DATA), and 6 (TABLES).
 
    Type 4 is a direct response from the FPGA that controls all aspects
    of MECA operations. The most common usage of this telemetry type is as
    a reply to routine requests including turning on LEDs for imaging,
    moving the microscope sample stage, deploying a chemistry actuator
    (sample drawer, water release, or stirring motor), or simply a status
    inquiry. The data return provides not only confirmation that the
    requested operation occurred, but specific information necessary for
    calibration, such as the position of the stage when the atomic force
    microscope is engaged. A second usage of this telemetry type is in
    response to a &apos;raw&apos; command, a direct instruction to the FPGA to execute
    any of its allowed functions. While not recommended for routine science
    measurements, this mode is often used for operations that are not
    performed in the desired sequence by the standard flight software
    commands. Notably, this may include voltammetry and potentiometry
    measurements in the chemistry cells, in which case the Type 4 return
    contains primary science data.
 
    Type 5 data returns the voltage and current provided by the primary
    MECA 5V (load and logic) and 15V (load and AFM) power supplies. These
    results are diagnostic of the functioning of all subsystems and should
    be indicative of many anomalous conditions.
 
    Type 6 data returns, on request, the contents of any of six tables
    that modify the operation of the MECA flight software (FSW). These
    include a state table which is autonomously maintained by FSW as well
    as several tables that can only be set by explicit user command. These
    user-maintained tables contain the values and allowed ranges of
    parameters and attributes that define the implementation of each
    experiment. For microscopy, for example, they might define the
    different substrate positions on the sample wheel as well as the
    optimal focus position. Download of these latter tables is for the
    purpose of confirmation that the actual parameters of an experiment
    were set as intended.
 
    More information is found in HECHTETAL2008, KOUNAVESETAL2008, and
    ZENTETAL2008.
 
  Scientific Objectives
  =====================
    N/A
 
  Calibration
  ===========
    N/A
 
  Operational Considerations
  ==========================
 
    N/A
 
  Detectors and Electronics
  =========================
 
    MECA flight software (FSW) runs on the primary spacecraft computer and
    communicates to MECA hardware at 9600 baud via a serial Payload and
    Attitude Control Interface(PACI) interface. On the other side of that
    interface is an FPGA, located on the Command and Measurement
    Electronics (CME) board inside the MECA enclosure. The FPGA controls
    all hardware functions in the MECA suite with the exception of the
    Atomic Force Microscope (AFM), which has an embedded processor, and
    discreet switches, controlled directly by the spacecraft computer, for
    powering MECA and for switching between AFM processor and FPGA. Data
    return described here is generated by the FPGA.
 
  Filters
  =======
    N/A
 
  Optics
  ======
    N/A
 
  Location on spacecraft
  ======================
 
    Information described here is returned by the FPGA on the Command and
    Measurement Electronics (CME) board, which is located inside the MECA
    enclosure on the spacecraft deck.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
