<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:pvo.onms</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>ORBITER NEUTRAL MASS SPECTROMETER for PVO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-08-26</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.pvo::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Hedin, A.E., H.B. Niemann, W.T. Kasprzak and A. Seiff, Global Empirical
                   Model of the Venus Thermosphere, Journal of Geophysical Research, vol. 88,
                   73-83, 1983.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.HEDINETAL1983</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Niemann, H.B., J.R.Booth, J.E. Cooley, R.E. Hartle, W.T. Kasprzak,
                   N.W.Spencer, S.H. Way, D.M. Hunten and G.R. Carignan, Pioneer Venus
                   Orbiter Neutral Gas Mass Spectrometer, IEEE Trans. on Geoscience and
                   Remote Sensing, vol. GE-18 (1), 60-65, 1980.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.NIEMANNETAL1980B</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>ORBITER NEUTRAL MASS SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Mass Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
      The ONMS instrument is a quadrupole mass spectrometer with an
      electron impact ion source for measurement of neutral gas
      composition in the mass range 1 to 46 amu.  The sensor consists
      of an ion source, a quadrupole mass filter and secondary
      electron multiplier as an ion detector.  The ion source is
      partially enclosed and exposed to the ambient atmosphere of
      neutral and ion particles through an entrance aperture.  Just
      inside the aperture is the ion repeller grid at 36 V above
      spacecraft ground designed to reject ions of this energy or
      less.  On either side of the ion repeller grid is a grid at
      -4.3 V designed to reject low energy electrons.  Neutral gas
      particles are not influenced by these grid potentials.  They
      pass through to the ionization region where a small fraction
      are ionized by electron impact from an electrostatically
      focused electron beam generated by a hot filament.  The ions
      are then focused into the quadrupole analyzer for separation
      according to mass to charge ratio.  The ion source grid
      assembly can also function as a retarding potential analyzer
      (RPA) for analysis of direct streaming particles that have not
      had any surface collisions.  With the filament off and the ion
      repeller set to 0 V, the sensor can detect thermal ions.  With
      the ion repeller set to 36 V, superthermal ions exceeding this
      energy can be detected.
 
      There are two selectable electron energies which can be used to
      identify neutral species based on the mass spectral cracking
      patterns.  The ionization and dissociation cross sections are a
      function of electron energy.  Mass spectra are simplified at
      lower electron energy but with a considerable loss in
      ionization efficiency.
 
      The ion source enclosure is such that it can function as a
      closed or an open source.  The neutral particle density in the
      ionization region consists of direct streaming particles and
      particles which have been reflected from the surfaces.  As a
      closed source, the neutral particle flux into the enclosure is
      balanced by the thermalized flux exiting the enclosure.  The
      thermalized flux results from particles colliding many times
      with the ion source surfaces.  This increased ram pressure
      results in a significant increase (about 60 for N2) over the
      ambient pressure of the species and lowers the detection
      threshold.  Species such as O and N chemically react on the
      surfaces forming O2 and NO.  The open source measures direct
      streaming particles that have not had surface collisions.  The
      view cone for the open source in the ionization region has a
      half angle of about 38 degrees.  The detection threshold for
      this mode is higher than that for the closed source since the
      ambient density is directly detected.  A retarding potential
      field is used to discriminate between direct streaming
      particles at spacecraft energy and surface reflected particles
      at a much lower energy.
 
      A radio frequency electromagnetic field is used to select a
      given mass to charge ratio ion.  Mass peak (mass/charge ratio)
      selection is accomplished through a proper combination of the
      ac and dc voltages applied to the hyperbolic rods.  Resolution
      is determined by the ratio of the ac to dc amplitude.  The
      peaks produced are flat topped and stepping from one mass peak
      to the other can be accomplished without requiring peak
      searching.
 
      A secondary electron multiplier is used as a detector operating
      either in a pulse counting mode or a current measuring mode.
      Either value can be output to the telemetry stream.  Normally
      the pulse counter values are output as long as the electrometer
      current does not exceed a given value.
 
      The sensor itself is constructed of stainless steel and was
      sealed under vacuum prior to delivery for launch.  A small ion
      getter pump was used to maintain the vacuum below 1.E-4 pascal.
      The ion source was covered by a metal-ceramic break-off cap
      which was removed by a pyrotechnic actuator after orbit
      insertion.
 
      The basic instrument data consists of a mass number being
      sampled, pulse counter or electrometer data, RPA mode type, and
      housekeeping data.  Proper operation of the instrument is
      verified through its housekeeping data.
 
      Data accumulation is always done at equally spaced time
      intervals.  Each 16 bit telemetry represents one reading
      obtained over an integration time determined by the spacecraft
      bit rate and format.  The individual 8 bit telemetry words
      assigned to the ONMS in a minor frame are not equally spaced in
      time.  Therefore, the data has to be stored internally for a
      period of time and then sent to the telemetry.  The storage and
      readout are accomplished through the use of two memories.  One
      memory is reading out unequally spaced data to the spacecraft
      telemetry system while the other is accumulating equally spaced
      data from the instrument.  Both memories are first in, first
      out (FIFO) type and are switched simultaneously.  The time
      interval over which the ONMS data is accumulated in memory
      depends on the spacecraft bit rate, format, and spin segment
      status.  With no spin segment, the memories are switched on at
      a minor frame beginning, data is accumulated for one minor
      frame and then read out to the telemetry system during the next
      minor frame.  With spin segment mode commanded, the data is
      accumulated at four times the rate of the no spin segment mode
      and at equally spaced time intervals from -45 degrees to +45
      degrees roll angle relative to the ONMS velocity ram direction.
      The memory switch time and data accumulation start time are
      determined from the spacecraft RAM pulse, which is assumed to
      represent the maximum velocity ram for the spacecraft +X axis
      (0 degrees spacecraft azimuth angle), and the ONMS azimuth
      angle.
 
      The ONMS has telemetry words in the formats PERC (6 words),
      PERB (14 words), and APOB (2 words).  Each word consists of 8
      bits.  The length of the data cycle for housekeeping data is
      128 words.  The unit of 64 16-bit words contains all of the
      information to determine the current command status, monitor
      values, etc., and is the basic unit of processing for the data.
      In addition to the internal monitors read out by the instrument
      electronics, other monitors are available from the spacecraft
      telemetry which do not require the ONMS to be operating:
      instrument temperature, bus voltage and instrument on/off
      status.
 
      A summary of the instrument parameters are as follows:
 
      Ion source: closed/open with particle retarding
                    deployment by metal-ceramic break off cap,
                    pyrotechnically activated
                  electron impact ionization
                  dual filaments,  20 ua emission
                  electron energy 27 eV or 70 eV
 
      Analyzer:   quadrupole mass filter, hyperbolic rods 7.5 cm long,
                  field radius 0.2 cm
                  rf frequency 5.6 mhz
 
      Detector:   secondary electron multiplier, copper-beryllium,
                    box and grid design, pulse counting up to about
                    852000 counts/sec (0.160 ua current)
                  current measurement from 0.160 ua to 15 ua minimum
                  detectable signal is 1 count per integration period
                  multiplier noise signal &lt; 1 count / minute
 
      Total detector dynamic range: 1.3E7
 
      Resolution/crosstalk: &lt; 1.E-4
 
      Mass range: 1 to 46 amu
 
      Mass measurement modes: programmed mass, 8 individual mass
                    numbers, 1 to 46 amu unit sweep,
                    1 to 46 in steps of 1 amu 1/8 unit sweep,
                    1 to 46 in steps of 0.125 amu
 
      Sample rates:
       a) Normal mode
          equally time spaced samples for all spacecraft spin angles
          6 samples/sec with nominal bit rate 1024 bits/sec and
                PERC format
          actual sample rate dependent on spacecraft telemetry
              format and bit rate used
       b) Spin segment mode
          equally time spaced samples for 45 degrees with respect to
               occurrence of velocity ram
          effective data rate 4 times the normal rate
 
      Number of words in telemetry format per minor frame:
        PERB: 14 8-bit words
        PERC:  6 8-bit words
        APOB:  2 8-bit words
        1 minor frame = 64*8 bits
 
      Integration time: 0.171875 s maximum, 0.006 s minimum
 
      The spacecraft orbit is nearly polar (105.6 degrees
      inclination) with periapsis near the equator (17 degrees north
      celestial latitude) and has an average period of 24.03 hours.
      The local time of periapsis increases 1.6 degrees/day (or
      orbit) so that it takes 224.7 days to sample one complete
      diurnal cycle (dayside, evening terminator, nightside, and
      morning terminator).  For the first 600 orbits, the altitude of
      periapsis varied from 142 km to 250 km.  After this period, the
      periapsis altitude was no longer controlled and increased in
      altitude as a result of solar gravitational perturbations.  The
      spacecraft spins with a nominal period of 12 seconds about an
      axis which points approximately toward the south ecliptic pole.
 
 
    Operational Modes
    =================
      Currently there are three distinct types of data that can be
      acquired by the ONMS instrument: Neutral density, superthermal
      ion flux and thermal ion density.  Independent of these three
      data types, there are a number of modes in which the data can
      be taken as well as a number of modes in which the instrument
      can be configured and tuned.  Generally speaking these
      of the instrument.
 
      Data measurement types:
        Neutral gas composition: closed source
          open source with particle retarding
        Ion composition: superthermal ions &gt; 36 eV  relative to
            spacecraft ground (ion repeller set to 36 V)
          normal ions  &gt; 0 V relative to spacecraft
            ground (ion repeller set to 0 V)
 
      Detection ranges{(1)}:
        Neutral composition:
          N2 sensitivity: 5.E4 (particles/cm**3) / (count/sec)
          Open source density range: 3.E5 to 4.E12 particles/cm**3
            for N2
          Closed source density range: 5.E3 to 7.E10 particles/cm**3
            for N2
        Superthermal (&gt;36 eV) ions:
          O+ sensitivity: 4.E3 (particles/cm**2/sec)/(count/sec)
          O+ flux range for 40 eV ions: 2.E4 to 3.E11
            particles/cm**2/sec
          O+ density range for 40 eV ions: 0.01 to 1.E5
            particles/cm**3
        Thermal ions:
          O+ sensitivity: 0.02 (particles/cm**3)/(counts/sec),
            normalized to OIMS
          O+ density range: 0.02 to 2.6E5 particles/cm**3
            for a spacecraft speed of 9.6 km/s
 
      (1) Based on minimum count rate, detector dynamic
          range and instrument sensitivity for mode used
 
      The instrument configuration modes:
 
        a) Ion source:
           Two different electron energies can be selected by
           command.  Ions can also be measured with the filament off.
           An ion repeller grid just inside the entrance aperture at
           36 V or 0 V rejects positive ions of this energy or less.
           Neutral gas particles are not affected by the 36 V grid
           potential and pass through into the ionization region.
 
        b) Retarding potential analyzer:
           Retarding and non-retarding modes can be commanded
           separately along with a mode in which they alternate. A
           retarding potential sweep through a range of retarding
           voltages is also commandable and is considered an
           engineering diagnostic tool.  The retarding voltage is
           VR=O+G*M where the offset O and and the gain G each have 4
           separate commandable levels, and M is the mass number in
           amu. The retarding sweep voltage is VR=O+0.0103*(64-S)
           where D is a fixed value and S is number 1...64.  For
           reference a spacecraft speed of 9.8 km/s corresponds to an
           energy of 8 eV.
 
        c) Quadrupole analyzer:
           Tuning on the peak and mass resolution are separately
           commandable with 4 different values.  Mass peak desired can
           be programmed as 8 selectable mass numbers, a unit amu
           sweep, and 1/8 amu sweep. The latter is primarily an
           engineering tool to check tuning and resolution. The unit
           sweep is a species survey mode, and programmed mass mode is
           used to concentrate on high time resolution measurements of
           particular species.
 
        d) Secondary electron multiplier detector:
           There are 4 selectable gain values determined from four
           commandable high voltage levels.
 
        e) Pulse counter discriminator:
           There are 4 commandable discriminator levels used in
           counting the individual multiplier pulses.  A commandable
           mode is available to alternately read out pulse counter and
           electrometer values for multiplier gain measurements.
 
    Unsupported Keywords
    ====================
     INSTRUMENT_ID               = ONMS
     INSTRUMENT_NAME             = &apos;ORBITER NEUTRAL MASS SPECTROMETER&apos;
     INSTRUMENT_TYPE             = &apos;QUADRUPOLE MASS SPECTROMETER&apos;
     PI_PDS_USER_ID              = HNIEMANN
     NAIF_INSTRUMENT_ID          = &apos;N/A&apos;
     BUILD_DATE                  = 1977
     INSTRUMENT_MASS             = 3.8 &lt;kg&gt;
     INSTRUMENT_HEIGHT           = 28 &lt;cm&gt;
     INSTRUMENT_LENGTH           = 35 &lt;cm&gt;
     INSTRUMENT_WIDTH            = 15 &lt;cm&gt;
     INSTRUMENT_MANUFACTURER_NAME = &apos;Goddard Space Flight Center&apos;
     INSTRUMENT_SERIAL_NUMBER    = &apos;Flight Unit&apos;
 
      REFERENCES
      ----------
      Niemann, H.B., J.R. Booth, J.E. Cooley, R.E. Hartle, W.T.
      Kasprzak, N.W. Spencer, S.H. Way, D.M.  Hunten, G.R. Carignan,
      Pioneer Venus Orbiter Neutral Mass Spectrometer Experiment,
      IEEE Trans. Geo. Rem. Sens., _GE-18_, 60-65, 1980.
      [NIEMANNETAL1980B]
 
 
    Scientific Objectives
    =====================
      The prime mission of the Orbiter Neutral Mass Spectrometer
      (ONMS) is to perform in-situ measurements of the neutral gas
      composition and its variation with altitude and local solar
      time in the thermosphere and exosphere of Venus.  Measurements
      of these variations are important in defining the dynamical,
      chemical and thermal state of the upper atmosphere.  When the
      periapsis altitude is below about 250 km, the neutral densities
      of helium, atomic oxygen, atomic nitrogen, molecular nitrogen,
      carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide are measured.  Gas kinetic
      temperatures can be derived from an analysis of the density
      scale heights.  Wave-like perturbations consistent with gravity
      waves can be observed after removal of the altitude variation
      in the data.  Neutral density data were taken during orbit
      1-645 and during orbits 4954-5055.
 
      Superthermal ions with energy &gt; 36 eV in the spacecraft
      reference have also been detected.  Ions of this energy have
      sufficient energy to escape the planet and represent an
      atmospheric loss.  They have been observed in the near tail
      region and near the dayside ionopause.  The ions were first
      detected in orbits associated with measurements of the neutral
      density and are evidenced as erratic signals above the usual
      gas background signal at high altitudes.  The ions must have an
      energy exceeding the voltage on the ion repeller grid (36 V) in
      order to be detected.  The ion composition can be determined
      and consists of mainly O+ with traces of He+, N+, CO+ and/or
      N2+, NO+ and O2+.  CO2+ occurs very rarely.  H+ is not
      measurable with the current instrument configuration.  After
      the first 935 orbits, when the altitude of periapsis was above
      300 km and the neutral atmosphere could no longer be measured,
      the instrument was configured to perform measurements of the
      superthermal ions with the filament off and ion repeller at 36
      V.  The direction of the ion flow in the ecliptic plane can
      also be determined from the spin modulation of the data.
 
      Thermal ions can also be measured with the filament off and the
      ion repeller set at 0 V.  Species observed include He+, N+, O+,
      CO+ and/or N2+, NO+, O2+ and CO2+.  H+ is not measurable with
      the current instrument configuration.  One component of the ion
      drift in the ecliptic plane can also be determined.  Thermal
      ion measurements have been taken sporadically at the end of
      neutral density passes and on alternate orbits when
      superthermal ions are not being measured.
 
      The ONMS instrument was not operated on all orbits and some
      orbits are devoted to engineering studies.  Typically neutral
      density passes occupied -40 min.  to +30 min.  relative to the
      time of periapsis.  Ion and superthermal ion mode passes
      typically are 15 to 20 minutes in duration on either side of
      periapsis.  Neutral density passes during entry also took about
      this same amount of time.
 
 
    Operational Considerations
    ==========================
      Instrument commanding: cannot directly command filament A to B;
        must turn-off filament between A and B
        cannot use highest multiplier voltage;
        current levels too high
        cannot use spin segment mode in PERB format and
          bit rates exceeding 1024 bps;
        4K memory overflow;
        cannot use it when less than one housekeeping cycle is
          stored in memory
 
      Maximum signal limitations: filament is shut off if detector
          multiplier current exceeds 15 ua
 
 
    Calibration
    ===========
      Initial testing of the retarding and ion modes was done using a
      low energy, 0-25 eV, ion beam.  Gas calibrations to establish
      the closed source neutral density were performed over the
      pressure ranges expected in flight.  This calibration
      established the overall relation between the thermalized
      particle density in the ionizing region and the electronics
      telemetry output.  Gases used for calibration were CO2, N2, O2,
      Ar, He, CO and NO.  The calibrations established mass spectral
      cracking patterns, low and high electron energy sensitivities,
      pulse counter dead time correction, ratio of electron
      multiplier count rate and current output, tuning and mass
      resolution characteristics.
 
      Comparison of the ONMS neutral densities with mass density
      measurements near 100 km deduced from the Pioneer Venus lower
      atmosphere probes, the bus mass spectrometer measurements and
      orbiter drag indicate that the overall sensitivity is about a
      factor of 1.6 low [HEDINETAL1983].  Estimates of the gas flow
      into the ion source at satellite speeds indicate that the
      sensitivity may deviate from that assumed in the data
      reduction.  Laboratory tests of the prototype instrument in a
      molecular beam system produced results consistent with this
      hypothesis but not conclusive because of the limited range of
      speeds that could be obtained.
 
      The relationship between the superthermal ion flux and
      instrument output was established in a post-flight calibration
      of the flight backup unit.  In the energy range 40-200 V, the
      maximum transmission occurs 10 V above the ion repeller
      potential and drops to 15% of the maximum transmission value
      above 100 eV.  The transmission decreases with increasing mass
      number and for Ar+ ions (m/e=40) it is about a factor of 2.5
      below that for O+ at the maximum transmission point.
 
      The relationship between thermal ion density and instrument
      output was established by direct comparison of the O+ signal
      with the O+ density determined from the Orbiter Ion Mass
      Spectrometer (OIMS) instrument using O+ data from orbit number
      530 at 300 seconds from periapsis.  Other species are assumed
      to have the same sensitivity as that of O+.  In this mode
      superthermal ions cannot be distinguished from thermal ions.
 
      Stability of the electronics and sensor combination as a
      function of temperature was established in tests using a vacuum
      chamber with temperature control.
 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
