<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:pvo.oims</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>PVO ORBITER ION MASS SPECTROMETER for PVO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-08-26</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.pvo::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Brinton, H.C., L.R. Scott, M.W. Pharo, III, and J.T.C. Coulson, The
                   Bennett ion-mass spectrometer on Atmosphere Explorer-C and -E, Radio Sci.,
                   vol. 8, 323, 1973.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BRINTONETAL1973</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Taylor, H.A., Jr., H.C. Brinton, S.J. Bauer, R.E. Hartle, T.M. Donahue,
                   P.A. Cloutier, F.C. Michel, R.E. Daniell, Jr., B.H. Blackwell, Ionosphere
                   of Venus: First observations of the dayside ion composition near dawn and
                   dusk, Science, vol. 203, 752, 1979.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TAYLORETAL1979C</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Taylor, H.A., Jr., H.C. Brinton, S.J. Bauer, R.E. Hartle, P.A. Cloutier,
                   F.C. Michel, R.E. Daniell, Jr., T.M. Donahue, R.C. Maehl, Ionosphere of
                   Venus: First observations of the effects of dynamics on the dayside ion
                   composition, Science, vol. 203, 755, 1979.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TAYLORETAL1979D</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>PVO ORBITER ION MASS SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Mass Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
----------------------------------------------------------
Copyright (c) 1980 IEEE, Reprinted, with permission, from IEEE
Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, GE-18, Num 1, 36-38,
1980.
 
This material is posted here with permission of the IEEE. Such
permission of  the IEEE does not in any way imply IEEE endorsement of
any of PDS&apos;s products  or services. Internal or personal use of this
material is permitted.  However, permission to reprint/republish this
material for advertising or promotional purposes or for creating new
collective works for resale or resdistribution must be obtained from the
IEEE by sending a blank email message to info.pub.permission@ieee.org.
 
By choosing to view this document, you agree to all provisions of the
copyright laws protecting it.
----------------------------------------------------------
NOTE:  References to figures are included in the
article even though the figures aren&apos;t. This enables
you to look up the actual article in the IEEE
transaction and find the figures.
----------------------------------------------------------
 
Bennett Ion Mass Spectrometers on the Pioneer Venus
                Bus and Orbiter
 
H.A. Taylor, Jr., H.C. Brinton, T.C.G. Wagner, B.H.
Blackwell, and G.R. Cordier
 
IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing
                January 1980
---------------------------------------------------
 
Abstract
 
Identical Bennett radio frequency ion mass spectrometer instruments
on the Pioneer Venus Bus and Orbiter have provided the first in-situ
measurements of the detailed composition of the planet&apos;s ionosphere.
The sensitivity, resolution, and dynamic range are sufficient to
provide measurements of the solar-wind-induced bow-shock, the
ionopause, and highly structured distributions of up to 16 thermal
ion species within the ionosphere.  The use of adaptive scan and
detection circuits and servo-controlled logic for ion mass and energy
analysis permits detection of ion concentration as low as 5 ions/cm3
and ion flow velocities as large as 9 km/s for 0+.  A variety of
commandable modes provides ion sampling rates ranging from 0.1 to 1.6
s between measurements of a single constituent.  A lightweight sensor
and electronics housing are features of a compact instrument
package.
 
I. Introduction
 
Owing to the weak intrinsic magnetic field of the planet, direct
interaction between the solar wind and the Venusian ionosphere
creates a more complex and variable structure than encountered in the
Earth ionosphere.  As a result, theoretical predictions advanced
prior to the Pioneer Venus (PV) mission set the requirement for
instrument capabilities exceeding those previously demonstrated in
extensive flight experience with the Bennett spectrometer in the
Earth ionosphere on the Orbiting Geophysical Observatory and
Atmosphere Explorer missions.
 
The primary objective of the PV Ion Mass Spectrometer (IMS)
investigations has been to make global measurements of the
composition of the ionosphere and, to the extent possible, measure
ion drift with sufficient accuracy to contribute to the understanding
of the solar-wind-induced dynamics of the ionosphere.  Development of
three unique measurement functions, 1)  the step-dwell peak sampling
technique, 2) the charge/velocity servo system, and 3)  the
explore/adapt ion mass sequencing system have proven to be essential
for providing accurate ion concentration measurements compatible with
both the data rate available from the spacecraft, and the high degree
of variability encountered in the Venusian ionosphere.
 
II. Instrument Description
 
The Bus IMS (BIMS) and Orbiter IMS (OIMS) instruments are identical
both electrically and mechanically, with the physical characteristics
shown in Fig. 1.  the instrument design and operational
characteristics are similar to those of ion spectrometers flown on
numerous rocket and satellite missions, including those on the
Atmosphere Explorer-C and - E spacecraft [1].  The instrument
consists of an analyzer tube and an electronics package.  Ambient
atmospheric ions sampled by the spectrometer enter the instrument
through the analyzer orifice which is oriented as closely as possible
in the direction of spacecraft motion, to enhance the collection of
ions &apos;scooped up&apos; by the relatively rapid motion of the spacecraft
through the thermal plasma.  Both the BIMS and OIMS instruments were
mounted with the analyzer axis parallel to the spacecraft spin axis;
this ensures a relatively small angle of attack throughout the
periapsis pass and eliminates spin modulation of the ion currents.
 
A. Mechanical Configuration
 
The mass analyzer, shown schematically in Fig. 2, consists of a
lightweight aluminum tube enclosing a series of grids, spacers, and
long drift spaces.  The grids are 0.001-in diameter knitted tungsten
mesh with approximately 90-percent transparency.  The intergrid
spacers are machined from polyimide which has been baked to drive out
volatiles.  The drift spaces, which must be conducting, are made of
gold- plated aluminum.  Vacuum sealing of the tube, which is required
only for the prelaunch calibration, is achieved by means of an O-ring
in the collector area and by use of a low outgassing RTV sealant
where the grid tabs protrude through the aluminum shell.
 
The electronics housing is machined from magnesium.  Component
mounting in the printed-circuit boards utilizes both stitch-weld and
solder techniques.  All boards are conformally coated.
 
The total mass of the instrument is 3.0 kg.
 
B. Instrument Techniques
 
The system block diagram for the ion spectrometer is presented in
Fig. 3.  The instrument is powered by the +28 V spacecraft Bus and
requires approximately 1.5 W of power in all modes of operation.  The
electronics system performs five major functions: 1) supplies
required RF and dc potentials to the ion analyzer tube, 2) detects
and amplifies ion current flowing to the collectors, 3) digitizes,
processes, and formats data for telemetry, 4) automatically
configures the sensor for subsequent measurements during a prescribed
measurement cycle, and 5) decodes and implements instrument
commands.
 
1) Ion Analyzer:  Mass analysis of the spectrum of ambient thermal
positive ions entering the Bennett RF spectrometer sensor (Fig. 2) is
performed by 1) imparting incremental energy to those ions which are
&apos;resonant&apos; as they traverse the analyzer, and subsequently 2)
applying a retarding potential barrier which inhibits detection of
ions except those which have gained the maximum energy with the
analyzer.  The instrument is identified as an RF spectrometer since
the incremental ion energy is imparted by an RF potential (VRF)
applied to each of four RF stages within the sensor.  The sequencing
of mass analysis within the chosen range of ion masses is
accomplished by stepping the negative voltage (Va) which accelerates
the positive ions down the longitudinal axis of the analyzer, through
the four RF stages, and toward the retarding potential barrier
established by the positive potential (Vs).  For a particular value
of the accelerating voltage (Va), the &apos;resonant&apos; velocity is imparted
to ions of a given amu, such that these particles pass through each
RF stage in synchronism with the phase of VRF.  These ions receive
maximum energy as they traverse the sensor, and are thus able to
penetrate the retarding potential barrier and reach the collectors.
 
The barrier field established by the positive dc voltage Vs restricts
the passage of all but the resonant ions, and thus acts as both an
efficiency and resolution control for the analyzer.  The gridded
collector intercepts a small percentage of the total detectable ion
flux and presents this current as input to a low-gain preamplifier.
Ion flow to the solid collector surfaces serves as input to the high-
gain preamplifier.  Two additional grid structures within the tube
suppress secondary electron emission from the collector surfaces and
also induce (upon command) simulated ion currents into the detectors
for end-to-end calibration of the electronic system.
 
2) Charge/Velocity Servo:  The potentials Va and Vs work together to
regulate the ion detection process with respect to the effects of 1)
spacecraft velocity, 2) spacecraft skin charge, and 3) ion flow
velocity generated by electric fields and/or solar-wind viscous
interaction.  For a sensor at rest relative to the plasma, equation
(1) of Fig. 2 applies, and the value of VA required to produce
resonance for an ion of mass M is simply determined by the fixed
coefficients K, S, and F.  The potential Vs is set to provide nominal
analyzer efficiency and resolution.  Under flight conditions
(equation (2) and Fig. 2) the sum of the axial components of
spacecraft and ion drift velocities (v) results in a ram energy term
for each ion mass, varying as 1/2 mv2.  The servo system
automatically compensates for this energy shift by appropriate
adjustment of the Va and Vs voltages to maintain constant instrument
efficiency and mass resolution.  The effect of spacecraft skin charge
is to add an energy offset proportional to phi sc, independent of ion
mass.  This additional term in the mass analysis equation is also
automatically accommodated by the instrument servo.
 
The axial component of ion drift velocity and the value of spacecraft
potential are determined by analysis of the servo coefficients
included in the BIMS and OIMS data stream.
 
3) Adaptive Mass Scan:  A second unique feature incorporated in the
BIMS and OIMS instruments is the explore/adapt logic sequence for
regulating the consecutive measurements of individual ion species.
This accomplished in two steps: 1) periodic exploration of all 16
preselected ion species, and 2) adaptive sequencing of repetitive ion
measurements according to the relative significance of ion currents
detected during the exploratory cycle.
 
Because of the significant variations in the distribution of the ions
within the Venusian ionosphere, and the data rate limitations
afforded by the PV mission, the explore/adapt measurement sequence
was employed to insure the maximum possible repetition rate for
sampling of species found to be prominent in a given altitude and/or
local time range.  Prompted by theoretical considerations, a total of
16 probable ion species to be identified in the Venusian ionosphere
were selected and are identified in Table I.  The sequence of ions
listed in the table is sampled by stepping the accelerating potential
Va to the appropriate value for each amu.  The explore/adapt concept
is shown in Fig. 4.  The basic explore/adapt cycle is repeated every
6.3 s, and consists of an explore interval during which a sequential
search is made for each of the 16 species, followed by a series of
shorter adapt intervals during which repeated measurements of as many
as eight prominent ions detected during the explore interval are
performed.  If eight or more ions are detected during the explore
interval, adapt measurements of the eight most prominent of these
will be repeated to fill out the remainder of the 6.3 s cycle as
shown in the upper part of Fog. 4, thereby providing a total of six
measurements of the eight prominent ions and one measurement of up to
eight less prominent ions during the 6.3-s cycle.  If less than eight
ions are detected during the initial explore interval, the adapt
intervals will contain repeated measurements of the most prominent
ions detected up to the maximum number of eight.  Thus, as shown in
the lower part of Fig. 4, if only one ion is detected during the
explore interval, forty repeat measurements of the same ion are made
during the adapt interval, providing maximum temporal and spatial
resolution for that single specie.  The explore/adapt sequence
thereby provides a spatial resolution of measurements inversely
proportional to the number of ions encountered and thus automatically
adjusts the measurement sequence so that information returned is
optimized relative to the conditions encountered during the mission.
 
 
                        TABLE 1
---------------------------------------------------------
           BIMS/OIMS Dedicated Ions Masses
---------------------------------------------------------
Measurement Sequence    Ion Mass      Ion
    Position              (AMU)       Species
=========================================================
      0                     1         H+
      1                    18         H20, 18^0+
      2                    12         C+
      3                    32         02+
      4                     4         He+
      5                    28         N2+, CO+
      6                    16         O+
      7                    44         C02+
      8                     2         H2+
      9                    24         Mg+
     10                    14         N+
     11                    40         Ar+
     12                     8         O++
     13                    30         NO+
     14                    17         OH+
     15                    56         Fe+
=========================================================
 
 
Several commandable options extend the flexibility and reliability of
the explore/adapt system.  As appropriate to conditions encountered,
the instrument may be commanded to 1) explore only, and 2) adapt to
less than eight prominent ions.
 
4) Step-Dwell Ion Current Detection:  As an improvement over previous
designs, the BIMS/OIMS ion spectrum scan is accomplished by a
step-dwell sequence of ion detection, rather than the less efficient
continuous sweep used in earlier instruments.  The step-dwell
sequence consists of a series of dwell intervals of approximately
0.1-s duration during which ion currents at each of the 16 mass
positions are detected sequentially during the explore interval.
 
At the onset of each of the 16 dwell intervals, the accelerating
potential Va is stepped to the approximate value required for the
resonant measurement of the specific ion.  As the measurement dwell
cycle proceeds, the values of Vs and Va are servoed to compensate for
changes encountered in spacecraft charge and velocity, thereby
ensuring mass resonance and constancy of sensor efficiency and
resolution for the ion current measurement.
 
During the dwell cycle VRF is switched an and off at a 30-Hz rate so
that intervals of ion current measurements are alternated with
intervals of background (zero-level) collector current.  These
alternating cycles of signal and noise are integrated in a manner
which cancels the zero level current.  At the end of the dwell cycle,
the accumulated ion current value is sampled and held for A/D
conversion and subsequent transfer to telemetry storage registers.
 
In addition to providing for the servoing Vs, Va interval, the
step-dwell feature of the mass scanning circuitry provides benefits
for both the bandwidth requirements of the instrument and the system
noise figure.
 
In order to cover the 120-dB (106/1) dynamic range of output current
from the ion analyzer, along with the desired current sensitivity,
two preamplifiers are employed, each receiving its input from the
appropriate collector surface within the sensor.  Each preamplifier
employs a low noise N- Channel field-effect transistor at its input
and a high megohm feedback resistor to establish the gain.  The
current sensitivity provided by this system permits the measurement
of ion concentrations as low as 5 ions/cm3.
 
5) Instrument Modes and Commandable Functions:  The OIMS instrument
has provision for sixteen commandable states, any one of which is
selected by a serial 5-bit code, 4 bits containing the command
information and one bit for initiating command.  The instrument can
be commanded to adapt to either the 8, 4, or 2 most prominent of the
16 ion masses.  In each case, it will adapt to no more than the
number commanded, but will adapt to a lesser number if there are
fewer masses present than the commanded number.  In addition, an
EXPLORE ONLY mode overrides the adapt interval and causes the
instrument to continue scanning all 16 mass positions repeatedly;
(the BIMS adapt command is fixed at 8 of 16).  The sensitivity of the
instrument may be modified by a GUARD RING command, which applies a
dc potential of either 0 or -6 V to the circular guard ring
surrounding the sensor orifice.  This command may be used to increase
the collection efficiency for ambient positive ions, thus increasing
the sensitivity.
 
The operation of the charge/velocity servo system may be checked by
use of the SERVO NORMAL/OVERRIDE command.  In the OVERRIDE mode, the
servo is disabled, and the Vs and Va parameters are set at nominal
values predicted to be appropriate for periapsis.  In this mode, the
instrument is nonresponsive to changes in ion flow velocity and
spacecraft charge.
 
In addition to the foregoing, the BIMS/OIMS instruments have a POWER
ON/OFF command and an internal CALIBRATION command.  The CALIBRATION
command couples known currents into the two preamplifiers equivalent
to ion currents detectable within the dynamic range of the
instrument.  These simulated ion currents provide an end-to-end
calibration of the electronics.
 
III. Initial Flight Results
 
Both the BIMS and OIMS instruments have performed accurately and
reliably in flight.  With repeated orbits, the OIMS has answered
several basic questions which motivated the PV mission.  In
particular, the identity of the dominant ions O+ in the upper
ionosphere and O2+ in the lower ionosphere was established
immediately.
 
In addition to the determination of the dominant ion, the OIMS also
identified H+, H2+, He+, O++, C+, N+, 18O+, and/or H2O+, CO+, and/or
N2+, NO+, O2+, and CO2+ in the Venusian ionosphere.  Data analysis
currently in progress shows positive indications that the ion energy
servo system will contribute to understanding the complex dynamic
nature of the ionosphere, as well as the detailed composition.
 
In addition to the early results from OIMS and BIMS already reported
[2] - [4], several examples of in-flight results are included here to
illustrate the fulfillment of the instrument design goals.  First,
the sensitivity and temporal resolution of the ion measurements have
permitted detection of numerous plasma signatures, including the
bowshock region, complex ionopause structure, and pronounced
irregularity in the ionosphere, as shown in Fig. 5.  In Fig.  6, the
capability is shown for simultaneous detection of axial ion drift
velocities of the order of km/sec along with associated extreme
structural variations in the ion concentration.  Together these
measurement tools provide a mean for detailed exploration of both the
composition of the Venusian ionosphere and the complexities of its
dynamic interaction with the solar wind.
 
Acknowledgement
 
The performance of the countless engineering tasks contributing to
the successful operation of the Pioneer Venus Ion Spectrometers
deserves special acknowledgement.  Particular among the many
contributors are J.S. Burcham, B.D. Gagnon, and M.W. Pharo of GSFC,
D.E. Simons, R.C.  Maehl, J.T.C. Coulson, D.E. Tallon, L.T. Fry, R.
Madaris, P.  Lepanto, and W. Heflin of Norlin Communications, Inc.,
and A.A. Stern of CSTA, Inc.
 
References
 
H.C. Brinton, L.R. Scott, M.W. Pharo, III, and J.T.C.  Coulson, &apos;The
Bennett ion-mass spectrometer on Atmosphere Explorer-C and -E&apos;, Radio
Sci., vol. 8, p. 323, 1973.
 
H.A. Taylor, Jr., H.C. Brinton, S.J. Bauer, R.E. Hartle, T.M.
Donahue, P.A. Cloutier, F.C. Michel, R.E. Daniell, Jr., B.H.
Blackwell, &apos;Ionosphere of Venus:  First observations of the dayside
ion composition near dawn and dusk&apos;, Science, vol. 203, p. 752,
1979.
 
H.A. Taylor, Jr., H.C. Brinton, S.J. Bauer, R.E. Hartle, P.A.
Cloutier, F.C. Michel, R.E. Daniell, Jr., T.M. Donahue, R.C. Maehl,
&apos;Ionosphere of Venus:  First observations of the effects of dynamics
on the dayside ion composition&apos;, Science, vol. 203, p. 755, 1979.
 
H.A. Taylor, Jr., H.C. Brinton, S.J. Bauer, R.E. Hartle, P.A.
Cloutier, F.C. Michel, R.E. Daniell, Jr., T.M. Donahue, &apos;Ionosphere
of Venus:  First observations of day-night variations of the ion
composition&apos;, Science, vol. 205, p.  96, 1979.
 
- End of IEEE copyrighted article -
- Begin Appendix from JGR article by Grebowsky et al. -
 
  Copyright (c) 1993 American Geophysical Union. Reprinted, with
      permission, from Journal of Geophysical Research, Vol. 98
      No. E5, 1993.
 
This material is protected by copyright, and should not be republished,
redistributed, or posted on the Internet.
 
By choosing to view this document, you agree to all provisions of the
copyright laws protecting it.
 
***********************************************************************
 
Appendix: Response of OIMS to Superthermal lons
 
   The Pioneer Venus Orbiter Ion Mass Spectrometer (OIMS)
[Taylor et al., 1981] was designed to measure cold
ionospheric plasma at Venus. When ambient ions exist with
energies comparable to or exceeding those of cold ions in
the frame of reference of the spacecraft, which travels at
~10 km/s, the spectrometer can often detect their presence.
These &apos;&apos;superthermal&apos;&apos; ions are detected as ion currents at
instrument mass settings for cold ion species that are
clearly not present in the environment. The energies of the
superthermal ions collected could be due to thermal plasma
motions and/or high bulk flow speeds (perhaps just a segment
of the tail of the ion velocity distribution).
 
    The basic mode of operation of the instrument (a Bennett
RF ion mass spectrometer) is well understood, leading from
its original conception by Bennett [1950]. Figure A1 is a
schematic diagram of the sensor tube. The spacing of the
grids and the frequency of the RF voltage signal that is
applied simultaneously across each grid set establishes a
&apos;&apos;resonant velocity&apos;&apos; that an incoming ion must have to
traverse the tube, from entrance to collector, and to
acquire the maximum kinetic energy from the RF E field
accelerations. An ion in traversing one RF grid set is
accelerated to a velocity which sets its time of flight
through the E-field free drift space region to the next grid
set. Those ions with the resonant velocity in the drift
space reach the entrance to the next RF grid set at
precisely the right phase of the RF potential for further
acceleration.  Nonresonant ions arrive at the RF grids at
non optimal phases and do not receive the maximal
acceleration. In front of the current collector plate a
retarding potential VS is applied to allow only the
resonantly accelerated ions to pass to the collector.
 
    The RF frequency is the parameter which sets the precise
speed which an incoming ion must have at the entrance to the
first grid set to be in resonance with the subsequent RF
field accelerations. This frequency and hence the resonant
ion speed is held fixed in the OIMS. The acceleration
voltage drop, VA, applied at the entrance to the
spectrometer is varied to accelerate different incoming ion
mass species to the resonance velocity; this provides the
ion mass discrimination.  Ions which are accelerated by the
potential drop VA to speeds near multiples of the RF
resonant velocity will receive partial acceleration in the
RF sections. This &apos;&apos;harmonic&apos;&apos; ion acceleration in the
spectrometer can result in an anomalous collection current
signal which could not be distinguished from that collected
from the desired resonance mass. For typical ionospheric
ions which have thermal energies less than l eV and enter
the spectrometer at the PVO 10 km/s velocity, the OIMS
nominal voltages were designed to prevent the harmonic ions
from being collected. This was only effective, however, for
relatively cold (&lt;1 eV) ion species and not superthermal
ions.
 
    To minimize the telemetry data rate, the OIMS was
designed to sample 16 discrete amu&apos;s rather than to sweep
continuously through all masses. The accelerating VA
potential drop at the spectrometer entrance was stepped
through 16 discrete values for the nominal collection of
thermal ionospheric species that were likely to be present
at Venus. The retarding potential VS on the grid before the
collector plate was similarly stepped to maintain a set
current collection efficiency for each amu. Since the
instrument selects an ion species by using the VA to bring
it to the resonant speed of the tube and because the
transmission through the retarding potential grid depends on
incoming particle energy, the instrument&apos;s amu response
depends upon the net energy of the ions entering the
spectrometer. That is, the analyzer section does not know
whether the drift energy is from the VA acceleration or from
ambient plasma flow.  Spacecraft electrical potential and
ambient plasma drift energy have the same impact on the OIMS
resonance response as do VA and VS changes.
 
    To compensate for variations in the incoming ambient
plasma energies, the VA and VS potentials were servoed in
tandem [Taylor et al., 1980a] starting from their expected
cold plasma values for each amu channel. The servo logic was
to seek and lock the instrument potentials for each amu
sample at those values for a prefixed collection efficiency
(i.e., the percentage of incoming ion flux that reaches the
collector).  The response time of the servo was designed to
be rapid enough that it would fully adjust to anticipated
variations in plasma ram energies along the spacecraft
orbit. The rate of adjustment was engineered to vary
proportionally to the magnitude of the collected ion
current, so that in low plasma density regimes sudden
changes in incoming ion energy would require a longer time
for the instrument to adjust to its proper efficiency
operating point than in high density regions.  This time
scale was of the order of minutes for the lowest measurable
ion concentration regions.
 
    Within the main body of Venus&apos; ionosphere the servo
compensation led to reliable ambient ion concentration
measurements, but near the boundary of the ionosphere two
features of the instrument&apos;s operation led to anomalous and
yet useful responses to ambient plasma components that it
wasn&apos;t
 
                 (unable to reproduce figures.)
Fig. A1. Schematic diagram of the OIMS analyzer structure.
 
directly designed to study. First, in order to maximize the
sensitivity of the instrument in low density plasma regimes,
the instrument voltages were automatically set more than
10 V away from the fixed servo point in regions when no, or
just trace amounts of, detectable ions were present. This
ensured the highest collection efficiency possible when ion
concentrations increased to just measurable levels. As a
result, at the inbound ionopause crossing the spectrometer
was &apos;&apos;offtune.&apos;&apos; The servo voltages converged toward the
desired values as the ionospheric density increased; but as
the response time was of the order of minutes, they did not
settle at the designed operating point until the spacecraft
entered into the ionosphere. Once it attained its designed
operating point it remained&apos;&apos; tuned&apos;&apos; to these voltages
until the spacecraft left the ionosphere and encountered
only trace ion concentrations.  Second, the servo response
was not designed to compensate for coexistent ion species
with differing flow velocities. In a region with one species
of cold ambient ions and a minor ion population of
superthermal ions with the same atomic mass, the instrument
voltages lock onto the desired operating point for the cold
species most rapidly. As the instrument voltages step for
amu scans, the voltages for each mass species are
automatically preset prior to servoing at values consistent
with the energy of that amu flowing into the instrument with
spacecraft speed and these settings do not change in the
short time between the cyclic scanning of all masses. Ions
with energies exceeding the spacecraft speed may be detected
with misidentified masses since their incoming energies
effectively add to the electrical potential energies set in
the spectrometer with the internal voltages alone used to
identify the resonant mass.
 
    The response of the OIMS to offsets in the operating
voltages and/or the presence of superthermal O+ ions in the
midst of a cold thermal O+ component is demonstrated in
Figure A2. The top shows the computed response to
superthermal O+ ions when the spectrometer is completely
outside the ionosphere. Superthermal oxygen ions could
appear in the 24 and 40 amu windows even in the absence of
thermal ambient ions with these masses. They would also
contribute to the current collected at the 16 amu setting,
but for most energies the efficiency of collection would be
less than that for the collection of cold incoming O+ ions
to which the plotted efficiencies are normalized. The bottom
part of the figure shows a similar calculation for
superthermal protons which also are detectable by the
appearance of anomalous mass signatures. Superthermal O+
ions with ambient energies exceeding 30 and 46 eV can, if
their fluxes are large enough, produce current contributions
in the 24 and 40 amu windows respectively. The protons are
detectable in the same mass windows with higher energy
thresholds. The upper limit of the instrument&apos;s capability
to resolve any amu is 100 eV which includes the spacecraft
ram energy. The responses plotted in Figure A2 were computed
assuming the internal voltages were set for a measurement
outside of the ionosphere, where instrument voltages were
intentionally offset from their desired ionosphere operating
values by the order of 10-20 v depending on the mass
setting. Once the spacecraft enters into the ionosphere,
this voltage offset is eliminated, although somewhat slowly,
by the servo mechanism. The instrument thereafter remains
tuned to such optimal voltages until it exits the ionosphere
and encounters only trace concentrations. The difference in
response in the bulk of the ionosphere transit and outside
the ionosphere is depicted in figure A3, where the response
of the 14 amu signal to superthermal O+ is shown. This
calculation shows that even cold 16 amu ions collected at
the spacecraft speed could produce a signal in the 14 amu
window in the low density regime outside of the ionosphere.
Inside the ionosphere the threshold for the detection of
superthermals as 24 or 40 amu signals would be raised by ~20
eV, a slightly higher change than is the case for the 14 amu
signature.
 
                (Unable to reproduce figures.)
 
Fig. A2 Effects of superthermal O+ (top) and H+ (bottom)
ions on the OIMS response. The figures reflect the
efficiency of collection in the mass positions of 16, 24,
and 40 amu, as was numerically modeled by calculating O+
motions through the DC and RF grid voltage layout of the
instrument.  Effectively, normalized efficiencies which drop
below the 0.001 level are undetectable. The efficiencies are
normalized to the instrument efficiency of collection for
cold O+ ions flowing at PV&apos;s ionosphere speed, which is ~1%.
 
Fig. A3. Response of the 14 amu signal computed as a
function of O+ energy into the spectrometer. Inside the
ionosphere and on the outbound transit through the ionopause
16 amu ions require speeds exceeding the spacecraft speed
entrance velocity to appear as 14 amu signals. Outside the
ionosphere due to the intentional offset of the instrument
voltages, and in the inbound crossing of the ionopause where
the instrument slowly servos to optimum operating voltages,
even cold ionospheric O+ ions would cause such a spurious
signal.
 
References cited in appendix.
 
 Bennett, W.H., Radiofrequency mass spectrometer, J. Appl.
         Phys., 21, 143, 1950.
 
  Taylor, H.A., Jr., H.C. Brinton, T.C.G. Wagner, B.H.
         Blackwell and G.R. Cordier, Bennett ion mass
         spectrometers on the Pioneer Venus bus and orbiter, IEEE
         Trans. Geosci. Remote Sensing, GE-18. 44, 1980a.
 
  Taylor, H.A., Jr., R.E. Daniell, R.E. Hartle, H.C. Brinton
         S.J. Bauer, and F.L. Scarf, Dynamic variations observed
         in thermal and superthermal ion distributions in the
         dayside ionosphere of Venus, Adv. Space Res., 1, 247,
         1981.
 
         (Received September 28,1992;
         revised January 25, 1993;
         accepted February 2, 1993.)
- End of Grebowsky et al. appendix. -

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
