<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:pvo.orpa</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>ORBITER RETARDING POTENTIAL ANALYZER for PVO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-08-26</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.pvo::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Knudsen W.C. , Evaluation and demonstation of the use of retarding
                   potential analyzers for measuring several ionospheric quantities, J.
                   Geophys. Res., vol. 71, pp. 4669-4678, 1966.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KNUDSENETAL1966</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Knudsen, W.C., J. Bakke, K. Spenner, and V. Novak, Retarding Potential
                   Analyzer for the Pioneer Venus Orbiter, Space Sci. Inst., 4, 351, 1979.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KNUDSENETAL1979</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Knudsen, W.C., K. Spenner, J. Bakke, and V. Novak, Pioneer Venus Orbiter
                   Planar Retarding Potential Analyzer Plasma Experiment, IEEE Trans. on
                   Geosci. Remote Sens., 18, 1, 60, 1980.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.KNUDSENETAL1980</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>ORBITER RETARDING POTENTIAL ANALYZER</name>
        <type>Particle Detector</type> <!--RChen/EN was Plasma Analyzer. No obvious choice. TBD in JSH's xl file-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
The Pioneer Venus Orbiter Retarding Potential Analyzer (ORPA) is
a plane gridded, retarding potential device. It is designed to
measure both ion and electron quantities in the 0-50eV energy range
in the Venusian ionosphere and solar wind. The PVO spacecraft
had an eccentric orbit with approximately a 24 hour period. For the
initial phase of the mission, periapsis was maintained at about 200 km
and apoapsis was at about 66,00 km. The low periapsis allowed
sounding of the Venusian ionosphere while the apoapsis altitude
provided an opportunity for observing the solar wind interaction.
 
  The quantities measured by the ORPA were electron
temperature* (Te), total ion concentration (Ni), individual
ion temperature Ti(j) of the most abundant species, their
concentrations Ni(j),  thermal ion drift velocity
(approximately D), and energy distribution of suprathermal
electron and ion fluxes f(E) up to 50 eV.
 
* The following conventions are used to create ASCII versions of
  equations, subscripts, etc.:
 
Xe or Xi is the electron or ion value, respectively, of parameter X
X(j)     is the jth value of a sweep of parameter X
^        indicates exponentiation
 
-----------------------------------------------------------
                     Measured Plasma Quantities
-----------------------------------------------------------
                                     Closest
                                     Distance
                           Sample    Between
                          Distance   Samples    Range     Uncert.
 Symbol    Quantity       (km) (1)   (km) (2)    (3)       (4)
===========================================================
Ni = Ne    Total Ion       1x10^-3  20x10^-3   ~10-10^7      ~5%
           concentration                        (cm^-3)
 
Ni(j)      Concentration    1.6     120        ~10^2-10^7    ~5%
           of up to 4 (j)                       (cm^-3)
           abundant ions
 
Ti(j)      Temperature of   1.6     120        100-10,000K   ~5%
           the jth ion                       ~10^2&lt;N-i&lt;10^7
                                                (cm^-3)
 
Mi(j)      Mass of the      1.6     120         1 - 56       ~1
           jth ion                              (amu)       (amu)
 
D          Ion drift        1.6,    500         0.05 - 5     ~50
           velocity         240                 (km/s)      (m/s)
 
fe         Low-energy       0.5     120         1-50ev       ~25%
           electron                           ~10^6-10^12
           distribution                  (cm^-2s^-1sr^-1eV^-1)
           function
 
Te         Ionospheric      0.4     0.4,        300-25000K   ~10%
           electron                 120        ~10^2&lt;N-e&lt;10^7
           temperature                            (cm^-3)
 
Te         Solar Wind       0.4     120       25000-5x10^5K  ~25%
           electron                            N-e &gt;= 0.5
           temperature                          (cm^-3)
 
Ne         Solar Wind       0.3      120      ~0.5-10^2      ~30%
           Electron                             (cm^-3)
           Concentration
============================================================
(1) This is the distance traveled by the spacecraft at a velocity
    of 10 km/s during which the plasma is sampled.
(2) This distance is dictated by the assigned bit rate.
(3) These ranges depend in some instances on the values of other
    parameters such as ion composition.
(4) These uncertainties apply to the higher concentration ranges. As
    the concentration drops toward the lower range value, the
    accuracies degrade.
 
 
The assembled ORPA consists of the sensor head which is surrounded by a
large ground plane 30 cm in diameter and the necessary electronics. The
planar sensor consists of a sequence of grids. The physical quantities
can be derived for a plasma from the integral flux of ions or electrons,
gathered by collector C, as a function of energy.  Only particles whose
energy is greater than the retarding voltage applied on the retarding
grid G-2 can strike the collector. Use of appropriate voltage programs
allows analysis of the particle energy.  The other grids and the
collector are biased with voltages, which separate positive and negative
particles and minimize secondary electrons produced by particle impact
and photons.
 
The sensor is used to measure both electrons and ions by changing the
sensor voltages.  The voltage program can be subdivided into three basic
modes with different options selectable through ground command.
 
Electron mode
 
In the electron mode, the ion current to the collector is negligible
with the collector at 47 V,  A potential difference of 20 V between G-4
and C was found sufficient to suppress most of the secondary electrons
produced by ion or electron impact at the collector.  The three front
grids G-0, G-1 and G-2 are the energy analyzing grids.  They are stepped
together from +6.8 to -4.2 V in the coarse scan. The corresponding
collector current is measured by an electrometer and then digitized. The
straight line portion is the retarding region, and the logarithmic slope
determines the electron temperature by the relation:
 
       e      D V
Te = - -  ------------                                               (1)
       k   D log (- Ie)
 
where e is the electron charge; k, the Boltzmann constant; and Ie, the
electron current.  The left side with larger positive voltage is the
attractive region.  The voltage Vp at which these two portions of the
curve join is the potential of plasma relative to spacecraft.  Vp is
expected to vary from a few volts negative in interplanetary space to 1
or 2 V positive in the Venusian ionosphere.  For the simulation it was
set to zero. The lower portion of the curve bends away from the
straight-line portion because the velocity distribution is not a true
Maxwellian distribution.  An additional population of suprathermal
electrons exists with higher energies than the thermal distribution.
 
  The retarding region of the characteristic curve is auto- matically
recognized by taking the measured differences of a logarithmic
electrometer.  On-board logic selects the peak difference and 4 or 10
adjacent values, depending on the commanded option.  The retarding
voltage in the electron mode consists of a coarse scan over the entire
voltage range followed by one or three fine scans over the appropriate
subrange centered where the largest difference in the coarse mode has
occurred. The retarding voltage at which the largest value of -delta
log (-Ie) occurs in the coarse electron scan is quite close to the
plasma potential and is used as a reference potential for the
retarding voltage in the ion mode.
 
 
------------------------------------------------------------
                     Control Voltage
------------------------------------------------------------
                                                Suprathermal
                          Electron (a) Ion (a)   Electron(a)
Symbol  Element            Mode (V)    Mode (V)    Mode (V)
============================================================
 G0   Entrance Grid       6.8 - -4.2     0 or -4.6      0
 G1   Ion Suppressor Grid 6.8 - -4.2   -0.1 to 36(b)   47
 G2   Retarding Grid      6.8 - -4.2   -0.1 to 36(b) 0 - -50
 G3   Displacement           47           -4.6         47
      Current Shield
 G4   Electron Suppressor    27          -24.6         27
      Grid
C, GR Collector, Guard       47           -4.6         47
      Ring
============================================================
(a) Referenced to satellite ground except where otherwise
    indicated.
(b) Referenced to plasma potential.
 
------------------------------------------------------------
                 Retarding Potential Programs
------------------------------------------------------------
                        Number   Step Size  Voltage Range(a)
Mode Scan               of steps    (V)           (V)
============================================================
 E   Electron, coarse   64      -0.176         6.8 - -4.6
     Electron, fine     20      -0.044(c)       0.88(c)
 I   Ion                80      J x 0.011(d)  -0.1 to 36(b)
 S   Suprathermal       48      J x 0.044(d)    0 - -50
     Electron
============================================================
(a) Referenced to satellite ground except where otherwise
    indicated.
(b) Referenced to plasma potential.
(c) Subdivides 5 coarse steps.
(d) The step size is proportional to J.
 
 
 
ION MODE
 
The basic principles of ion measurements with an RPA are
described by W.C. Knudsen (1966).  The ion current given by
 
  I = A * Tr * e * v * cos(alpha) * SIGMA(j)                   (2)
 
where
 
           --                                    exp(- K(j)^2)
SIGMA(j) = &gt;     (Ni(j) [ 0.5 + 0.5 * erf(K(j)) + -------------------
           --                                    2 * sqrt(pi * Bi)
           j
 
 
  K(j)   =     B(j)  -  sqrt( e * s^2 / (k * Ti(j)) )
 
              v * cos(alpha)
  B(j)   =    -----------------
            sqrt(2 * k * Ti(j) / Mi(j))
 
 
  s     =     V - Vi
 
where e is the electron charge (1.6X10^-19 Coulomb),v is the
ion velocity relative to the satellite, alpha is the angle
of attack, Tr is the grid transparency, A is the grid area
and V is the retarding voltage.  The array index j denotes
the ion species and the subscript i denotes that the
quantities refer to ions.  The expression for dI/ds is
 
  dI        --    Ni(j)          s          -e
  --  =  -c &gt;  -------------- * --- * exp[-------- * (s - s(j))^2] (3)
  ds        -- sqrt(k * Ti(j))   si       k * Ti(j)
             j
 
where
 
                   Mi(j) * v^2 * cos^2(alpha)
   s(j)  =   sqrt[  --------------------------  ]
                           2 * e
 
and
 
             A * Tr * e^1.5 * v * cos(alpha)
   c    =    -----------------------------------
                       sqrt(pi)
 
 
The current derivative with respect to the square root of
the effective retarding potential s is the sum of individual
ion terms.  Each term contains a Gaussian factor centered
on the value s(j), which is determined by the ion mass.
The half width of the Gaussian, sqrt( kTi(j)/e), is
proportional to the square root of the ion temperature
and the peak value is proportional to Ni(j)/sqrt(Ti(j)).
  The 80 retarding potential step height increments in the
ORPA ion mode vary according to the relation
 
   delta V = V(j-1) - V(j) =  J * 0.011V    J = 1, 79,
 
and the beginning value Vi(j) is started at Vref.  Thus,
 
                  J * (J - 1)                0.011
   Vi - Vref   =  ---------- * 0.011 ~ J^2 * ------,   J &gt; 10 (4)
                     2                         2
 
The difference in collector current between adjacent
retarding potential steps becomes
 
 
 delta I(j)    = I * [ V(j-1) - I * V(j)]
 
                        0.011
              ~ - sqrt( -----) * c * SIGMA(j)                 (5)
                        J(j)
 
where
 
             --   Ni(j)          J         -0.011 * e
 SIGMA(j) =  &gt; ------------ *   --- * exp[ ---------- * (J-J(j))^2]
             -- sqrt(k * Ti(j)) J(j)       2k * Ti(j)
             j
 
and
 
                     Mi(j) * v^2 * cos^2(alpha)
   J(j)      =  sqrt( --------------------------- )
                             0.011 * e
 
 
Depending on the commanded mode of operations, either I(j) values or -
delta I(j) values are selected and stored in temporary storage registers
for subsequent readout to the spacecraft.  The -delta I(j) values are
seen to consist of well separated Gaussian peaks and, as expected from
Equation (5) the values of -delta Ii(j) are approximately proportional
to the concentrations Ni(j).  The computer simulation is described in
somewhat more detail hereafter.  In what we anticipate to be the most
common mode of operations, the ORPA program logic recognizes and selects
a maximum of two sets of -delta I values  corresponding to the ion
masses.  Each set consists of a peak value and the five adjacent values
on either side.
 
In an optimal peak mode of operation, the ORPA selects up to four sets
of -delta I values.  Each set consists of the peak value and two
alternate values of -delta I on either side.  If more that four (two)
peaks are sensed, the logic retains the largest peak and three (one)
additional peaks. Ion temperatures, masses, concentrations, v cos alpha,
and plasma potential are deduced from the sets of -delta I values by
fitting the theoretical values for -delta I(j) formed from Expression
(2) to the measured values.  The approximation, Equation (5), is not
used. In addition to the peak values of -delta I, the first current
value I(1) is stored in all modes and permits computation of the total
ion concentration given by
 
                            I(1)
   Ni    =      ---------------------------                      (6)
                 A * Tr * e * v * cos(alpha)
 
The technique of taking differences in log Ie or Ii in the electron and
ion mode, respectively, and selecting values only around the sensed
peaks reduces the number of telemetry words needed to define a scan
without losing much scan information. The finest possible spatial
resolution of plasma quantities is obtained with a limited bit rate.
For special investigations, 48 consecutive or alternate values of the
electron or ion characteristic curve (log Ie or Ii) may be measured and
transmitted with consequent reduction in spatial resolution.
 
PHOTOELECTRON MODE
 
The retarding potential varies quadratically through the range 0 to -50
V.  The photoelectron energy distribution function fe is derived from a
set of 25 or 49 values of Ie(j) depending on commands.
 
 
MEASUREMENT SEQUENCE
 
The basic measurement sequence of the ORPA is EIIIP where E, I and P
represent electron, ion, and photoelectron modes, respectively.  The
instrument remains in each mode for one complete spacecraft spin cycle
before executing the next mode.  The complete sequence takes five spin
cycles.  An individual retarding potential scan is completed as rapidly
as possible consistent with required measurement accuracy so that the
scan will closely represent a &apos;point&apos; measurement.  The scan together
with other activities, including zero adjustment, background current
adjustment, and background current measurement, typically requires only
0.3s.  Thus, approximately 40 scans can be completed in one spacecraft
spin cycle.  The telemetry rate assigned to the ORPA is sufficient for
only one of these scans to be telemetered to earth for each spin cycle.
In one command option, the ORPA selects that scan which has the largest
first current value.  This scan will have been recorded when the angle
of attack was smallest (Equation (2)) when the ORPA is in the I mode,
and close to optimum orientation in the E and P modes.  Alternatively,
in a second command option, the ORPA selects the first scan that occurs
after receipt of a ram pulse from the spacecraft.  The space- velocity
vector lies in or close to the plane defined by the spacecraft spin axis
and the centerline to the ORPA at the time of receipt of this pulse.
Three ion scans at three different directions are required to determine
the ion drift velocity. To provide the second and third directions, the
ion scans in the second and third ion spin cycles are selected 45 degree
in roll angle before and after the first scan. By command, the basic
measurement sequence described above may be altered by skipping over one
or more of the modes in the sequence.
 
SENSOR SUBASSEMBLY
 
The sensor has seven grids of large diameter (6 cm diameter) covering
nearly the whole sensor front (8 cm   diameter). The large entrance grid
and the small collector plate (1.9 cm diameter) surrounded by a guard
ring provide for a radially uniform particle flux around the sensor
axis. The collector samples either electrons or ions from the uniform
central region.  Disturbing field effects at the grid edges are thus
avoided.  The first two grids are connected together to reduce the
electric field produced outside the sensor by the stepping retarding
potential in the ion mode. Any change in spacecraft potential produced
by the ORPA is thus minimized. The retarding grid G-2 is also a double
grid which provides a reasonably uniform retarding voltage in the
photoelectron mode.  To satisfy the need for a more uniform potential in
the ion and electron modes additional grids are biased with the same
retarding voltage during these modes. The grids G-0, G-1, G-2 are coated
with Aquadag, a graphite emulsion, to achieve a uniform surface
potential. All other conduction sensor parts are gold plated.  The grid
material of G-0, G-1, G-2 consists  of electro-formed copper- beryllium
with about 30 lines/cm and 82 percent transparency. The distance between
individual grids is approximately 0.3 cm. Electrical connection to the
grids is provided by two redundant connectors.  This design provides for
easy grid exchange without soldering from the front side of the sensor.
To provide a plane plasma sheath, the ORPA is surrounded by  an Aquadag
coated aluminum ground plane 20 cm in diameter. It is thermally
insulated from the experiment to reduce the heat flux to both the
experiment and spacecraft but is electrically connected to spacecraft
ground. With the sensor axis at 25 degrees from the spacecraft spin
axis, the angle the sensor axis makes with the spacecraft velocity
vector will be zero or small during a portion of each roll period when
the spacecraft is within the ionosphere.  For ion measurements, it is
important that the angle of attack be small, otherwise the assumptions
used in deriving Equation (2) are progressively violated.  The angle of
attack must not change too much during one scan to avoid ambiguous
results.  With our 160-ms scan time, the angle of attack changes only
approximately 5 degrees. To estimate and correct for systematic errors
arising from nonuniform retarding potential in the plane of the
retarding grids, the average potential must be known. The difference in
potential between the applied potential and the mean potential has been
arrived at through capacity measurements.  For the ion mode, the mean
potential differs from that applied by less than one part in a thousand:
 
    delta Vr = (-2 - 0.8Vr) * 10^-3 * V                  (7)
 
  The highest accuracy is required in this mode.  For the
  photoelectron mode:
 
    delta Vr = (380 - 8 * Vr) * 10^-3 * V                (8)
 
  The deviation in the electron mode is still smaller than
that given for the ion mode because of the five grids. The
grids are coated with Aquadag to minimize work function
variation in the plane of the grids.  The one sigma
variation from the mean is approximately 5 mV.
Equations (7) and (8) do not include the work function
variation.
 
CURRENT AMPLIFIER
 
The collector current of either polarity is
amplified by a linear electrometer.  The electrometer has
a sensitivity of approximately 6 X 10-13 to 1.3 X 10-4 A
in eight overlapping ranges.
 
The absolute accuracy within 1 year of aging was about 1
percent.  A zero adjustment in the input of the electro-
meter after every scan provides for long-term stability.
The collector is disconnected from the electrometer during
this adjustment and the differential input is controlled
by the output signal.  Additionally, the gain of the
electrometer can be checked internally by a calibration
command.  Five different current values are produced by
high impedance resistors and a well-regulated
voltage supply.  The largest feedback resistor is a 309
megaohm  metal oxide resistor with 100 ppm temperature
variation.  This  means that a temperature correction in
the expected temperature range from 0 to 60 degree C is not
necessary even in the most sensitive range.  The amplifier
time constant is 0.4 ms in all ranges.  The linear output
voltage is rectified to get only positive signals
between 0 and 10 V for currents of positive and negative
polarity.  The sign of the current is provided by an
additional logic signal. The linear output voltage V-lin is
related to the input current by the formula
 
              V-lin * 8^(L - 3)
     I   =    --------------------- * sign                 (9)
                        R
 
where R is the feedback resistor (309 megaohm) and L
is one of the automatically  adjusted ranges between
0 and 7.
  In the ion mode, the linear output voltage Vhn is
digitized.  In the electron mode, a logarithmic
scale has to be used and therefore a logarithmic post-
amplifier converts the linear signal to a logarithm
voltage where 10 V and 1.25 V linear are related to 7.5 V
and 5 V, respectively, in a logarithmic scale.  The
electrometer and directly related circuits such as
calibration generator and background compensation are built
in a shielding box.  The electrometer potential depends on
the mode and therefore all circuits connected with the
electrometer and the shielding case are insulated from the
normal signal ground and biased with the collector voltage.
  A background compensation circuit is incorporated in the
sensor electronics to provide the full dynamic range and
accuracy of the instrument available in the most
sensitive range even when a constant background current
is superposed on the signal current.  The retarding
potential at its maximum retarding value before every
retarding scan, the background current produced by highly
energetic particles or by secondary electrons in the sensor
is compensated to a very low value.  The compensation
circuits add current of the opposite polarity to the input
of the electrometer until the output voltage is less than
0.5 V in the most sensitive range.  The compensation
current is held fixed for the duration of the following
scan.  Currents from approximately 10^-8 to 3 X 10^-12 A
can be compensated with a stability of about 3 X 10^-13 A,
which is in the overall electrometer noise.  The output
noise (standard deviation) of the complete system
corresponds  to a current below 10^-12 A or 0.02 %,
whichever is higher.
  Some attention was given to minimizing the microphonic
sensitivity of the sensor since the spacecraft
contains a despun antenna and several instruments
have stepping mechanisms.  To this end the G-4 grid was
given a very high tension to reduce the amplitude of
any possible oscillation.  Further, all connections to
the electrometer input were quite rigid and short and
the electronic board was fastened with some damping
material.  The microphonic noise was below 5 X 10^-12 A
for a sinusoidal 0.1-g acceleration at all frequencies.
 
CONTROL VOLTAGES
 
The voltages are supplied by low impedance amplifiers which are
controlled by a 12 bit digital-to-analog (D/A) converter.  The retarding
potential steps are generated by appropriate digital values transferred
to the D/A converter and appropriately amplified.  The time interval
between successive steps is 2 ms when no range change occurs.  Every
range change increases the step length by 2 ms. The noise ripple on the
retarding potentials in the pass- band of the electrometer has been
measured at 0.8 mV peak to peak (=4 sigma). In the electron mode, the
retarding potential uncertainty is 1 mV or 0.1 percent, whichever is
larger.  In the ion mode the uncertainty is 5 mV or 0.1 percent,
whichever is higher.
 
DATA PROCESSING
 
Depending on mode, the linear or logarithmic amplifier output is
digitized during the last 100 microseconds before the next retarding
potential is applied. A 12-bit analog-to-digital (A/D) converter is used
but only the 10 most significant bits are retained. The 10-bit mantissa
and a  3-bit range value formed for each measurement are shifted into a
memory during the photoelectron mode and also during the electron and
ion modes when the I-V option is exercised.  At the completion of the
roll period, the memory is normally enabled for read- out within the
next spin period.  In the &apos;peak select&apos; mode of operation, each current
value is subtracted from the preceding value, and the difference -delta
I, together with the range information, is shifted into a buffer
register. Second differences delta(delta I) are also formed and used to
recognize when a peak in -delta I has occurred.  The criteria used are:
 
 delta I(j-2) , delta I(j-1) , delta I(j) , delta I(j+1)  &lt; 0
 
 delta delta I(j-2) , delta delta I(j-1) , delta delta I(j)  &lt; 0
 
 delta delta I(j+1) &gt;= 0.
 
These criteria reject noise peaks but permit detection of a genuine
peak.  When the criteria are satisfied, either 4 alternate or 10
adjacent values around a peak together with the peak value and retarding
potential step information are transferred into memory for later
transfer to the spacecraft.
  In addition to the differences -delta I, the first measured current I-
1 of a scan is stored.  It is used by instrument logic to recognize
and return the scan with the smallest angle of attack measured during
a spin revolution.
 
COMMAND SYSTEM
 
The ORPA can be commanded from earth into several mode sequences.  The
normal sequence starts with an electron mode followed by three ion modes
and one photoelectron mode. The photoelectron mode can be removed to
increase the spatial resolution of the other measured quantities.
Alternately, a photoelectron-only mode can be commanded with
measurements spaced at 90 degrees in roll angle to investigate the
angular distribution.  An electron-only mode may also be commanded for
high resolution of thermal electron parameters.
 
In both the ion and electron modes, one may choose either the peak-
select option in which -delta I values are stored or the I-V option in
which I values are stored.  The spatial resolution is typically reduced
by one-third in the latter option.  With the peak-select option, it is
possible to choose 4 peaks with 5 -delta I values each or 2 peaks with
11 -delta I values, as previously explained.
 
In a special mode of operation, with the control voltages set to measure
ions and the retarding potential fixed at its lowest step, the ion
current is sampled at 2-ms intervals until the memory is filled.  The
saturation ion current thus measured with high time resolution.
Irregularities in total ion density are measured at distance intervals
of 20 m.  Beginning with the next roll period the total ion
concentration is sampled at approx- imately 4-km intervals until the
memory is filled.
 
The voltage of the entrance grid may be commanded to 0 or -4.6 V
relative to spacecraft ground when the ORPA is in the ion mode.  This
option will permit measurement of low-mass, low-energy ions should the
spacecraft become slightly positive relative to the plasma.
 
THE CALIBRARTION SEQUENCE
 
When the ORPA is commanded into calibration the experiment cycles
through two calibration sequences of EIIIP and then returns to the
normal measuring sequence.  In the first calibration sequence the
electrometer is disconnected from the collector.  In the electron mode a
sequence of internal calibration currents satisfying the peak criteria
are produced to permit an evaluation of electrometer sensi- tivity and
peak selection logic.  In the ion mode the internal noise is measured in
the most sensitive range. In the second sequence the retarding voltage
is sampled to verify amplifier gain and proper logic operation.
 
------------------------------------------------------------
             Instrument Parameter Summary
------------------------------------------------------------
Parameter                        Value
============================================================
Current Range &lt;A&gt;                     10^-4 - 10^-12
Current Accuracy &lt;percent&gt;            98 (10 bit A/D)
Sampling Interval &lt;s&gt;                 0.002
Retarding Voltage Uncert. &lt;percent&gt;   0.1
Bit Rate &lt;bps&gt;                        40 or less
Commands                              6
Power &lt;W&gt;                             2.4
Weight &lt;kg&gt;                           2.9
Volume &lt;cm^3&gt;                         4440
============================================================
 
References
 
Knudsen, W. C., Evaluation and Demonstration of the use
of Retarding Potential Analyzers for Measuring Several
Ionospheric Quantities, J. Geophys. Res., 71, 4669, 1966.
 
Knudsen, W. C., J. Bakke, K. Spenner, and V. Novak, Retarding
Potential Analyzer for the Pioneer Venus Orbiter, Space Sci. Inst.,
4, 351, 1979.
 
Knudsen, W. C.,  K. Spenner, J. Bakke, and V. Novak, Pioneer Venus
Orbiter Planar Retarding Potential Analyzer Plasma Experiment, IEEE
Trans. on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, 18, 1, 60-65, 1980.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
