<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:pvo.ouvs</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>PIONEER VENUS ORBITER ULTRAVIOLET SPECTROMETER for PVO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-08-26</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.pvo::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Stewart, A.I, &apos;Design and Operation of the Pioneer Venus Orbiter
                   Ultraviolet Spectrometer&apos;, IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote
                   Sensing, GE-18, 65-70, 1980.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.STEWART_1980</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>PIONEER VENUS ORBITER ULTRAVIOLET SPECTROMETER</name>
        <type>Spectrometer</type> <!--RChen/EN was Ultraviolet Spectrometer-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    INSTRUMENT OVERVIEW
    ===================
 
      The University of Colorado&apos;s Ultraviolet Spectrometer
      instrument carried on the Pioneer Venus Orbiter spacecraft is a
      125-mm f/5 Ebert-Fastie design with a 250-mm Cassegrainian
      telescope.  The detectors are two EMR miniature photomultiplier
      tubes with a combined sensitivity range of 1100 to 3300
      Angstroms.  The diffraction grating is controlled by an optical
      device using the moire fringes generated by two offset radially
      ruled gratings.  A grating motor moves the grating through 27
      degrees in 512 equal steps.  Each step size corresponds to 4.4
      Angstroms.  The motor may be operated in a scan-and-flyback mode
      or in a mode in which it steps to a commanded position and
      holds there.  Further description of the instrument is found
      below.  A detailed description of the instrument, its
      operations and its derived data products is given in
      STEWART_1980.
 
      The instrument was manufactured by the Laboratory for
      Atmospheric and Space Physics and the &apos;build date&apos; is taken to
      be 1976-01-01.  The spectrometer dimensions were 0.0213 by
      0.0390 by 0.0169 (height by length by width in metres) and the
      mass was 2.72 kg.
 
      Instrument ID		   : OUVS
      Instrument Host ID	   : PVO
      PI PDS USER ID		   : AIFSTEWART
      Instrument Name		   : Ultraviolet Spectrometer
      Instrument Type		   : Ultraviolet Spectrometer
      Build Date		   : 1976-01-01
      Instrument Mass		   : 2.72
      Instrument Length		   : 0.0213
      Instrument Width		   : 0.0390
      Instrument Height		   : 0.0169
      Instrument Manufacturer Name : Laboratory for Atmospheric and
      				     Space Physics
 
 
    PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR
    ======================
 
      The Principal Investigator for the Ultraviolet Spectrometer was
      A. Ian F. Stewart.
 
 
    SCIENTIFIC OBJECTIVES
    =====================
 
      The objective was to study Venus in the ultraviolet from all
      ranges between 66,000 km, far outside its tenuous corona of
      atomic hydrogen, and 140 km, inside the fringes of the
      atmosphere itself, and to do so continually at all local times
      throughout an entire solar cycle.  During the 14 year mission
      continuous images, spectral scans and limb profiles of Venus
      were made.  In addition, observations were made of several
      comets and stars.
 
 
    CALIBRATION
    ===========
 
      The OUVS instrument response was calibrated at LASP using
      tungsten, deuterium, and argon miniarc sources derived from NBS
      standards.  Also measured were the response of off-axis light,
      the nonlinearities in the detector systems, and the instrument
      polarization.  Periodic calibrations during flight were
      performed using a calibration lamp and by viewing selected
      stars.
 
 
    OPERATIONAL CONSIDERATIONS
    ==========================
 
      A data buffer was essential to reconcile the basic instrument
      data rates of between 2048 and 256 b/s (depending on the
      integration period) with the OUVS allocation in the spacecraft
      telemetry stream, which is typically 80 b/s (although it could
      be as high as 512 b/s).  This low duty cycle also requires
      careful timing of the acquisition of data (a data arc), so that
      the scientific content of the data can be maximized.  The
      acquisition of spectral data also poses a problem, since the
      spacecraft (and therefore the OUVS line of sight) rotates
      through 60 degrees during the 2 s required for a complete
      spectral scan; this motion causes gross changes in the viewing
      and illumination geometry during the acquisition of the
      spectrum and renders interpretation difficult.
 
      Data-arc timing is accomplished by accepting spatial reference
      pulses from the spacecraft and by providing a commandable
      time-delay device.  The spatial reference pulses are issued
      when the spacecraft X-axis passes through the planes containing
      the spin axis and the velocity vector (RAM pulse), the
      planet-spacecraft vector (NADIR pulse), and the 270 degree
      ecliptic longitude vector (RIP pulse).  The instrument limb
      sensor also generates pulses at the leading and trailing edges
      of the planet&apos;s illuminated disc.  The spacecraft issues 1024
      sector pulses per rotation, and the time delay is accomplished
      by counting a commanded number of these pulses after receipt of
      the selected spatial reference pulse, before beginning to load
      data words into the buffer.  The length of the data arc is
      determined by the integration period; at 4 ms the buffer fills
      in 1 s, or 30 degrees of spacecraft rotation; while at 32 ms it
      takes 8 s or 240 degrees.
 
      The size of the data buffer means that spectra are acquired in
      two halves, with an interval between the halves for the
      telemetry system to read out the buffer.  The problems caused
      by the variation in line-of-sight during the data acquisition
      are minimized by taking spectra only when the spacecraft is
      near periapsis, so that the disc subtends much more than 30
      degrees at the instrument, and by using the NADIR pulse to
      begin the data arc 15 degrees before the line-of-sight crosses
      the nadir plane (the arc then ends 15 degrees beyond this
      plane).  This procedure reduces the variations in lighting and
      viewing angles during the acquisition of the spectrum.
 
 
    DETECTORS
    =========
 
      OUVS is mounted on the orbiter via a mounting wedge, so that
      the line-of-sight is offset 59.95 degrees from the spin axis.
      The spin axis points nominally at the south ecliptic pole.
 
      The detectors are two EMR miniature photomultiplier tubes
      operating in the F and G channels with a combined sensitivity
      range of 1100 to 3300 Angstroms.  The 510G-09 tube has a
      cesium-iodide cathode, a lithium-fluoride window and is
      sensitive from 1100 to 1800 Angstroms.  The 510F-09 tube has a
      cesium-telluride cathode, a fused silica window and is
      sensitive from 1600 to 3300 Angstroms.  The sensitivities at
      several wavelengths are given in Table II in STEWART_1980.
      Each tube has its own pulse amplifier and discriminator unit
      and the dark-count level for both tubes is about 4/s.
 
 
    ELECTRONICS
    ===========
 
      The electronics consist of logic box, low and high voltage
      power supplies, and a pulse amplifier and discriminator unit
      for each photomultiplier tube.  The logic box contains the
      spacecraft interface units, the command decoding logic, the
      pulse counters, word compressors, and data buffer used to
      process the detector outputs, and the instrument status logic.
      Additional logic provides for such functions as voltage
      regulation, and temperature compensation of devices such as the
      grating motor control units.
 
      Pulses from the detectors enter a 15-bit counter with
      integration periods of 4,8,16 or 32 ms.  The data word thus
      formed is compressed by shifting it until the leading bit
      reaches position 15; a new 8-bit word is then formed consisting
      of the next 4 bits plus four bits indicating the number of
      shifts.  The stream of 8-bit words is stored in a 256-word
      buffer; once the buffer is full, no new words are generated
      until the spacecraft telemetry system has read out the entire
      buffer.
 
 
    OPTICS
    ======
 
      Light enters the instrument through a 250-mm f/5 Cassegrainian
      telescope, heavily baffled against scattered off-axis light and
      protected by a cylindrical sunshade.  The sunshade has one
      internal baffle and is lined with a honeycomb material.  The
      telescope focuses light from the source on the 6 mm by 0.6-mm
      entrance slit of the monochromator, giving a 1.4 degree X 0.14
      degree field of view.  The monochromator is an Ebert-Fastie
      design of 125-mm focal length, using a 1-in diffraction grating
      ruled at 3600 grooves/mm, giving a dispersion of 22
      Angstroms/mm in first order at the exit slit plane.  The
      grating is blazed at 1300 Angstroms.  Two exit slits of the
      same size as the entrance slit are used; the spectral
      resolution is thus 13 Angstroms.  All the reflecting surfaces
      in the optical train are coated with magnesium fluoride, and
      all scattering surfaces are painted black.
 
 
    OPERATIONAL MODES
    =================
 
      In orbit around Venus the spacecraft spin rate is 5 rev/min
      with the spin axis pointed nominally at the south ecliptic
      pole.  The orbit is highly eccentric (e=0.843); periapsis and
      apoapsis altitudes are approximately 150 km and 66,000 km, and
      the latitude of periapsis has moved from 18 degrees to -10
      degrees over the 14 years of the mission.
 
      The OUVS line-of-sight is offset 60 degrees from the spin axis
      and the planet is in view for two periods: the first, from P -
      125 min (i.e., 125 min before periapsis) to P - 35 min is used
      for global imaging, since the planet subtends less than 40
      degrees, while the second, from P - 15 min to P + 10 min, is
      used for high-resolution mapping, spectral work, and limb
      profile measurements, i.e., those observations that must be
      made at close range.  When the planet is not in view, the
      atomic hydrogen corona can be observed from P - 5 h to P + 1 h,
      and outside this period, stars and interplanetary hydrogen can
      be observed around the small circle at 30 degrees south
      ecliptic latitude.  For observations of comets the spacecraft
      spin axis is maneuvered so that the OUVS line-of-sight passes
      through the target during each spin.
 
      Two instrument modes were available.  The wavelength mode used
      the grating motor in its fixed-position mode, and the data
      channel, integration period, and data-arc timing were all
      commandable.  In spectral mode the grating position was changed
      by one step after acquiring the previous sample.  The data
      buffer was used to store and read out acquired samples.
      Data-arc timing and the data channel were selected by command.
      A full 512-grating position spectrum was acquired in two parts
      since the buffer holds 256 data words.
 
      The minimum sampling time was 0.004 seconds and the maximum was
      0.032 seconds.  Wavelength resolution was 13 Angstroms and the
      wavelength step size was 4.4 Angstroms.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
