<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
	xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.xsd http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument:rl.consert</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>Comet Nucleus Sounding Experiment by Radiowave Transmission for RL</title>
    <information_model_version>1.16.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2021-06-15</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Migrated from PDS3 catalog file.</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.rl</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <doi>10.1007/s11214-006-9034-9</doi>
      <reference_text>Kofman, W. et al., The Comet Nucleus Sounding            
        Experiment by Radiowave Transmission (CONSERT): A Short                  
        Description of the Instrument and of the Commissioning Stages,           
        Space Science Reviews, 128(1-4), 431-432, Feb 2007.</reference_text>
      <description>Reference to the instrument paper.</description>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>Comet Nucleus Sounding Experiment by Radiowave Transmission</name>
    <Type_List_Area>
      <ctli:Type_List>
        <ctli:type>Radar</ctli:type>
      </ctli:Type_List>
    </Type_List_Area>
    <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>
    <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>
    <description>                                 
                                                                      
        INSTRUMENT OVERVIEW                                                   
        ===================                                                   
                                                                              
        THE COMPLETE CONSERT EXPERIMENT IS COMPOSED OF:                       
                                                                              
        - ONE ORBITER PART (ELECTRONICS, ANTENNA, HARNESS)                    
        - ONE LANDER  PART (ELECTRONICS, ANTENNAS,HARNESS)                    
                                                                              
                                                                              
                                                                              
        SCIENTIFIC OBJECTIVES                                                 
        =====================                                                 
                                                                              
        Our experiment concerns the rough tomography of the comet nucleus     
        performed by the CONSERT instrument. It works as a time domain        
        transponder between one module landed on the comet surface           
        (Lander) and another flying around the comet (Orbiter).               
        The CONSERT signal consists in a 90 MHz sinusoidal waveform 
        which is phase modulated by a pseudorandom code or PSK (phase shift 
        keying) coding. Such frequency, 
        in the radio range, is expected to minimize the losses during the     
        propagation inside the comet material and the generated pulse code    
        maximizes the signal to noise ratio.                                  
        In these experimental conditions CONSERT will perform a   
        measurement of the mean dielectric properties and on the detection of 
        large size embedded structures or small irregularities within the     
        comet nucleus.                                                        
                                                                              
        CALIBRATION                                                           
        ===========                                                           
                                                                              
        Due to the design of the instrument, there is no special calibration operation
         mode. The science data are composed of the signal characterising the 
         propagation channel of the comet nucleus as a function of time:      
        - The propagation time is the main data to be inverted and its        
          accuracy is waranted by the Consert clock absolute accuracy and      
          stability.                                                          
        - The signal amplitude can also provide information about the         
          nucleus structure but there is no internal calibration channel      
          to increase the link budget accuracy.                               
                                                                              
        OPERATIONAL CONSIDERATIONS                                            
        ==========================                                            
                                                                              
        The Lander makes a coherent addition and a detection of the position (delay) 
        of the correlation principal peak. A clean coded signal is finally back 
        emitted to the Orbiter with the found delay. The orbiter accumulates the 
        received signal and sends it to the Earth (via the satellite interface).
                                                                              
        OPERATIONAL MODES                                                     
        =================                                                     
                                                                              
        Each scientific measurement sequence (called scanning sequence)       
        involves the Orbiter part and the Lander. The duration of this scan   
        sequence is related to the duration of the orbit of the Rosetta       
        spacecraft relatively to the Lander on the rotating comet nucleus.    
        This duration is typically of the order of 10 hours during one revolution 
        around the nucleus. The individual duration of each sounding is less than one
        second.                                                               
                                                                              
        This duration of scanning sequence  should                            
        correspond to the time when the Lander and the Orbiter are separated  
        by the comet. During the direct line of sight periods, where Philae and
        Rosetta are in visibility of each others, the synchronization occurs. This
        mandatory and preliminary phase is also called the CONSERT 'tuning'.
        This means that the duration of the data      
        recording does not correspond to the total time of one revolution, but
        only for the part where Philae and Rosetta are in occultation by the comet
        nucleus.    
        The number of samples which theoretically should be taken is given by the 
        following formula:              
        2 * pi * radius of comet / ( lambda / 2 ) 
        where lambda is wavelength.                                           
        During the scanning sequence for a hypothetical circular comet with a 750 m 
        radius, about 3000 individual measurements, called soundings should be      
        taken.                                                                
                                                                              
        The general structure of the Consert operational scenario does not    
        depend on the comet type that is explored during the Rosetta          
        mission, however  a certain amount of the parameters depends on the      
        shape and size of the comet nucleus and on the orbit of the           
        spacecraft and nucleus rotation.                                      
                                                                              
                                                                              
        MEASURED PARAMETERS                                                   
        ===================                                                   
                                                                              
        While acquiring the signal which propagates through the comet
        nucleus, the CONSERT intrument measures the following physical
        parameters:
           - Propagation time of one to three peaks (in case of 
             multi-path propagation).
           - Attenuation of these signal peaks along the propagation
             channel.               
        </description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
