<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
	xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.xsd http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument:rl.mupus</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>Multi Purpose Suite for Surface and Subsurface Science for RL</title>
    <information_model_version>1.16.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2021-06-15</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Migrated from PDS3 catalog file.</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.rl</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <doi>10.1007/s11214-006-9081-2</doi>
      <reference_text>Spohn, T., et al.,                                       
        Mupus - A Thermal and Mechanical Properties Probe for the Rosetta        
        Lander Philae, Space Sci. Rev., 128(1-4), 339-362, Feb. 2007.</reference_text>
      <description>Reference to the instrument paper.</description>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>Multi Purpose Suite for Surface and Subsurface Science</name>
    <Type_List_Area>
      <ctli:Type_List>
        <ctli:type>Accelerometer</ctli:type>
		    <ctli:type>Sub-Surface Tool</ctli:type>
        <ctli:type>Radiometer</ctli:type>
        <ctli:subtype>Infrared Radiometer</ctli:subtype>
      </ctli:Type_List>
    </Type_List_Area>
    <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>
    <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>
    <description>                                 
                                                        
        Instrument Overview                                   
        ===================                                    
        Multi Purpose Suite for Surface and Subsurface Science (MUPUS)
        is part of the Philae instrument payload.  It consists of a 
        Penetrator (PEN) which is equipped with 16 thermal sensors, the
        infrared radiometer (TM), and thermal (ANC-T) and accelerometer
        sensors /ANC-M) located in the Philae harpoons.         
                                                          
                                                                
        Scientific Objectives                             
        =====================                              
        The scientific goals of MUPUS are:
          - to determine the energy balance of the comets surface and 
            its variation with time and depth
          - to determine the thermal conductivity of the comet down to
            a depth of 32 cm
          - to determine the thermal inertia of the surface
          - to determine the strength of the cometary surface layers
        
                                                          
                                                          
        Calibration                                     
        ===========                                 
        Due to problems with the ground calibration the PEN sensors 
        were re-calibrated in flight by comparison with a h/k Pt-100
        located on the holder the penetrator tube. The TM radiometer 
        was calibrated in the Space simulator at DLR Berlin using an 
        LN2 cooled low temperature blackbody. The calibrated 
        temperature range was 120-270 K. TM is further equipped with an
        inflight calibration device (a cylindrical blackbody which 
        covers a small part of the FOV which can be heated up to 
        400 K). Inflight calibration runs performed during cruise have
        revealed a significant degradation compared to the ground 
        calibration (suffered already on Earth !). Therefore, the final
        calibration of TM was done using the deep space view during the
        descent of Philae to the comet.
   
                                                        
                                                           
        Operational Considerations   
        ==========================                       
        The sensor heads PENEL and TM are both equipped with a 
        front-end-electronics which require a certain minimum switch-on
        temperature (-50 deg for PEN and -90 deg for TM). Therefore, a
        warm-up heating phase controlled by the MUPUS DPU is required
        before these sensor heads can be switched on.
        
                                               
        Detectors                                  
        =========                                 
        MUPUS comprises of three sensors: a cylindrical Penetrator tube
        with a length of ~ 35 cm and a diameter of 1 cm which is 
        equipped with 16 RTD-type thermal sensors made by sputtering 
        Titan on a Kapton foil. The sensors can also serve as heaters
        for acctive thermal conductivity measurements; an infrared 
        radiometer equipped with 4 thermopile detectors and the 
        necessary reference temperature sensors realized by miniature
        Pt-1000; the Philae harpoons which are each equipped with a 
        Pt-100 temperature sensor and an accelerometer working at a 
        sampling frequence of 48 kHz.
        More details are found in Spohn et.al, 2007         
                                                       
                                                          
        Electronics                                         
        ===========                                             
        Details on the electronics of the instrument are described in 
        Spohn, et.al, 2007.                               
                                                                
                                                               
        ========                                                   
        MUPUS PEN is mounted on the Lander balcony attached to its 
        deployment device (DD) during cruise. After landing on the 
        comet the DD will be used to deploy PEN up to a maximum 
        distance of 1 m from the balcony. TM is mounted on the V-strut
        on the balcony close to the CIVA-St camera and below the Tx/Rx 
        antennas. The harpoons are located below the Lander baseplate 
        and may penetrate up to 2 m depth after the shot. The MUPUS 
        central electronics is located inside the warm compartment of
        Philae.        
  
                                                       
        Operational Modes                                  
        =================                                    
        MUPUS can be operated in several different different modes. The
        main mode is TEM which performs temperature measurements using 
        all MUPUS thermal sensors (PEN, TM, ANC-T) in regular time 
        intervals. A similar mode but without measuring the PEN sensors
        is MAPPER which should  be used if the PEN is not deployed. The
        third thermal mode of the instrument is THC which performs an 
        active thermal conductivity measurement using a (configurable)
        number of PEN sensors for heating. Further operational modes 
        are ARM (deploying the PEN), HAMMER (inserting PEN into the 
        ground), and ANCHOR (fast sampling of the accelerometers in the
        harpoons after the shot).   
                                                               
        Subsystems                                             
        ==========                                             
        The sub-systems are described in Spohn et al, 2007.    
                                                               
                                                               
        Measured Parameters                                    
        ===================                                     
        Measured parameters are temperatures for PEN and ANC-T,
        brightness temperatures which are equivalent to infrared net
        fluxes for TM, and acceleration for ANC-M.    
      </description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
