<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
	xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.xsd http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument:rl.sesame</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>Surface Electric Sounding and Acoustic Monitoring Experiment for RL</title>
    <information_model_version>1.16.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2021-06-15</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Migrated from PDS3 catalog file.</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.rl</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <doi>10.1007/s11214-006-9118-6</doi>
      <reference_text>K. J. Seidensticker et al., Sesame - An                  
        Experiment of the Rosetta Lander Philae: Objectives and General          
        Design, Space Sci. Rev., 128(1-4), 301-337, Feb. 2007.</reference_text>
      <description>Reference to the instrument paper.</description>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>Surface Electric Sounding and Acoustic Monitoring Experiment</name>
    <Type_List_Area>
      <ctli:Type_List>
        <ctli:type>Seismometer</ctli:type>
        <ctli:type>Dust Analyzer</ctli:type>
        <ctli:type>Electric Field Instrument</ctli:type>
      </ctli:Type_List>
    </Type_List_Area>
    <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>
    <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>
    <description>                                               
                                                                      
    
        CASSE
        ======
      
           Instrument Overview                                            
           ===================                                            
           The Comet Acoustic Surface Sounding Experiment (CASSE) should 
           study the cometary surface layer by applying active and passive
           methods. 
           To this end, CASSE uses accelerometers (ACC) and custom-made Piezo
           stacks (called transmitter = TRM) mounted in the soles of Philae's
           feet that can record and generate vibrations in the audible
           frequency range. The temperature of each sensor is monitored by a 
           thermistor (PT 1000) for calibration purposes.
     
           By command, any combination of receivers and transmitters can be
           selected. The sounding frequency can be varied from 10 Hz to
           10000 Hz for a duration up to 2000 s. The sampling frequency can
           be varied from 80 Hz to 100000 Hz for a recording duration also
           up to 2000 s.
           The nominal gain can be varied in 16 irregular steps from 1 to
           168 by combining four amplifier stages. Thus, CASSE can either
           excite elastic waves that are transmitted through the cometary 
           matter beneath Philae and recorded by CASSE sensors or detect such
           waves generated by other artificial or natural sources. The use of
           triaxial accelerometers allows a polarization analysis and thus the
           distinction of different wave types.
     
           The CASSE electronics is controlled by the common SESAME 
           flight software.
     
     
           Scientific Objective                                   
           ====================                                           
           The scientific objective of CASSE is to study lateral and vertical
           elastic and structural properties of the cometary surface layer 
           over the foot-to-foot distance of about two meter. The quality of 
           these investigations depends on the elastic properties of the 
           surface material and its mechanical contact to the lander soles.
     
           The primary goal of the CASSE investigation is to determine elastic
           parameters like Young s modulus and the Poisson ratio as well as
           their daily and seasonal variations by analyzing the registered
           signal profiles of (repeated) active soundings or by recording
           artificial signals like the Philae touchdown and the MUPUS-Pen
           hammering.
     
           Additional goals are:
            - The monitoring of thermally or impact-caused cometary
              activity and the localization of activity spots;
            - The determination of the macro-structure of the cometary
              surface, such as the expected layering or embedded
              inhomogeneities, by using refraction and / or reflection
              seismograms;
            - The study of emitted particles impacting on the soles during the
              orbit phase as well as during the descent to the cometary 
              surface. 
                                                                          
           Electronics                                                    
           ===========
           The CASSE sensors are controlled by an electronics board (PCB) as
           part of the SESAME central electronics. The general design of the
           CASSE PCB is that of a triggerable 12-channel transient recorder
           (9 accelerometer and 3 transmitter channels) with a sampling rate
           of up to 100 kHz that will be distributed evenly on the channels
           selected. The electronics also includes a signal generator with a
           variable output frequency for the three transmitters. The received
           signals coming from the input multiplexer are amplified with a 
           selectable gain ranging from 1 to 168 (0 to 44.5 dB), converted by
           an 7-bit custom-made analog-to-digital converter (ADC) plus sign
           bit and recorded in a 128 kByte ring buffer. The transfer function
           of the ADC is quasi-logarithmic, using piecewise linear approximation.
           A recorded signal is read from the CASSE memory by the SESAME flight
           software and further processed or handed over to the Philae Command
           and Data Management System (CDMS) for downlink.
     
     
           Location                                                       
           ========                                                       
           The three CASSE triaxial accelerometers (Bruel and Kjaer, type 4506
           W002) are mounted in the left sole of each Philae s feet (looking
           from Philae s center) above the electrode mesh of the SESAME
           Permittivity Probe (PP) instrument. The other sole of each foot 
           contains a custom-made Piezo stack (producer FHG-IfZP) that can 
           generate and record vibrations.
     
           The ACC are connected by 4-wire cables separated from the
           transmitters (using 9-wire cables) to the CASSE electronics in
           order to reduce cross talk between transmitting and receiving
           lines. But this principle is broken in three common connectors
           between the CASSE electronics and the sensors.
     
           The thermistors (PT 1000) are mounted directly on each sensor
           using the a 2-wire connection with a common ground in the 9-wire
           cables of the transmitters. 
     
                                                                              
           Subsystems                                                     
           ==========                                                     
           None
     
     
           Operational Considerations                                     
           ==========================                                     
           SESAME-CASSE is sensitive to external vibrations. During the cruise
           phase CASSE recorded e.g. the vibrations caused by the dither
           actuators of the orbiter gyros as well as those generated by the
           Philae flywheel. Any mechanical activity that is not needed for
           the proper CASSE measurement was avoided during CASSE operations.
     
           In addition, CASSE also detected CONSERT soundings as fake
           acceleration signals. Thus parallel operation of CASSE and CONSERT
           were reduced to a minimum and avoided during the touchdown
           measurements at Agilkia.
     
                                                                          
           Operational Modes                                              
           =================                                              
           CASSE can be operated in 5 modes:
           1) Health Check: This mode executes a programmed sequence with no 
              tele-command parameters.
              A ping (a vibration with 1000 Hz and a duration of 5 ms) is
              sequentially generated by the transmitters of each foot and 
              simultaneously recorded by the accelerometer on the same foot
              (x, y, z axes; total listening duration per foot: 40 ms, sampling
              rate per channel: 16 kHz). The amplifier gain is set to 53.79. 
              The measurements are repeated once. As this mode uses the closest
              possible distance between sounder and receiver for CASSE, the
              health of transmitter, accelerometer and CASSE electronics
              can be checked by this operation. The quality of the Health Check
              measurements is checked by the repetition.
     
           2) Listening Mode: The simplest operating mode of CASSE is the
              Listening mode. Any combination and number of accelerometer
              channels and transmitters can be operated as receivers. Various
              parameters like sampling frequency and duration and gain can be
              set by executing a CASSE jobcard (a tele-command used for 
              setting the CASSE instrument parameters) before executing the
              Listening mode. The common operation of accelerometers and
              transmitters as receivers should be avoided, as in this case
              large DC offsets are generated by the CASSE electronics.
     
           3) Trigger Mode: The Trigger mode is a special case of the
              Listening mode as one or more receiver channels are designated
              as trigger channels. All incoming data in the receiver channels
              are stored in the CASSE RAM in FIFO mode until the signal
              exceeds predefined positive or negative trigger levels or the
              Trigger time-out duration is reached. The trigger levels and 
              gain can be set either by command or automatically by executing
              at least two Listenings before the Trigger operation. When a 
              trigger event is detected, additional data are stored in the
              CASSE RAM until the end of the recording duration.
              These data, including a time period before the trigger event
              (called 'trigger delay'), are then transferred to the SESAME
              Common Data Processing Unit.
     
           4) Sounding Mode: In the Sounding mode at least one transmitter
              is excited and the signal via the Philae landing gear and / or
              the cometary surface can be registered by any combination
              of CASSE receivers. By using a CASSE jobcard, the sounding
              frequency and duration can be set. It should be noted that
              the CASSE electronics only allows a limited number of
              combinations of sounding and receiving frequencies within
              the operating ranges of transmitters and accelerometers. 
     
           5) Stacking Mode: The Stacking mode is a special case of the
              Sounding mode, as the soundings can be repeated and up to
              127 linearized time series can be stacked in order to improve
              the signal-to-noise ratio.
     
           In any operation mode of the SESAME flight software version FM-3
           statistics data (minimum, maximum and mean of each recorded time
           series (in ADC units)) can be stored and transferred to ground. 
           This option is quite useful for the Stacking mode, as only the
           statistics data can tell, whether any problematic time series
           (flat lines, background noise variation) were stacked on board. 
           At least flat line time series, which are sometimes produced by
           the CASSE electronics and result in all three statistics parameters
           having the same value, can be removed on ground.
      
                                                                          
           Calibration                                                    
           ===========
           The nominal CASSE calibration comprises the following steps:
     
           a1) All modes but Stacking mode:
               Linearize the sample ADC value by inverting the 
               quasi-logarithmic ADC curve and convert the result to 
               voltage before ADC.
           a2) Only Stacking mode:
               Divide the sample, which is actually the sum of linearized
               samples from several measurements, by the number of
               measurements and perform voltage conversion. In this step
               any flat line time series (see above) can be removed by
               subtracting the flat line value(s) from the sum and reducing
               the number of measurements accordingly.
           b)  Convert the voltage before ADC to the output voltage of the 
               sensors by dividing the ADC voltage by the nominal amplifier
               gain.
           c)  Divide the output voltage by the sensor sensitivity to get the
               acceleration in [m s^-2].
               The accelerometers are individually calibrated by the producer
               Bruel and Kjaer and have a typical sensitivity 
               10 mV/(m s**-2) +-5 percent in the range from 10 Hz to 
               about 5 kHz (depending on axis). No sensitivity data are
               available for the transmitters, whose signals are pre-amplified
               before entering the CASSE amplifier. A few measurements during
               the Rosetta cruise phase indicate that an external signal in
               ADC units recorded by a transmitter is about twice as large as
               that recorded by an accelerometer.
                                                                          
                                                                          
           Measured Parameters                                            
           ===================
           All CASSE operation modes record time series of acceleration values.
           Most of these data are transferred to ground as un-calibrated
           quasi-logarithmic ADC values. Only the Stacking mode delivers
           linearized summed up time series. Additionally, several time stamps
           (e.g. start and end of recording) are transmitted, in order to
           determine the correct absolute time series start on ground. At least
           at the beginning of each measurement, the temperatures of all CASSE
           sensors (also those not used in this operation) are collected.
     
        DIM
        ====
           Instrument Overview                                            
           ===================                                            
           DIM applies the principle of piezoelectricity to detect and analyze     
           impacting cometary dust particles. An impact evokes a decaying
           electric signal (burst), which is a mixture of several frequencies,
           at the output of the sensor. At the beginning of this transient
           signal a nearly perfect half-sine wave can be observed, which lasts
           for the impact duration. 
           The peak voltage is observed when the impact deformation reaches
           its maximum (elastic impacts are supposed). During the second
           quarter of the sine wave, the deformation caused by the particle
           decreases until the grain leaves the sensor.
           The piezoelectric sensors of DIM are mounted on a cube with about
           7 cm side length. Three sides of the cube are covered with sensors,
           the other three sides are either closed by aluminum plates or left
           open for harness access. Each of the active DIM sides is divided
           into three equally sized segments that carry rectangular
           piezoelectric sensors made of PNZT7700 (Pb, Ni, Zi, Ti). 
           The size of each segment is 50x16x1 mm**3. Adding all nine active
           segments leads to about 70 cm**2 total sensor area.
           The DIM electronics is controlled by the common SESAME flight
           software.
     
           Scientific Objectives                                   
           =====================                                           
           When the ice on a cometary surface is heated by solar radiation,
           the gas molecules released by the ice sublimation drag grains
           composed of refractory (dust) and volatile (ices) matter from the
           cometary surface. Due to the combined action of gas drag and
           gravitational forces, grains are either ejected into space becoming
           part of the interplanetary dust or are drawn back by gravity onto
           the cometary surface. The goal of the DIM instrument is to improve
           our knowledge about these particulate constituents of comets. 
           DIM obtains quantitative data on:
             - Directional statistics of impacting particles;
             - Velocity and mass distribution of back-fallen particles and for 
               particles on escape trajectories from the nucleus.
           These data are to collected over an extended time period in order to
           find possible correlations with the cometary diurnal and orbital
           phases. The analysis of these data should help to:
             - Improve our models of the distribution and the flux of
               near-surface dust and small particles as a function of their
               size and velocity;
             - Understand cometary activity with its underlying processes;
             - Explain the formation of cometary mantles
                                                                          
           Calibration                                                    
           ===========                                                    
           Each particle impact onto one of the piezoelectric sensor plates
           generates an electric pulse that is registered with the instrument
           electronics. The measured signals are analysed by Hertz' theory of
           contact mechanics. The output signal can be approximated by a damped
           sine wave. The amplitude and the width of the first half-sine pulse
           are registered by the instrument electronics and used to derive
           particle properties like the reduced modulus and the mass. To
           calibrate the instrument signals, a large number of drop 
           experiments with particles made of different materials 
           were performed.
     
           Operational Considerations                                     
           ==========================                                     
           SESAME-DIM turned out to be very sensitive to electrical
           disturbances by the MPPTs of the solar energy generators on board
           Philae. Therefore, several of the measurements obtained during
           Philae s descent to the surface of comet 67P (Agilkia) were
           disturbed by a large number of false signals. Only very few single
           false signals were recorded at the final landing site Abydos where
           DIM was operated at night when the solar arrays were not
           illuminated. False signals are characterised by the instrument 
           software as true dust impacts but for which we know by other
           means that they cannot be due to dust impacts. The instrument
           software is not able to distinguish false signals and dust impacts.
                                                                          
           Electronics                                                    
           ===========                                                    
     
           The DIM instrument is controlled by an electronics board as part
           of the SESAME electronics and receives its +5V digital and +/-5V
           analog power from the SESAME power supply board. The analog and
           the digital ground are separated. The signals coming from a given
           PZT sensor face are amplified by a logarithmic amplifier (U_out)
           which is then sent to a peak detector (U_Peak). The DIM electronics
           can detect an event if the amplified signal voltage U_out exceeds
           an adaptive threshold value U_thr. The detection threshold U_thr is
           the sum of an adjustable margin and a signal average. 
           The margin can be increased in steps of 10 dB in the range from 10
           to 70 dB. Each step changes the threshold voltage by approximately
           0.3 V. 
           The signal average is determined by the DIM electronics with a time 
           constant of approximately 1 s. It varies slowly with impact
           properties and frequency, aiming at covering a wide range of event
           voltage levels. 
           According to Hertz' theory the initial part of the dust impact
           signal can be approximated by the first half of a sine wave. An 
           impact should thus show up as a voltage, crossing the threshold
           voltage upwards, followed by a second threshold crossing downwards.
           The period between the two threshold crossings defines the impact
           duration Tc. If the amplified sensor signal crosses the detection
           threshold too early (less than 1 ms after the single event
           measurement was initialized), the event is classified as a 
           false event, else it is accepted as the beginning of a potential
           real impact. In BCT2 mode (see Section Operational Modes), the
           measurement is stopped after 1.6 ms. The event is ruled out as a
           long event, if no second threshold crossing was detected within
           500 microseconds (in case of the BC mode, this limit is 79 
           microseconds) during the measurement duration. 
           A true dust impact is thus characterised by its occurrence later
           than 1 ms after the initialization of the measurement and a duration
           of less than 500 microseconds for the BCT2 and 79 microseconds for
           the BC mode, respectively. Regardless of the event type (dust impact,
           false signal, false or long event), an adjustable dead time, the 
           so-called sensor signal decay time is included after the end of each
           single event measurement. 
           Apart from the signal decay time, several waiting and latency
           periods are added to the total duration of a single impact
           measurement. All latency periods add up to a total instrument dead
           time of approximately 10 ms.
     
           Location                                                       
           ========                                                       
           The DIM cube is mounted on the top side of Philae, and the three
           active sensor sides point in the +X, +Y and +Z directions in the
           Philae coordinate system. 
     
           Operational Modes                                              
           =================                                              
           Before any DIM measurement is started, a few operations have to be
           performed to guarantee that DIM is properly working. 
           After DIM is switched on: 
              (A) A power check is performed to verify that the supply
                  voltages are within predefined limits. Then 
              (B) Electronic noise is measured on the DIM amplifier (with
                  the DIM sensor being disconnected): Starting from a very
                  low value, the detection threshold (so-called margin) is
                  increased in steps of 10 dB until no false 
                  event is detected anymore. The rates of false events
                  typically encountered in flight were such that the margin
                  was set to 30 dB or 40 dB. This means that a true dust
                  impact must have an amplitude of at least 0.1 mV or 
                  0.25 mV, respectively, to overcome the threshold of the
                  amplifier. In a next step 
              (C) A DIM sensor test checks if all three sensor sides are
                  operational. An electrical pulse (approximately 5 V for
                  10 microseconds) is applied to each sensor side, and the
                  response is registered in the same way a dust impact would
                  be measured. Finally 
              (D) The electronics performs a DIM calibration to re-calibrate
                  the transfer characteristic of the logarithmic amplifier
                  and to check the time measuring circuit: Two test pulses
                  are applied to the logarithmic amplifier. Pulse height and
                  duration are 1 mV, 8 microseconds for low-level and 100 mV,
                  20 microseconds for high-level, respectively. The results
                  of the calibration procedure were supposed to be used to
                  re-calibrate the amplifier transfer function in the data
                  evaluation on Earth. However, it turned out after launch
                  that the high-level value is in saturation so that this 
                  re-calibration procedure could not be applied. 
           After successful execution of the above listed steps, DIM is ready
           for measuring dust impacts. Two measurement modes were used to
           measure dust at the comet:
              (1) Single events on one sensor side can be registered in the
                  so-called Burst Continuous (BC) Mode. The measured peak
                  amplitude U_m and the impact duration T_c are stored in a
                  compressed way: They are scaled to a logarithmic scale, 
                  and the counts for impacts with a particular logarithmic
                  U_m, T_c combination are stored in memory cells of different
                  sizes, depending on the expected frequency of such events.
                  Each BC measurement starts with a 10 s instrument warm-up
                  period which is not included in the measuring time.
              (2) In addition to the BC mode (which delivers the logarithmic
                  U_m, T_c matrix), the instrument can be operated in a
                  so-called Burst Continuous Test2 mode (BCT2). Similar to the
                  BC mode, the BCT2 mode delivers U_m and T_c for each 
                  individual impact. Here the raw uncompressed data are
                  transmitted instead of the compressed logarithmic values, and
                  in addition the event time when the impact or false signal
                  was registered. The number of data sets for impacts, 
                  which can be stored and transmitted to Earth in BCT2 mode, is
                  limited to 350. 
           Measuring values for the respective sensor side of the signal average
           are transmitted to Earth if sampling of average values is commanded.
     
           Subsystems                                                     
           ==========                                                     
           None
                                                                          
                                                                          
           Measured Parameters                                            
           ===================
           The electrical pulse generated by a particle hitting the DIM sensor
           is to first order a damped sine wave. The signal curve is analysed
           by the instrument electronics, and two parameters - impact duration
           T_c and the peak voltage U_m - are derived from the signal curve and
           transmitted to Earth.
              A) Impact Duration
              The impact duration is derived from the number of counts of a
              20 MHz clock. 
              So-called false and long events are identified. These 
              events are defined according to the measured impact duration.
              They are counted with an onboard counter and only their total
              numbers are transmitted to Earth. The impact 
              durations are transmitted for true dust impacts, but not for
              false and long  events.
              B) Peak Voltage
              The instrument provides the peak voltage of a single dust impact
              after logarithmic amplification. The transfer characteristics of
              the logarithmic DIM amplifier can vary with time. It is regularly
              checked by a calibration procedure.
              C) Event Time
              In addition to the impact duration and the peak voltage of a
              signal, the time in UTC when the event occurred is also stored
              for up to 350 events transmitted in Burst Continuous Test2 mode
              (not in Burst Continuous mode).
     
        PP
        ==
     
           Instrument Overview                                            
           ===================                                            
           PP is based on a quadrupole configuration of sensors attached to
           different parts of the Lander which are capacitively coupled to
           the comet surface.
           Metal meshes included in the soles of the +Y and -Y feet serve as
           receiving electrodes, connected via preamplifiers inside the soles
           to the SESAME electronics.
           Three transmitter electrodes are integrated with the +X foot sole,
           the MUPUS PEN and the APXS detector, respectively. Any combination
           of transmitter  electrodes can be selected by software. A digitally
           generated electrical sine wave of a freely programmable frequency
           is applied to the transmitter electrodes causing an AC-current to
           flow through the medium and cause a varying potential in the near
           environment of the Lander. Current, potential and phase difference
           between them are measured to determine the electrical properties
           of the medium underneath the Lander.
           The PP electronics is controlled by the common SESAME flight
           software.
     
           Scientific Objectives                                   
           =====================                                           
           Characterize the complex permittivity of the nucleus surface
           material, i.e. the electrical conductivity and dielectric
           polarizability, and their frequency and time dependences, down
           to a depth commensurate with the size of the lander. Assess the 
           sublimation rate of the volatile deposits, as functions of 
           temperature, illumination, and solar distance.
           Secondary objective: Measure the plasma density, and the
           electromagnetic and electrostatic waves generated by the 
           interaction between the nucleus environment and the solar wind,
           and thus monitor the outgassing activity
           of the comet.
                                                                          
           Calibration                                                    
           ===========                                                    
           Following calibration functions are applied to the SESAME-PP data
           at SONC level:
                 1) Translation of control parameters into timing information
                    for time series data
                 2) Translation of measured data into physical units mA, V,
                    phase angle, spectral power and voltage densities for
                    plasma data.
           Using laboratory simulations and reference measurements the measured
           data are converted and the instrument team's laboratory to 
           conductivity and permittivity values of the material in the vicinity
           of the electrodes.
     
           Operational Considerations                                     
           ==========================                                     
           SESAME-PP is very sensitive to any kind of electrical disturbances.
           During active or passive (permittivity or plasma) measurements
           instruments generating radio waves in the frequency range 5 Hz to
           40 kHz like CONSERT and the flywheel should not be operated if
           possible.
           Detectors with PP-electrode attachments - APXS and MUPUS-PEN -
           must not be powered while the respective attached PP-electrode is
           used for PP active measurements.
                                                                          
           Electronics                                                    
           ===========                                                    
           The PP instrument is controlled by an electronics board as part
           of the SESAME electronics and receives its +5V digital power,
           +/-5V and +/-12V analog power from the SESAME power supply board.
           For active measurements the SESAME software calculates the optimal
           combination of a sine wave vector and a read-out frequency to 
           generate a frequency close to the commanded one. The data
           vector is stored in the beginning of PP's on-board memory, read out
           at the defined frequency, converted into voltages by an 8-bit
           Digital-to-Analog Converter, then amplified to a voltage between
           +10 V and -10 V.
     
           Location                                                       
           ========                                                       
           The PP sensor system consists of 2 receivers, implemented as
           insulated wire meshes into the sole material of both soles at the
           +Y and -Y foot, 1 transmitter electrode mesh integrated into the
           +X foot soles, 1 transmitter built as ring disk elektrode attached
           to the outside of the APXS detector lid and 1 transmitter electrode
           implemented as insulated flexboard mesh attached to the MUPUS PEN
           deployment mechanism joint at the PEN. The receiver electrodes are
           directly connected to preamplifiers attached to the inside of one
           of the sole lids of the respective foot with a low impedance coaxial
           connection to the electronics board in the warm compartment while
           the transmitter electrodes are connected directly via Triax cables
           to the electronics.
           The Triax's central shield acts as guard to reduce stray capacitance
           effects.
                                                                          
           Operational Modes                                              
           =================                                              
           PP can be operated in 6 modes:
           1) Healthcheck: All 8 analog channels are measured providing a 
              conclusive summary of the instrument's status: ADC performance,
              transmitter current monitoring for all three electrodes,
              receiver preamplifiers, differential amplifier, the related
              power switches and the plasma monitor
           2) Passive mode: The potential difference between the two receiver
              electrodes is sampled with usually 40 kHz. The time series is
              analyzed with an on-board wavelet algorithm generating up to 10
              logarithmically spaced spectral power bins below half the sampling
              frequency. Sampling frequency, data vecor length and number of
              bins can be modified by changing the related parameters in the PP
              configuration table.
           3) Passive test mode: The measurement of the time vector is the same
              as in passive mode. Additionally to the power spectrum the complete
              original time vector is included in the telemetry for detailed 
              post-processing on ground.
           4) Active mode: A set of 20 frequencies at 3 different amplitudes
              each is generated by the PP electronics, the current from the
              wave generator through cables and the comet material, the induced 
              potential variation inside the comet medium and the phase shift
              between both signals are analyzed on board and included in the
              telemetry. The number of used frequencies and their values are
              defined in the configuration table and can be modified by command.
              The used transmitter electrode combination is defined via a
              command parameter
           5) Active test mode: A single frequency defined by a command
              parameter is generated, the current, induced potential difference
              and their phase difference are measured and included in the
              telemetry. Transmitter electrode combination and amplitude of
              the transmitted wave are defined as additional command parameters.
              Besides the results of the on-board analysis the complete current
              and potential vectors are included in the telemetry.
              Special usage: By defining as current monitor instead of one of
              the transmitter electrodes one of the receiver channels, the 
              direct response of that receiver channel as a function of time
              can be recorded. Together with the differential signal both
              receiver responses can be monitored separately for gain
              compensation of the pre-amplifiers or stray capacitance
              measurements.
           6) Plasma wave monitor: The plasma environment in the vicinity of
              the detector wire attached to the DIM sensor cube can be
              monitored by integrating the received charges. Depending on the
              amount of received charges the timer linked to an integrator
              with predefined limits will be stopped earlier or later. The
              timer value is provided as measurement result. The clock driving
              the timer can be adjusted by command parameter between 5 MHz and
              312.5 kHz to increase the sensitivity. If no sufficient number
              of charges are received, the largest possible 16-bit value is
              transmitted.
                                                                          
           Subsystems                                                     
           ==========                                                     
           None
                                                                          
                                                                          
           Measured Parameters                                            
           ===================
           Passive mode: scaled spectral power in logarithmically scaled
                         bins in internal units.
           Passive test mode: additionally a time vector of potential
                              differences in internal units
           Active mode: For each used frequency the current amplitude, 
                        potential difference amplitude and phase difference.
                        The given values are averaged across all measured
                        sine waves.
           Active test mode: additionally a time vector of current and of
                             potential difference values.
           Plasma wave monitor: timer scaling factor and integration time                                            
         </description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
