<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.sch"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
	xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.xsd http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1G00_1200.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument:rl.sd2</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>Sampling, Drilling and Distribution Subsystem for RL</title>
    <information_model_version>1.16.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2021-06-15</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Migrated from PDS3 catalog file.</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.rl</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <doi>10.1007/s11214-006-9134-6</doi>
      <reference_text>Ercoli-Finzi, A. et al., SD2 - How To Sample A           
        Comet, Space Sci. Rev., 128(1-4), 281-299, Feb. 2007.</reference_text>
      <description>Reference to the instrument paper.</description>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>Sampling, Drilling and Distribution Subsystem</name>
    <Type_List_Area>
      <ctli:Type_List>
        <ctli:type>Sub-Surface Tool</ctli:type>
      </ctli:Type_List>
    </Type_List_Area>
    <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>
    <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>
    <description>                                                   
                                                                           
        Instrument Overview                                                
        ===================        
        SD2 is a subsystem that aim to collect samples from the 
        ground of comet, verify volume of sample by an item called
        Volume Checker, and distribute the collected samples to the
        others experiments  (CIVA and COSAC). SD2 is composed by a 
        Drill, Carousel, Volume  Checker and electronic box. The 
        Drill creates the hole and collects samples at different 
        depths. The samples are placed in ovens mounted on the 
        distribution subsystem, the Carousel, which is in charge of
        distributing the samples to the designated experiment.
        Before distribution, the volume of the collected sample is 
        measured by the Volume Checker.

        Scientific Objectives                                            
        =====================        
        The scientific goal of SD2 is to collect samples from the 
        comet soil, measure the volume of the sample using the Volume 
        Checker, and distribute the collected samples to the experiments
        CIVA and COSAC. In conjunction with complementary data from 
        lander subsystems and instruments, SD2 scientific data can also
        be used to determine the depth at which the sample has been 
        collected.

        Calibration                                  
        ===========        
        No calibration is planned for the telemetry data. Only a 
        translation in more comprehensible format is performed. Thus,
        the calibrated data are obtained by the mere translation of the
        raw data.
                                                                         
        Operational Considerations                                      
        ==========================      
        SD2 translation is commanded in offsets from SD2 reference (zero)
        position. Thus, the operator cannot command the depth directly:
        the depth reached can be deduced if the distance of the soil from
        the lander baseplate in the drilling area is available.

        Operational Modes
        =================
        Two main operational modes are foreseen for SD2 Nominal and Dead
        mode. The first one is for the nominal operational mode; the second
        one is associated to failure occurrence.
                       
        Measured Parameters    
        ===================
        Drill position; Drill rotation speed; Carousel position.
    </description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
