<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:giada.ro</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>GRAIN IMPACT ANALYSER AND DUST ACCUMULATOR for RO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.ro::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Bussoletti E. et al., The GIADA experiment for Rosetta mission to comet
                   46P/Wirtanen: design and performances, Adv. Space Res., 24, 1139, 1999.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BUSSOLETTIETAL1999</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Colangeli, L. et al., The Grain Impact Analyser and Dust Accumulator (GIADA)
                   experiment for the Rosetta mission: design, performances and first results,
                   Space Sci. Rev., 128(1-4), p.803-821, Feb 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.COLANGELIETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Esposito F. et al., Physical aspect of an &apos;Impact sensor&apos; for the detection of
                   Cometary dust Momentum onboard the Rosetta Space Mission, Adv. Space Res., 29,
                   8, 1159-1163, 2002.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ESPOSITOETAL2002</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Mazzotta Epifani E. et al., The Grain Detection System for the GIADA
                   instrument: design and expected performances, Adv. Space Res., 29, 8, 1165,
                   2002.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MAZZOTTAEPIFETAL2002</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Palomba, E., et al., The sticking efficiency of quartz crystals for cosmic
                   sub-micron grain collection, Planet. Space Sci., 49, 919, 2001.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.PALOMBAETAL2001</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Palomba, E., et al., Performance of Micro-Balances for dust flux measurement,
                   Adv. Space Res., 29, 1155-1158, 2002.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.PALOMBAETAL2002</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>GRAIN IMPACT ANALYSER AND DUST ACCUMULATOR</name>
        <type>Dust</type> <!--RChen/EN was Dust Detector-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
    The Grain Impact Analyser and Dust Accumulator (GIADA) is the
    instrument on-board the ROSETTA Orbiter that has been designed to
    study the dust environment of comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko.
    Thanks to the rendezvous configuration of the mission, GIADA will
    be plunged into the dust environment of the coma and will explore
    the dust flux evolution and grain dynamics vs. position and time.
    This is a unique opportunity to perform measurements on key
    parameters that no ground-based observation or fly-by mission are
    able to obtain and that no tail or coma model elaborated so far
    have been able to properly simulate. The coma and nucleus
    properties shall be, then, clarified with consequent improvement
    of models describing both inner and outer coma evolution and dust
    and gas emission from the nucleus during different evolution
    phases. GIADA shall measure mass/size of single particles larger
    than about 15 micron, together with momentum in the range
    6.5 x 10^(-10) - 4.0 x 10^(-4) kg m s^(-1) and for velocities up
    to about 300 m s^(-1). The cumulative mass shall be detected,
    with sensitivity 10^(-10) g, for micron/submicron particles.
    These performances shall provide a statistically relevant set of
    data about dust physical and dynamic properties in the environment
    of comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko.
    GIADA is based on three different sensing methods. A Grain
    Detection System (GDS) shall detect optically the transit of each
    single grain entering GIADA, without affecting its dynamic
    properties; an Impact Sensor (IS) shall monitor, by piezoelectric
    sensors (PZTs), the momentum released by the same grain upon
    impact onto an aluminium plate. Independently, five Micro Balance
    Systems (MBSs), pointing towards different space directions, will
    measure the cumulative deposition in time of fine dust.
 
    A more complete description of the GIADA instrument is in
    RO_GIA_OACUPA_IF_011_I3 (reported in DOCUMENT dir). Other
    additional information are given in the following papers (as cited
    in REF.CAT):
        [BUSSOLETTIETAL1999] and [COLANGELIETAL2007] for what
        concerns the overall GIADA instrument description,
        [ESPOSITOETAL2002] for what concerns working principle
        and tests on IS,
        [MAZZOTTAEPIFETAL2002] for what concerns working principle
        and tests on GDS,
        [PALOMBAETAL2001] and [PALOMBAETAL2002] for what concerns
        the performances and working principle of Microbalances.

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
