<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument:ro.midas</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MICRO-IMAGING DUST ANALYSIS SYSTEM for RO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias><alternate_title>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:midas.ro</alternate_title></Alias>  <!-- deprecated LID -->
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-02-24</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Changed inst LIDs from
                      u:n:p:c:i:instID.scID to
                      u:n:p:c:i:scID.instID
                    Changed LIDs from urn:nasa:pds: to urn:esa:psa:
                    And per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.7,
                    changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.ro</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Riedler, W. et al., MIDAS - The Micro-Imaging Dust Analysis System for the
                   Rosetta Mission, Space Sci. Rev., 128(1-4), 869-904, Feb. 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.RIEDLERETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>MICRO-IMAGING DUST ANALYSIS SYSTEM</name>
        <type>Microscope</type> <!--RChen/EN was Scanning Probe Microscope-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
  This catalog file contains excerpts from Riedler et al, 2006.
  Refer to this paper for an in depth description of the
  instrument.
 
  Scientific Objectives
  =====================
 
  The main objective of the instrument MIDAS (Micro-Imaging
  Dust Analysis System) on board of the Rosetta Orbiter is the
  analysis of particles collected in the coma of Comet
  67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko by means of atomic force microscopy.
  The instrument will provide 3D images and statistical
  parameters of the particles in the nm-um range. The main
  anticipated results include
  - 3D images of single particles,
  - images of the textural complexity of particle aggregates,
  - identification of crystalline material,
  - identification of sub-features on clean surfaces which
  provides insight into the growth conditions (e.g. twinning
  defects) and/or storage environment (e.g. dissolution marks),
  - statistical evaluation of the particles according to size,
  volume and shape,
  - variation of particle fluxes between individual exposures of
  the collector unit on time scales of hours.
 
  Measurement Principle
  =====================
 
  An Atomic Force Microscope forms the heart of MIDAS. A sharp
  tip scanning the surface of a sample is used to derive
  information from the tip-sample interaction, which depends on
  the nature of the tip and is based on mechanical force and -
  in connection with suitable sensors - magnetic force.
  The surface features can be resolved with almost atomic
  resolution. MIDAS adopts dynamic AFM as the main working mode
  and employs piezo-resistive cantilevers that can detect their
  own deflection electrically. In this mode, the cantilever is
  excited at its natural mechanical resonance frequency (~100
  kHz) at close distance to the sample. The amplitude of the
  cantilever vibration is of the order 100 nm. Close to the
  surface, the resonance frequency of the cantilever changes due
  to the tip-surface interaction forces. The changes of
  resonance frequency and amplitude are used to derive the
  topography of the sample in a closed loop system. The basic
  elements of an AFM are a piezoelectric scanner for cantilever
  movement, a tip mounted near the edge of the cantilever, a
  detection system for cantilever deflection, and a feedback
  system to control the vertical tip position. In addition, a
  coarse approach system is needed to bring the tip to within
  the working distance of the piezoelectric scanner.
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
 
  The MIDAS instrument is a single mechanical unit. The top part
  houses the elements of the AFM and the system to collect and
  transport the dust samples from the exposure position to the
  head of the microscope. A funnel-shaped dust intake system,
  which protrudes through the outer spacecraft wall, is attached
  to the upper part of the box. An external cover protects the
  internal elements against contamination during ground
  operations and launch. A shutter at the outer end of the
  funnel controls the exposure time of one facet at a time on
  the dust collector wheel inside the box. This wheel can be
  rotated and translated to transport the dust samples to one of
  16 sensor elements (cantilevers) in the AFM after exposure.
  The array of cantilevers is fixed to the Z microscope stage,
  which is attached to the high-resolution XY positioning stage.
  All stages are driven by piezoelectric systems, and the
  displacements can be measured by a strain gauge and capacitive
  sensors. In addition, the voltages applied to the
  piezoelectric actuators provide the same displacement
  information through the respective calibration curves. To
  begin the imaging process, the XYZ-stage is brought into
  contact with the sample on the dust collector wheel by the
  approach mechanism. As soon as the selected cantilever senses
  contact with the sample (indicated by a deflection of the
  cantilever in contact mode, or a change of amplitude in
  dynamic mode), the scanning operation can start. After the
  measurement, the XYZ-stage has to be retracted, and another
  approach procedure has to be performed before the measurement
  on another area. The 16 available needles have slightly
  different characteristics and shapes, and four out of them are
  additionally sensitive to magnetic forces. As the measurements
  by the AFM are sensitive to microvibrations induced by other
  active mechanisms aboard Rosetta, the AFM element is fixed to
  the base plate of the box by four studs of highly flexible
  silicone material with a high damping capability. During
  ground operations and launch, the AFM platform was locked in
  its zero position by a clamping device, which is unlatched
  after launch by a mechanism using paraffin actuators. The
  lower part of the instrument serves as the electronics box,
  which could be decoupled from the upper section to help the
  assembly process. Most of the printed circuit boards are
  located in the lower section, but a few sensitive amplifiers
  reside in the AFM area close to the sensors. The electronics
  box has a connector panel for redundant electrical interfaces
  to data, power and checkout. Some additional connectors, e.g.
  for pyrotechnic actuators, are mounted on the AFM box.
 
  Operational Modes and On-Board Software
  =======================================
 
  MIDAS has to acquire and analyse samples of cometary dust at
  regular intervals throughout all phases of the mission. At
  first, the selected facet of the dust collector wheel has to
  be exposed to the ambient dust flux until the required surface
  coverage by dust is achieved. The best coverage value remains
  to be determined experimentally and will also depend on the
  type of analysis planned (imaging of individual particles or
  statistics). Current estimates indicate a surface coverage of
  0.1% should be sufficient for most purposes. The required
  exposure times range from fractions of an hour during high
  cometary activity at close distances to the nucleus (few
  cometary radii) to several days during moderate activity
  and/or larger distances. Apart from the facet selection and
  shutter operations at the beginning and end, MIDAS may be left
  unpowered. Alternatively, if it remains in standby mode, it is
  able to listen to broadcast messages that may be used to
  adjust the exposure time autonomously. If MIDAS is powered
  during exposure, it may also simultaneously process previously
  obtained images. After exposure, the shutter is closed and the
  target wheel can be turned to another position for the
  exposure of another facet, or a facet can be placed underneath
  the scanner head. AFM images of the exposed target areas are
  obtained by scanning. At the beginning of the scan mode, an
  area on the collector wheel is selected by rotating the chosen
  facet under the scanner head. In each scan, only a small part
  of the exposed surface is imaged by the microscope. The
  selection of scan areas within a facet is achieved by fine
  control of the angle and lateral position of the wheel. A
  single exposure period will be followed by several scanning
  operations on the previously exposed facet at varying
  resolutions. It is also possible to scan or rescan facets that
  have been exposed much earlier. The time needed to scan a
  single area on a facet depends on the operational settings and
  is of the order of several hours. Processing and transmitting
  the acquired data is typically performed after completion of a
  scan (image acquisition). Typically, processing time is short
  compared to the image acquisition time. The baseline MIDAS
  operations involve alternating between exposure, scanning and
  processing, but data collection simultaneously with the
  processing and transmission of collected images is also
  possible. Some images will be reduced to simple statistical
  parameters for transmission (for example, the number and sizes
  of dust grains), while others will be studied at full
  resolution. The standard modes for exposure, scanning, and
  image processing as well as the associated positioning of the
  target surfaces are complemented by modes for checkout and
  in-flight calibration.
  The MIDAS software is structured into a low-level software
  kernel and a high-level main program. Every time the
  instrument is switched on, the kernel program is loaded into
  the Random Access Memory (RAM) and executed. After a
  successful check of the Electrically Erasable Programmable
  Read-Only Memory (EEPROM), the main program is started and the
  instrument enters standby mode. The software kernel handles
  the interface between the hardware and the main program, basic
  telecommand processing, generation of basic housekeeping
  telemetry, software maintenance and uploads, timing and low-
  level control of the hardware. Main program tasks include
  high-level instrument control, scientific and extended
  housekeeping data generation, and image processing. Control of
  the instrument relies on sequences of low-level commands
  combined into larger packets. Recognised packets are processed
  with high or normal priority, depending on the telecommand
  type. Commands with high priority are executed immediately.
  They include time-critical commands, such as program abort,
  error reporting, and all commands processed by the kernel such
  as telecommand acknowledgements. Commands with normal priority
  are stored in a command buffer and executed sequentially. The
  low priority buffer is used for housekeeping and science data
  transfer where the packets are grouped into larger blocks. Two
  different subtypes of housekeeping data packets and six
  subtypes of science data packets have been defined. Science
  data packets are generated during or after acquisition of an
  image and processing of the image data. In general, data from
  one image will extend over many packets, depending on the
  resolution. Among the routinely used modes, only the scan mode
  produces raw science data that are stored temporarily in
  instrument memory. The size of an image can be set to
  multiples of 32 pixels in each direction, with a maximum of
  512 pixels. A typical single image of 256x256 pixels requires
  128 Kbyte of memory. As 1 Mbyte is available for raw data,
  eight typical images can be held. Onboard image data
  processing is foreseen for two main reasons: the reduction of
  the data volume, and the identification and characterisation
  of dust grains to determine the coordinates of following scans
  (zoom-in).
 
  Key Capabilities and Characteristics
  ====================================
  Maximum scan field    94 x 94 um
  Minimum scan field    0.97 x 0.97 um
  Image resolution      256 x 256 pixels (typ.),
                        512 x 512 pixels (max.)
  Lateral resolution    variable 3.8 nm ... 400 nm
  Height resolution     0.16 nm
  Number of AFM tips    16
  Number of targets     61
  Mass                  8.2 kg
  Power consumption     8.3 to 13.4 W  (peak power &lt;17 W)
  Telemetry rate        100 bit s-1

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
