<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument:ro.rpcies</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>ROSETTA PLASMA CONSORTIUM - ION AND ELECTRON SENSOR for RO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias><alternate_title>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rpcies.ro</alternate_title></Alias>  <!-- deprecated LID -->
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-02-24</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Changed inst LIDs from
                      u:n:p:c:i:instID.scID to
                      u:n:p:c:i:scID.instID
                    Changed LIDs from urn:nasa:pds: to urn:esa:psa:
                    And per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.7,
                    changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:esa:psa:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.ro</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Burch, J. et al., IES - The ROSETTA Ion and Electron Spectrometer, Space Sci.
                   Rev., 128(1-4), 697-712, Feb. 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BURCHETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>ROSETTA PLASMA CONSORTIUM - ION AND ELECTRON SENSOR</name>
        <type>Particle Detector</type> <!--RChen/EN was Plasma Instrument. No obvious choice. TBD in JSH's xl file-->
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
    Instrument Overview
    ===================
    The Ion and Electron Sensor (IES) is one of the 5 instrument
    members of Rosetta Plasma Consortium (RPC). The objective of the
    instrument is to measure the flux of ions and electrons as a
    function of energy and direction in the solar wind, and in the
    environment during the flybys of Earth, Mars, the two asteroids,
    and comet 67p/Churyumov-Gerasimenko.
 
    Scientific Objectives
    =====================
    The scientific objectives of the instrument are to measure and
    understand the dynamics, structure, and evolution of the plasma
    properties in these environments.  Of particular interest is the
    interaction of the solar wind with the comet, especially the
    formation of pickup ion structures and their relation to the local
    magnetic field.
 
    Calibration
    ===========
    The IES instrument was calibrated on the ground in the ion
    calibration facility at the Southwest Research Institute,
    San Antonio, TX, USA. In addition cross-calibrations are performed
    in flight with the RPC-LAP and RPC-ICA instruments.
 
    Operational Considerations
    ==========================
    RPC-IES should be operated continuosly as long as power and
    telemetry rate permit.  When possible, all other RPC instruments
    should be operated while RPC-IES is in operation in order to allow
    joint analysis of the resulting data. RPC-IES high voltages should
    be turned off 5 min before until 5 min after thruster firings to
    prevent arcing.
 
    RPC-IES Instrument Description
    =========
    The Rosetta Ion and Electron Sensor (RPC-IES) is comprised of a
    double toroidal top-hat electrostatic analyzer (ESA), one analyzer
    for electrons, the other for ions, arranged back-to-back.  The
    common entrance aperture has a 360 degree field of view in the
    symmetry (denoted here by azimuth) plane. Electrostatic angular
    deflection optics give a scanned field of view of +/- 45 degrees
    normal to the sensor symmetry axis (denoted here by the elevation
    angle).
 
    The instrument objective is to obtain ion and electron
    distribution functions over the energy range from 4.32 eV/e to
    17.67 keV/e, with a basic time resolution of 128 s. This geometry
    allows IES to analyze both electrons and positive ions with a
    single entrance aperture, simultaneously. The IES top hat
    analyzers have toroidal geometry with a smaller radius of
    curvature in the deflection plane than in the orthogonal plane.
    This toroidal feature results in a flat deflection plate geometry
    at the poles of the analyzers and has the advantage that the focal
    point is located outside the analyzers rather than within them, as
    is the case with spherical top hat analyzers. The IES field of
    view (FOV) thus encompasses a total solid angle of 2.8 Pi
    steradians.
 
    Ions and electrons approaching the IES first encounter a
    toroidal-shaped grounded grid encircling the instrument. Once
    inside the grid the electric field produced by bipolar electrodes
    deflects ions and electrons with a range of energies and incident
    directions into a field-free entrance aperture containing serrated
    walls to minimize scattering of ultraviolet light and stray
    charged particles into the instrument. The particles then enter
    the top hat region and the electric field produced by the flat
    electrostatic analyzer segments of the ion and electron analyzers.
 
    Particles with an energy accepted by the ESA and within a narrow
    4% energy pass band will pass through the analyzers and be focused
    onto either the electron or ion microchannel plates (MCPs), which
    produce charge pulses on 16 discrete anodes for each, which define
    the azimuth acceptance angles. For electrons the anodes are of
    equal width so the azimuth resolution is 22.5 degrees.  (It was
    discovered after launch that electron channel 11 was noisy so it
    was decided not to download the data from that channel.  Hence
    only fill data appear for that channel.)  For ions the 16 anodes
    are divided unequally in size, with 9 of them (each 5 degrees
    wide) oriented in the direction expected to view the solar wind
    most of the time (anodes 3 to 11).  The remaining 7 anodes are
    each 45 degrees wide. For both electrons and ions the nominal
    resolution in the elevation direction is 5 degrees.  This
    resolution would provide 18 measurement bins over the 90 degrees
    full elevation FOV.  However, in order to simplify the instrument
    electronics, the FOV has been divided into 16 (=24) bins.  This
    results in a small gap in coverage between bins.
 
    The selected energy will correspond to a particular 5 degree
    elevation entrance angle, depending on the ratio of voltages on
    the angle deflectors and the ESAs.  Note that the use of the terms
    &apos;azimuth&apos; and &apos;elevation&apos; angle for IES differs from the
    conventional terminology of &apos;polar&apos; and &apos;azimuth&apos;.
 
    Viewing Maps (from the RPC-IES IK data)
    ======================================
 
    IES/Electron Sector Layout
 
    The IES/Electron Sector&apos;s 360.0 x 90.0 degrees aperture is split
    into 256 sectors -- 16 in-plane (azimuthal) by 16 cross-plane
    (polar). In the in-plane direction the sectors are numbered from 0
    to 15, in the cross-plane direction the sectors are also numbered
    0 to 15. All 16 in-plane sectors are 22.5 degrees wide with their
    center view directions 22.5 degrees apart. In the cross-plane
    direction all sectors have the same size of 5 degrees with their
    center view directions 6 degrees apart. In-plane the &apos;view
    direction&apos; of each sector is looking inwards, from the sector
    position through the center of the aperture.
 
    This diagram illustrates in-plane (azimuthal) IES/Electron sector
    layout:
 
                  ^ +Yies
                  |                        A# indicate the azimuthal
              V12 |  V11                     sector # position in
         V13  ....|....   V10                 the sensor assembly.
           .&apos; A4  |  A3 `.
      V14.&apos; A5    |     A2`. V9            V# indicate the # sector
        . A6      |       A1.                     view direction.
    V15.          |          . V8
       .A7        |        A0.                 For example, for
       .          o--------------&gt; +Xies       Sector 2 the view
       .A8       / +Zies  A15.              direction is the vector
    V0 .        /            . V7             emanating from the
        .A9    /         A14.               aperture center through
      V1 .A10 /         A13.  V6            the point designated
          `. / A11  A12  .&apos;                         by V2.
          V2 `......... &apos; V5
           /   V3   V4
          V
       Azimuthal sector &apos;3&apos;
          view direction
 
 
    This diagram illustrates cross-plane (polar) IES/Electron Sensor
    sector layout:
 
 
                  +Yies     Polar Sector &apos;3&apos;
                    ^         ^ view dir.     P# indicate the polar
                 V8 | V7     /                 sector # position in
               .----|----.  V3                  the sensor assembly.
       V15  ,-&apos;   P8|P7   `/.   V0
          .&apos;        |     P3 `.
         `.P15      |    /  P0.&apos;             V# indicate the # sector
           `.       |   /   .&apos;                    view direction.
             `.     |  /  .&apos;
               `.   | / .&apos;                    For example, for polar
                 `. |/.&apos;                       Sector 3 the view
     &lt;-------------`o&apos;+Xies                  direction is the vector
   +Zies          .&apos; `.                        emanating from the
                .&apos;     `.                    aperture center through
              .&apos;         `.                     the point designated
            .&apos;             `.                       by V3.
          .&apos;P15            P0`.
          `.                 .&apos;
        V15 `-.   P8 P7   ,-&apos;  V0
               `---------&apos;
                 V8   V7
 
 
    IES/Ion Sector Layout
 
    The IES/Ion Sector&apos;s 360.0 x 90.0 degrees aperture is split into
    256 sectors -- 16 in-plane (azimuthal) by 16 cross-plane (polar).
    In the in-plane direction the sectors are numbered from 0 to 15,
    in the cross-plane direction the sectors are numbered 0 to 15.
    Not all 16 in-plane sectors have the same size: seven of them --
    sectors 0-2 and 12-15 -- are 45 degrees wide while the other
    nine -- sectors 3-11 -- are 5 degrees wide. In the cross-plane
    direction all sectors have the same size of 5 degrees with their
    center view directions 6 degrees apart. In-plane the &apos;view
    direction&apos; of each sector is looking inwards, from the sector
    position through the center of the aperture.
 
    This diagram illustrates in-plane (azimuthal) IES/Ion sector
    layout:
 
                      +Yies
                    ^
                    |                        A# indicate the azimuthal
                    |                          sector # position in
            V15 ....|....  V0                    the sensor assembly.
             .&apos; A7 A11    `.
           .&apos; A3    |   A12 `.               V# indicate the # sector
       V14.         |         . V1                  view direction.
         . A2       |      A13 .
         .          |          .     +Xies       For example, for
         .          o--------------&gt;           Sector 12 the view
         .         / +Zies     .              direction is the vector
         . A1     /        A14 .               emanating from the
       V13.      /            . V2            aperture center through
           .    /            .                 the point designated
            `.A0        A15.&apos;                         by V12.
            V12 ......... &apos; V3
             /      V11  V7
            V
  Azimuthal sector &apos;12&apos;
     view direction
 
 
    This diagram illustrates cross-plane (polar) IES/Ion Sensor sector
    layout:
 
 
                   +Yies     Polar Sector &apos;3&apos;
                     ^         ^ view dir.     P# indicate the polar
                  V8 | V7     /                 sector # position in
                .----|----.  V3                  the sensor assembly.
        V15  ,-&apos;   P8|P7   `/.   V0
           .&apos;        |     P3 `.
          `.P15      |    /  P0.&apos;             V# indicate the # sector
            `.       |   /   .&apos;                    view direction.
              `.     |  /  .&apos;
                `.   | / .&apos;                    For example, for polar
                  `. |/.&apos;                       Sector 3 the view
      &lt;-------------`o&apos;+Xies                  direction is the vector
    +Zies          .&apos; `.                        emanating from the
                 .&apos;     `.                    aperture center through
               .&apos;         `.                     the point designated
             .&apos;             `.                       by V3.
           .&apos;P15            P0`.
           `.                 .&apos;
         V15 `-.   P8 P7   ,-&apos;  V0
                `---------&apos;
                  V8   V7
 
 
    Electronics
    ===========
    Pulses from the segmented anode are amplified by charge-sensitive
    preamplifiers (CSPs) and recorded in the 16 x 24 bit ion and
    electron counters. The data are buffered before being sent to the
    output serial register for transmission to the RPC Plasma
    Interface Unit (PIU) as serial telemetry packets. The stepping
    sequences of the angle and energy deflection voltages of the
    instrument are fixed in memory.
 
    The IES instrument contains a single micro-controller (RTX20X10)
    which communicates with the RPC-PIU over the IEEE 1355 bus,
    transmits the collected science data, and monitors the instrument
    status. The flight software is written in the C and Forth
    programming languages. The PIU stores and re-transmits to the
    spacecraft the data stream that the instrument produces. No
    special data handling is required. Commands and command sequences
    for IES are formulated by the IES team, sent to Imperial College,
    where they are translated to the proper format and sent to the
    project ground system.  They are eventually uploaded to the
    spacecraft and are stored for later execution. In some cases the
    command may be executed immediately.  The sequence provides for
    selection of one or more operational modes (see below) or in some
    cases repeated cycling through a series of modes.
 
    High Voltages
    =======
    The voltages for the ESAs, deflector (DEF), and MCPs are derived
    from a single supply of 8514 volts.  The ESA and DEF voltages are
    stepped according to LUTs. The ESA sweeps between 0.407 V and
    1667 V in 128 approximately logarithmically spaced steps.  The DEF
    steps between -6667 and +6667 V, alternating negative to positive
    and positive to negative between the 2 deflector plates.  The MCP
    potentials can be set to a potential between +/- 2500 V and
    +/-3500 V, the positive level for the electrons and negative for
    the ions.  Except for a short test on May 1-2, 2010, the levels
    have been at 2500 V based on measurements on the ground before
    flight.
 
    Data Binning
    =======
    Since IES produces more data than can be transmitted within its
    telemetry allocation, in order to compress the data they are
    binned in a lossy fashion by use of look up tables (LUTs) stored
    onboard in the instrument.  (See the specific documentation on the
    details of the different data modes.) For example, the counts from
    adjacent energy steps can be combined and the sums transmitted to
    ground, or the counts from a range of energy and/or angle bins or
    any combination of these, are transmitted, depending on the
    scientific objective for a particular observation period. Hence
    the appearance of the data structure will depend on the mode for
    that particular observation.
 
    Flyback
    =======
    Cycling of ESA voltages is completed using 128 steps (0 to 127)
    which include 4 steps (124 to 127) during &apos;flyback&apos; (FB), the
    transition from the highest voltage of 1667 V (step 123) to 0 V
    (step 127). While the actual transition time does not require all
    4 steps, i.e. the 0 V level may be attained in 2 steps or less,
    science data readings during the first three steps of the flyback
    should be considered unreliable. When flyback steps are averaged,
    they are averaged only with other flyback steps. Step 127 may be
    considered as 0V for background measurements if not averaged.
 
    Location
    ========
    The IES instrument is located on the +Z deck of the Rosetta
    spacecraft in the corner formed by the +X and +Y spacecraft
    surfaces.  The instrument is oriented such that the symmetry axis
    of the ESAs (i. e. through their poles) is at 45 degrees to the +Z
    as well as the +X and +Y spacecraft surfaces.  Hence the azimuth
    plane of the FOV (and hence the elevation 0 degrees) is also
    tilted upward 45 degrees.  This arrangement was selected in order
    to minimize interference to the FOV by any spacecraft or other
    instrument structures but will still allow viewing the solar wind
    when the spacecraft is oriented favorably (i.e. when the angle
    between the spacecraft +Z axis and the sun is between 70 degrees
    and 100 degrees).
 
    Operational Modes
    =================
    When powered on, the IES instrument runs its boot PROM code. The
    boot PROM, by default, checks all RAM, EEPROM and PROM resources
    within the IES instrument and reports their status in
    housekeeping. Whether the PAUSE-PROM or RESUME-PROM mode is
    entered depends on what was planned for the first operation.
    PAUSE-PROM prevents the PROM from going automatically into the
    EEPROM code so that telecommanding or maintenance mode
    telecommands can be executed. The boot PROM can execute the entire
    suite of maintenance mode commands but only a limited set of
    telecommands. In order to program the EEPROM using the activate
    patch function in maintenance mode, IES must be running from the
    boot PROM. This is because the boot PROM code runs using a lower
    clock frequency which is amenable to the EEPROM write timing. The
    EEPROM code is run at a faster clock frequency to accommodate all
    the tasks that must be executed during science data acquisition.
    Housekeeping is generated every 32 seconds. Maintenance and event
    messages are possible from this mode.
 
    RESUME-PROM is a waiting mode to allow telecommands or maintenance
    mode commands to be received by IES before automatically going to
    the EEPROM code. Housekeeping is generated every 32 seconds. Event
    messages are possible from this mode. LVSCI-EEPROM is the first
    EEPROM mode entered and allows IES commands to be executed. This
    is the mode used for low-voltage stimulation operation.
    Housekeeping is generated every 32 seconds. Science and event
    messages are possible from this mode.
 
    HVSCI-EEPROM is entered if an IES-INSTR-PROG-MODE HVSCI
    telecommand is received. Here, high-voltage telecommands can be
    executed to turn on the HV supplies and manipulate their settings.
    All plasma science data are acquired in this mode. Housekeeping is
    generated every 32 seconds. Science and event messages are
    possible from this mode.
 
    LVENG-EEPROM is used for executing maintenance commands and memory
    manipulation telecommands. Note that the EPROM cannot be written
    in this mode due to the timing constraints mentioned in the
    PAUSEPROM description. Housekeeping is generated every 32 seconds.
    Maintenance and event messages are possible from this mode.
 
    A science data collection mode is determined by the LUT(s)
    specified in the definition of the mode and determined by the
    command sequence sent to the instrument.  See the 3 tables in the
    Appendix to the Rosetta-RPC-IES Planetary Science Archive
    Interface Control Document, Document No. 10991-IES-EAICD-01 for
    details of the data collapsing for each science mode. These tables
    give the definitions currently stored in IES memory and show how
    the full 128 energy by 16 azimuth by 16 elevation bins are
    selected and or combined to fit either the normal or burst
    telemetry cases.
 
    Acquisition Timing
    ==================
    IES uses cycles of varying durations to acquire ION and ELC data
    across the energy and angular ranges to allow tailoring of
    energy/angular resolution and time resolution. A cycle requires
    128, 256, 512 or 1024 seconds to complete sweeping across the
    energy range using 128 steps. At each energy step, the deflection
    voltages are swept using 16 steps (elevations). Each step requires
    a rise and settle time of 30ms during which no acquisition takes
    place followed by integration time or acquisition window. The
    following table lists the cycle durations, and the associated
    acquisition times.
 
    Cycle Duration (seconds): 128
    Duration to complete each energy step which inclues 16 elevation
    steps (seconds): 1
    Acquisition/integration time at each elevation/deflection step
    (milliseconds): 32.5
 
    Cycle Duration (seconds): 256
    Duration to complete each energy step which inclues 16 elevation
    steps (seconds): 2
    Acquisition/integration time at each elevation/deflection step
    (milliseconds): 95
 
    Cycle Duration (seconds): 512
    Duration to complete each energy step which inclues 16 elevation
    steps (seconds): 4
    Acquisition/integration time at each elevation/deflection step
    (milliseconds): 220
 
    Cycle Duration (seconds): 1024
    Duration to complete each energy step which inclues 16 elevation
    steps (seconds): 8
    Acquisition/integration time at each elevation/deflection step
    (milliseconds): 470
 
    Measured Parameters
    ===================
      Energy:  Range                   4.32 eV to 17.67 KeV
               Resolution              4%
 
      Angle:   Range (FOV)            90 deg x 360 deg  (2.8 Pi sr)
               Resolution (electrons) 5 deg (elev) x 22.5 deg (azim)
                                      (16 azimuthal x 16 elevation)
               Resolution (ions)      5 deg (elev) x 45 deg (azim)
                                          for 7 sectors
                                      5 deg (elev) x 5 deg (azim)
                                          for 9 sectors
                                      (16 azimuthal x 16 elevation)
 
     Temporal resolution:
               3D distribution         128s
               downlink rates           Normal: 5 bps
                                        Burst:  250 bps
 
     Geometric factor:
      total (ions)            5 x 10e-4 cm^2 sr eV/eV counts/ion
      per 45 deg sector       5 x 10e-5 cm^2 sr eV/eV counts/ion
      per 5 deg sector        7 x 10e-6 cm^2 sr eV/eV counts/ion
      total (electrons)       5 x 10e-5 cm^2 sr eV/eV counts/electron
      per sector (electrons)  5 x 10e-6 cm^2 sr eV/eV counts/electron

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
