<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:urap.uly</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>UNIFIED RADIO AND PLASMA WAVE EXPERIMENT for ULY</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.uly::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   MacDowall, R.J., R.A. Hess, N. Lin, G. Thejappa, A. Balogh, and J.L. Phillips,
                   Ulysses spacecraft observations of radio and plasma waves: 1991:1995, submitted
                   to Astron. Astrophys., 1996.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.MACDOWALLETAL1996</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Stone, R.G., J.L. Bougeret, J. Caldwell, P. Canu, Y. de Conchy, N.
                   Cornilleau-Wehrlin, M.D. Desch, J. Fainberg, K. Goetz, M.L. Goldstein, C.C.
                   Harvey, S. Hoang, R. Howard, M.L. Kaiser, P.J. Kellogg, B. Klein, R. Knoll, A.
                   Lecacheux, D. Lengyel-Frey, R.J. MacDowall, R. Manning, C.A. Meetre, A. Meyer,
                   N. Monge, S. Monson, G. Nicol, M.J. Reiner, J.L. Steinberg, E. Torres, C. de
                   Villedary, F. Wouters, and P. Zarka, The Unified Radio and Plasma Wave
                   Investigation, Astron. Astrophys. Suppl. Ser. 92, 291-316, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.STONEETAL1992A</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>UNIFIED RADIO AND PLASMA WAVE EXPERIMENT</name>
        <type>Plasma Wave Spectrometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    (excerpted from: [STONEETAL1992A])
 
    Abstract.  -- The scientific objectives of the Ulysses Unifiewd
    Radio and Plasma wave (URAP) experiment are twofold: 1) the
    determination of the direction, angular size, and polarization
    of radio sources for remote sensing of the heliosphere and the
    Jovian magnetosphere and 2) the detailed study of local wave
    phenomena, which determine the transport coefficients of the
    ambient plasma.  The tracking of solar radio bursts, for
    example, can provide three dimensional &apos;snap-shots&apos; of the
    large scale magnetic field configuration along which the solar
    exciter particles propagate.  URAP observations of Jovian radio
    emissions should greatly improve the determination of source
    locations and consequently our understanding of the generation
    mechanism(s) of planetary radio emissions.  The study of
    observed wave-particle interactions will improve our
    understanding of the processes that occur in the solar wind and
    at Jupiter and of radio wave generation . . . .  The URAP
    sensors consist of a 72.5 m electric field antenna in the spin
    plane, a 7.5-m electric field monopole along the spin axis and
    a pair of orthogonal search coil magnetic antennas.  The
    various receivers, designed to encompass specific needs of the
    investigation, cover the frequency range from DC to 1 MHz.  A
    relaxation sounder provides very accurate electron density
    measurements.  Radio and plasma wave observations are shown to
    demonstrate the capabilities and limitations of the URAP
    instruments: radio observations include solar bursts, auroral
    kilometric radiation, and Jovian bursts; plasma waves include
    Langmuir waves, ion acoustic-like noise, and whistlers.
 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
