<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:vhm-fgm.uly</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>VECTOR HELIUM/FLUXGATE MAGNETOMETERS for ULY</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.uly::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Balogh, A., T.J. Beek, R.J. Forsyth, P.C. Hedgecock, R.J. Marquedant, E.J.
                   Smith, D.J. Southwood, and B.T. Tsurutani, The magnetic field investigation on
                   the Ulysses mission: Instrumentation and preliminary scientific results,
                   Astron. Astrophys. Suppl. Ser. 92, 221-236, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BALOGHETAL1992A</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>VECTOR HELIUM/FLUXGATE MAGNETOMETERS</name>
        <type>Magnetometer</type>
        <naif_instrument_id>not applicable</naif_instrument_id>

        <serial_number>not applicable</serial_number>

        <description>
 
 
  Instrument Overview
  ===================
    (excerpted from: [BALOGHETAL1992A])
 
    Abstract.  -- A fundamental feature of the heliosphere is the
    three dimensional structure of the interplanetary magnetic
    field.  The magnetic field investigation on Ulysses, the first
    space probe to explore the out-of-ecliptic and polar
    heliosphere, aims at determining the large scale features and
    gradients of the field, as well as the heliolatitude dependence
    of interplanetary phenomena so far only observed near the
    ecliptic plane.  The Ulysses magnetometer uses two sensors, one
    a Vector Helium Magnetometer, the other a Fluxgate
    Magnetometer.  Onboard data processing yields measurements of
    the magnetic field vector with a time resolution up to 2
    vectors/second and a sensitivity of about 10 pT.  Since the
    switch-on of the instrument in flight on 25 October 1990, a
    steady stream of observations have been made, indicating that
    at this phase of the solar cycle the field is generally
    disturbed: several shock waves and a large number of
    discontinuities have been observed, as well as several periods
    with apparently intense wave activity.  The paper gives a brief
    summary of the scientific objectives of the investigation,
    followed by a detailed description of the instrument and its
    characteristics.  Examples of wave bursts, interplanetary
    shocks and crossings of the heliospheric current sheet are
    given to illustrate the observations made with the instrument.
 

        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
