<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:uwo_meteor_radar.cmor.cmor_inst</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>Canadian Meteor Orbit Radar (CMOR)</title>
    <information_model_version>1.10.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2020-02-18</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Initial export from OLAF</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:uwo_meteor_radar.cmor</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_telescope</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <reference_text>Webster, A.R., P.G. Brown, J. Jones, K.J. Ellis, and M. Campbell-Brown, Canadian
Meteor Orbit Radar (CMOR), Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss. 4, 1181-1201, 2004.</reference_text>
    </External_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <reference_text>Jones, J., P. Brown, K.J. Ellis, A.R. Webster, M. Campbell-Brown, Z. Krzemenski, and
R.J. Weryk, The Canadian Meteor Orbit Radar: system overview and preliminary results,
Planetary and Space Science 53, 413-421, 2005.</reference_text>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>Canadian Meteor Orbit Radar (CMOR)</name>
    <type>Radio-Radar</type>
    <description>The Canadian Meteor Orbit Radar (CMOR) is located at the University of Western
Ontario (UWO) meteor radar complex near Tavistock, Ontario, and has been in operation
since late 2001.  It consists of three separate interferometric radars, synchronized
in transmission and reflection and operating from a single site.  Details of the
system may be found in Jones et al. (2005) and Webster et al.  (2004).

The three systems operate at 17.45, 29.85, and 38.15 MHz.  The "orbit" component of
the system applies only to the 29.85 MHz system which has two outlying remote
stations (6.2 and 8.1 km respectively from the main site) providing reflections from
portions of the meteor trail not directly accessible from the specular reflections to
the main site.  For these echoes, the interferometry from the main site provides
sufficient information to permit measurement of velocity vectors for individual
meteors.

Each of the three systems has seven antennae and seven separate receivers.  For the
17 and 38 MHz systems all seven receivers are used for reception (to boost signal to
noise levels) but only five are used for determination of the measured echo direction
using interferometry.  The 29 MHz system uses the two extra receivers to record
signals from the two outlying stations.

The transmit and receive antennae have broad (nearly all-sky) gain patterns.  The
transmit antenna is a vertically directed horizontally-polarized three-element Yagi
with G = 7.6 dB(i) (relative to an isotropic radiator) and a beam width to the 3 dB
points of 30 degrees.  The receive antennae are all two-element vertically directed
horizontally polarized Yagis with G = 6.5 dB(i) and beam widths of 45 degrees to the
3 dB points.  Directions to each echo are measured using the relative phase
difference between the antennae within each of the 5-element interferometer arrays. 
The interferometric error is less than 0.5 degrees for echoes with elevations above
30 degrees found for simulation for echoes with SNRs of 15 dB.  Due to the
degradation in interferometric accuracy at low elevations, no echoes are processed
with their nominal elevation is below 20 degrees.

All receivers are cosmic noise limited.  The variation in noise levels is controlled
principally by galactic cosmic noise at HF/VHF frequencies and produces a diurnal
noise variation of 2 dB for the 29 and 38 MHz systems.  The 17 MHz system suffers
from heavy terrestrial interference during the day, limiting useful echo detections
to night-time hours only.  For the 29 MHz orbital system, the absolute minimal
detectable signal strength corresponds to meteors with radio magnitudes near +9. 
However, effective counting statistics for 29.85 MHz are complete only to +8 due to
the roll-off in sensitivity as the absolute detection threshold is reached - this is
the effective detection limit for the radar and corresponds to meteoroids of ~10^-7
kg mass for an average velocity of 30 km/sec.

References:

Jones, J., P. Brown, K.J. Ellis, A.R. Webster, M. Campbell-Brown, Z. Krzemenski, and
R.J. Weryk, The Canadian Meteor Orbit Radar: system overview and preliminary results,
Planetary and Space Science 53, 413-421, 2005.

Webster, A.R., P.G. Brown, J. Jones, K.J. Ellis, and M. Campbell-Brown, Canadian
Meteor Orbit Radar (CMOR), Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss. 4, 1181-1201, 2004.</description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>

