<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model 
    href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1F00.sch" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model 
    href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.sch"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context
    xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1
            https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1F00.xsd
            http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1 
            https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.xsd">
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:vex.virtis</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Venus Express Visible and Infrared Thermal Imaging Spectrometer (VIRTIS)</title>
        <information_model_version>1.15.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>VIRTIS</alternate_id>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-11-17</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>First version</description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.vex</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Coradini, A., F. Capaccioni, P. Drossart, A. Semery, G. Arnold, U. Schade, F. Angrilli, M. A.
                Barucci, G. Bellucci, G. Bianchini, J. P. Bibring, A. Blanco, M. Blecka, D. Bockelee-Morvan,
                R. Bonsignori, M. Bouye, E. Bussoletti, M. T. Capria, R. Carlson, U. Carsenty, P. Cerroni,
                L. Colangeli, M. Combes, M. Combi, J. Crovisier, M. Dami, M. C. DeSanctis, A. M. DiLellis,
                E. Dotto, T. Encrenaz, E. Epifani, S. Erard, S. Espinasse, A. Fave, C. Federico, U. Fink, S. Fonti,
                V. Formisano, Y. Hello, H. Hirsch, G. Huntzinger, R. Knoll, D. Kouach, W. H. Ip, P. Irwin,
                J. Kachlicki, Y. Langevin, G. Magni, T. McCord, V. Mennella, H. Michaelis, G. Mondello,
                S. Mottola, G. Neukum, V. Orofino, R. Orosei, P. Palumbo, G. Peter, B. Pforte, G. Piccioni,
                J. M. Reess, E. Ress, B. Saggin, B. Schmitt, Stefanovitch, A. Stern, F. Taylor, D. Tiphene, and
                G. Tozzi. Virtis : an imaging spectrometer for the rosetta mission. Planetary and Space Science,
                46:1291-1304, October 1998.
            </reference_text>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <doi>10.1016/j.pss.2007.01.003</doi>
            <reference_text>
                P. Drossart, G. Piccioni, A. Adriani, F. Angrilli, G. Arnold, K. H. Baines, G. Bellucci, J. Benkhoff,
                B. Bezard, J.-P. Bibring, A. Blanco, M. I. Blecka, R. W. Carlson, A. Coradini, A. di Lellis,
                T. Encrenaz, S. Erard, S. Fonti, V. Formisano, T. Fouchet, R. Garcia, R. Haus, J. Helbert, N. I.
                Ignatiev, P. G. J. Irwin, Y. Langevin, S. Lebonnois, M. A. Lopez-Valverde, D. Luz, L. Marinangeli,
                V. Orofino, A. V. Rodin, M. C. Roos-Serote, B. Saggin, A. Sanchez-Lavega, D. M. Stam, F. W.
                Taylor, D. Titov, G. Visconti, M. Zambelli, R. Hueso, C. C. C. Tsang, C. F. Wilson, and T. Z.
                Afanasenko. Scientific goals for the observation of Venus by VIRTIS on ESA/Venus express
                mission. Planetary and Space Science, 55:1653-1672, October 2007. doi: 10.1016/j.pss.2007.01.003.
            </reference_text>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Piccioni, G., P. Drossart, E. Suetta, M. Cosi, E. Ammannito, A. Barbis, R. Berlin, A. Boccaccini,
                G. Bonello, M. Bouy, F. Capaccioni, G. Cherubini, M. Dami, O. Dupuis, A. Fave, G. Filacchione,
                Y. Hello, F. Henry, S. Hofer, G. Huntzinger, R. Melchiorri, J. Parisot, C. Pasqui, G. Peter,
                C. Pompei, J. M. Ress, A. Semery, A. Soufflot, A. Adriani, F. Angrilli, G. Arnold, K. Baines,
                G. Bellucci, J. Benkhoff, B. Bezard, J.-P. Bibring, A. Blanco, M. I. Blecka, R. Carlson, A. Coradini,
                A. Di Lellis, T. Encrenaz, S. Erard, S. Fonti, V. T. Formisano, V. Fouchet, R. Garcia,
                R. Haus, J. Helbert, N. I. Ignatiev, P. Irwin, Y. Langevin, S. Lebonnois, M. A. Lopez Valverde,
                D. Luz, L. Marinangeli, V. Orofino, A. V. Rodin, M. C. Roos-Serote, B. Saggin, A. Sanchez-
                Lavega, D. M. Stam, F. Taylor, D. Titov, Visconti G., and M. Zambelli. VIRTIS (Visible and
                Infrared Imaging Spectrometer) for Venus Express. ESA, special publication 1295 edition, 2007.                
            </reference_text>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Instrument>
        <name>Venus Express Visible and Infrared Thermal Imaging Spectrometer (VIRTIS)</name>
        <Type_List_Area>
            <ctli:Type_List>
                <ctli:type>Spectrometer</ctli:type>
            </ctli:Type_List>
        </Type_List_Area>
        <description>
            VIRTIS on Venus Express was a hyperspectral
            imager repurposed from the flight spare of the instrument of the same name of the Rosetta mission
            [Coradini et al., 1998]. It combines a scanning mirror with a refraction grating to disperse the
            light from a narrow slit across a detector array. VIRTIS data are organized as cubes with one 
            spectral dimension (bands) and two spatial dimensions, which are along the direction of the slit 
            (samples) and along the direction of the scanning mirror (line).        
        </description>
    </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
