<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch"         schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.sch"  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:pds ="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" 
    xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
    xmlns:xsi ="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation=
    "http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1    https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd
     http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1   https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1/PDS4_CTLI_1D00_1101.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:vg2.eng</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Voyager 2 Spacecraft Sensors</title>
        <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-05-13</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    The initial version of this context product, which describes the 
                    systems on the Voyager 2 spacecraft and (indirectly) the sensors
                    that report status and performance.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.vg2</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Kohlhase, C., The Voyager Neptune Travel Guide, JPL Publication 89-24, 276 pp.,
                Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, 1989.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                Summary of Voyager 2 plans at Neptune.  Although written for Voyager 2,
                the chapter about the spacecraft applies equally well to Voyager 1 since
                the two spacecraft were built to be identical.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Morrison, D., Voyages to Saturn, NASA SP-451, 227 pp., National Aeronautics and
                Space Administration, Washington, DC, 1982.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                Summary of Voyager 1 and 2 accomplishments at Saturn.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument>
        <name>Voyager 2 Engineering</name>
        <Type_List_Area>
            <ctli:Type_List>
                <ctli:type>Spacecraft Sensor</ctli:type>
                <ctli:subtype>The aggregation of all spacecraft sensors on the Voyager 2 spacecraft.</ctli:subtype>
            </ctli:Type_List>
        </Type_List_Area>
        <description>
            The aggregation of spacecraft sensors on the Voyager 2 spacecraft.
                                               
            The Voyager 2 spacecraft was built by the Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL).          
            Its mass was 815 kilograms, including its own power, propulsion, and                
            communications systems and its own science instruments.                   
            Spacecraft electrical power was supplied by Radioisotope                  
            Thermoelectric Generators (RTGs) that produced about 400 watts.           
            The Attitude and Articulation Control Subsystem (AACS),                   
            Computer Command Subsystem (CCS), and Flight Data Subsystem               
            (FDS) managed spacecraft operations.  Thrusters and gyroscopes                
            provided physical propulsion and attitude control.                        
            Communications between the spacecraft and Earth were carried              
            out via a high-gain radio antenna using both S-band and X-band            
            frequencies at data rates as high as 115.2 kilobits per second.           
            A Digital Tape Recorder (DTR) could save up to 500 million bits           
            when no Earth station was available for real-time data                    
            transmission.  Voyager control systems could record sets of               
            several thousand instructions, allowing autonomous operation              
            for days or weeks at a time.  Many of the systems were equipped
            with sensors, which fed engineering data to the ground where
            status and performance could be monitored.
            
            The spacecraft itself was built around its 'bus' -- a decagonal           
            prism, which was about 2 meters in diameter and about 60 cm               
            deep.  Each of the ten sides of the bus was associated with a             
            'bay' containing engineering systems or science instrument                
            electronics.  Bay 1, for example, contained the radio                     
            transmitter.  The High-Gain Antenna (HGA) was mounted to the              
            end of the bus facing Earth.  The bays were numbered 1 through            
            10 in a clockwise direction when viewed from Earth.  Extending            
            away from the bus were three booms: a science boom and scan               
            platform to which most instruments were mounted, a magnetometer           
            boom, and a boom to which the RTGs were mounted.                          
            
            Spacecraft Coordinate System                                              
            ----------------------------                                              
            The centerline of the bus was the roll axis of the                      
            spacecraft; it also served as the z-axis of the spacecraft              
            coordinate system with the high-gain antenna (HGA) boresight            
            defining the negative z-direction.  The HGA boresight was               
            also defined as cone angle 0 degrees and as azimuth 180                 
            degrees, elevation 7 degrees.  The science boom, supporting             
            the scan platform, extended in the general direction of                 
            positive y; this boom was also defined as being at cone angle           
            90 degrees, clock angle 215 degrees and at azimuth 180                  
            degrees, elevation 97 degrees.  The boom supporting the RTGs              
            was mounted on the bus in generally the negative y direction.           
            The positive y-axis (yaw axis) of the spacecraft coordinate             
            system passed through Bay 3; the negative y-axis passed                 
            through Bay 8.  The x-axis (pitch axis) was in a direction              
            which defined a right-handed rectangular coordinate system.             
            The positive x-axis was at cone angle 90 degrees, clock angle           
            305 degrees (azimuth 270 degrees, elevation 90 degrees).                
            
            Telecommunications Subsystem                                              
            ----------------------------                                              
            The high-gain antenna was mounted to the spacecraft bus,                
            pointing in the negative z-direction.  It was a parabolic               
            reflector 3.7 meters in diameter with a feed that permitted             
            simultaneous operation at both S-band (13 cm wavelength) and            
            X-band (3.6 cm).  The half-power full-width of the antenna              
            beam was 0.6 degrees at X-band and 2.3 degrees at S-band.               
            The Low-Gain Antenna (LGA) was mounted on the feed structure            
            of the HGA and radiated approximately uniformly over the                
            hemisphere into which the HGA pointed.                                  
            
            The Telecommunications Subsystem (TCS) electronics included a           
            redundant pair of transponders, meaning that a failed                   
            functional unit in one transponder could be bypassed by                 
            swapping to the redundant unit.  The TCS could transmit                 
            science data on the X-band link at rates between 4.8 and                
            115.2 kilobits per second and engineering data on the S-band            
            link at 40 bits per second.  It could receive instructions              
            sent (uplinked) from ground stations at a rate of 16 bits per           
            second.  Commands were extracted from the uplink signal by              
            the Command Detector Unit (CDU) and were then sent to the               
            Computer Command Subsystem (CCS).                                       
            
            Spacecraft receivers were designed to lock to the uplink                
            signal.  Without locking, Doppler effects -- resulting from             
            relative motion of the spacecraft and ground station -- could           
            result in loss of the radio link as the frequency of the                
            received signal drifted. Voyager 2 differed from Voyager 1
            in this locking mechanism, which failed after launch.  Although
            lock could be achieved, the uplink signal had to be within a
            window only 100 Hz wide around the Voyager 2 receiver's rest
            frequency.  Engineers discovered both the problem and the
            solution during cruise and were able to tune the uplink
            transmitted from the ground so that commands could be sent
            and data received for encounters with all four of the 
            Voyager 2 target planets.
            
            Attitude and Articulation Control Subsystem                               
            -------------------------------------------                               
            The Attitude and Articulation Control Subsystem (AACS)                  
            provided three-axis-stabilized control so that the spacecraft           
            could maintain a fixed orientation in space.  Attitude                  
            control was accomplished using gyroscopes or by celestial               
            reference.  The AACS also controlled motion of the scan                 
            platform, upon which the four 'remote sensing' instruments              
            were mounted.                                                           
            
            Gyro control was used in special situations (e.g., trajectory           
            corrections and solar conjunctions) for periods of up to                
            several days.  The inertial reference unit operated with                
            tuned rotor gyros having an uncalibrated drift rate of less             
            than 0.5 degrees per hour and a calibrated drift rate of less           
            than 0.05 degrees per hour.                                             
            
            Celestial control was based on viewing the Sun (through a               
            sensor mounted on the high-gain antenna) and a single bright            
            star (through a second sensor named the Canopus Star Tracker,           
            after the star used most frequently as the reference).  When            
            the spacecraft attitude drifted by more than a small amount             
            from the reference objects, the AACS fired small thrusters              
            which returned the spacecraft to the proper orientation.  The           
            Sun sensor was an optical potentiometer with a cadmium                  
            sulfide detector; its error was less than 0.01 degrees and              
            its limit cycle was +/-0.05 degrees.  The Canopus Star                  
            Tracker was an image dissector tube with a cesium detector,             
            an error of less than 0.01 degree, and a limit cycle of                 
            +/-0.05 degrees.                                                        
            
            Redundant (backup) sun sensors, star trackers, and computers            
            were also part of the AACS.  The non-redundant portions of              
            the AACS were those controlling the pointing of the                     
            instrument scan platform, which had two degrees of freedom --           
            elevation and azimuth (see below).
            
            Propulsion Subsystem                                                      
            --------------------                                                      
            The propulsion system was part of the AACS and consisted of             
            16 hydrazine thrusters.  These thrusters were also used to              
            control the three-axis stabilization of the spacecraft.  Two            
            thrusters on opposite sides of the spacecraft were used to              
            perform positive roll turns around the +Z axis.  Two                    
            oppositely pointed thrusters were used to perform negative              
            roll turns.  One thruster was used to perform positive yaw              
            turns (around the +Y axis) and one was used to perform                  
            negative yaw turns.  One thruster was used to perform                   
            positive pitch turns (around the +X axis) and one was used to           
            perform negative pitch turns.  A backup hydrazine system was            
            connected to a redundant set of eight thrusters.                        
            
            Power Subsystem                                                           
            ---------------                                                           
            Spacecraft power was provided by three Radioisotope                     
            Thermoelectric Generators (RTGs) mounted on a boom in the               
            negative y-direction.  At Launch the three RTGs converted               
            7000 watts of heat into 475 watts of electrical power.  RTG             
            electrical output decreased by about 7 watts per year because           
            of decay of the plutonium dioxide fissionable material and              
            degradation of the silicon-germanium thermocouples.  The                
            difference between available electrical power and the power             
            required to operate spacecraft subsystems was called the                
            'power margin.' Voyager Project guidelines required a power             
            margin of at least 12 watts to guard against electrical                 
            transients and miscalculations; excess electrical power was             
            dissipated as heat in a shunt radiator.                                 
            
            Data Storage Subsystem                                                    
            ----------------------                                                    
            The Digital Tape Recorder (DTR) was used to store data when             
            real-time communications with Earth were either not possible            
            or not scheduled.  The DTR recorded data on eight tracks;               
            rates were 115.2 kilobits per second (record only), 21.6                
            kilobits per second (playback only), and 7.2 kilobits per               
            second (record and playback).  Capacity of each track was 12            
            images or equivalent.                                                   
            
            Computer Command Subsystem                                                
            --------------------------                                                
            The Computer Command Subsystem (CCS) consisted of two                   
            identical computer processors, their software algorithms, and           
            associated electronic hardware.  The CCS was the central                
            controller of the spacecraft.  During most of the Voyager               
            mission the two CCS computers on each spacecraft were used              
            non-redundantly to increase the command and processing                  
            capability of the spacecraft.                                           
            
            Flight Data Subsystem                                                     
            ---------------------                                                     
            The Flight Data Subsystem (FDS) consisted of two                        
            reprogrammable digital computers and associated encoding                
            hardware.  The FDS collected and formatted science and                  
            engineering telemetry data for transmission to Earth.                   
            Convolutional coding was imposed on all data transmitted from           
            the spacecraft.  Additionally, both Golay encoding and Reed-            
            Solomon encoding were available for use on spacecraft data.             
            Data compression was also performed within the FDS.                     
            
            Science Boom                                                              
            ------------                                                              
            The Voyager science instrument boom carried the plasma                  
            detector, cosmic ray detector and the low energy charged                
            particle detector.  The scan platform was mounted on the                
            science boom.                                                           
            
            Scan Platform                                                             
            -------------                                                             
            Four instruments (Imaging, PhotoPolarimeter, Infra-Red                  
            Interferometric Spectrometer, and Ultra Violet Spectrometer)            
            were mounted on the scan platform, which could be slewed by             
            motors and gears (called actuators).  Elevation of the scan             
            platform was measured with respect to a plane slightly offset           
            (by approximately 7 degrees) from the spacecraft x-z plane;             
            the spacecraft positive y-axis was at 97 degrees elevation              
            (see Spacecraft Coordinate System above).  The scan platform            
            azimuth reference was defined by the y-z plane, with zero               
            azimuth being in the negative z-direction.  Drive actuators             
            were controlled by fine feedback potentiometers; the error of           
            each was less than 0.03 degrees, and the final pointing error           
            of the scan platform was nominally +/-0.1 degrees (2-sigma              
            per axis).  Subsequent analysis by the Navigation and                   
            Ancillary Information Facility (NAIF) at JPL showed larger           
            errors during at least the Jupiter and Saturn encounters.               
            High rate slews of 1 deg/sec were discontinued after the                
            azimuth drive mechanism on Voyager 2 temporarily froze a                
            short time after Saturn closest approach.  The medium slew              
            rate was 0.33 deg/sec, and the low slew rate was 0.08                   
            deg/sec.                                                                
            
            Magnetometer Boom                                                         
            -----------------                                                         
            Two low-field magnetometers were mounted on a 13-meter-long             
            boom that was unfurled and extended automatically after                 
            Launch.  One low-field magnetometer was mounted at the end of           
            the boom and a second was mounted about 3 meters from the               
            end.  Two high-field magnetometers were mounted at the base             
            of the boom.                                                            
            
        </description>
    </Instrument>
    
</Product_Context>
