<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:wise.wise_camera</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>WISE Camera</title>
    <information_model_version>1.10.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    <Modification_History>
      <Modification_Detail>
        <modification_date>2021-02-08</modification_date>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <description>Initial export from OLAF</description>
      </Modification_Detail>
    </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Reference_List>
    <Internal_Reference>
      <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.wise</lid_reference>
      <reference_type>instrument_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
    </Internal_Reference>
    <External_Reference>
      <reference_text>Wright, E.L., Eisenhardt, P.R.M., Mainzer, A.K., Ressler, M.E., Cutri, R.M., Jarrett,
T., Kirkpatrick, J.D., Padgett, F., McMillan, R.S., Skrutskie, M. 2010. The
Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE): Mission Description and Initital On-Orbit
Performance. Astron. J. 140, 1868-1881. doi: 10.1088/0004-6256/140/6/1868</reference_text>
    </External_Reference>
  </Reference_List>
  <Instrument>
    <name>WISE Camera</name>
    <type>Imager</type>
    <description>The Space Dynamics Laboratory in Logan, Utah, designed, fabricated and tested the
instrument. They also manufactured the electronics used to control the instrument and
perform onboard processing of the detector images.
The instrument includes a 40-centimeter-diameter (16-inch) telescope and four
infrared detectors containing one million pixels each, all kept cold inside an outer
cylindrical, vacuum-tight tank filled with frozen hydrogen, called a cryostat. Some
say the whole assembly looks like a giant Thermos bottle, while others see a
resemblance to the Star Wars robot R2-D2. After launch, the hydrogen vents on the
cryostat are opened and the instrument cover is ejected. Once these events have
occurred, a scan mirror in the telescope will be the only moving instrument part.
At the bottom of the instrument is a three-axis stabilized, eight-sided spacecraft
bus that houses the computers, electronics, battery and reaction wheels needed to
keep the observatory operating and oriented correctly in space. Two star trackers for
precision pointing are mounted on the sides of the spacecraft bus. A fixed solar
panel that provides all the spacecraft's power is mounted on one side of the bus, and
a fixed high gain antenna for transmitting science images to the ground is mounted on
the opposite side. The bus structure is composed of an aluminum skin backed by
aluminum honeycomb panels. It has no deployable parts -- the only moving parts are
four reaction wheels used to maneuver the satellite.
Telescope
The WISE telescope has a 40-centimeter-diameter (16-inch) aperture and is designed to
continuously image broad swaths of sky at four infrared wavelengths as the satellite
wheels around Earth. The four wavelength bands are 3.4, 4.6, 12 and 22 microns. The
field of view is 47-arcminutes wide, or about one-and-a-half times the diameter of
the moon.
The telescope was built by L-3 SSG-Tinsley in Wilmington, Mass. Its design uses a
total of 10 curved and two flat mirrors, all made of aluminum and coated in gold to
improve their ability to reflect infrared light. Four of the mirrors form an image
from the 40-centimeter primary mirror onto the flat scan mirror. The scan mirror
moves at a rate that exactly cancels the changing direction of the spacecraft on the
sky, allowing freeze frame images to be taken every 11 seconds. The scan mirror then
snaps back to catch up with the craft as it continues to survey the sky.
The remaining mirrors form a focused image of the sky onto the detector arrays.
Before reaching the arrays, the light passes through a series of flat "dichroic"
filters that reflect some wavelengths and transmit others, allowing WISE to
simultaneously take images of the same part of the sky at four different infrared
wavelengths.
The image quality, or resolution, of WISE is about six arcseconds in its 3.4, 4.6 and
12 micron bands, meaning that it can distinguish features one six-hundredth of a
degree apart. At 22 microns, the resolution is 12 arcseconds, or one three-hundredth
of a degree. This means WISE can distinguish features about five times smaller than
the Infrared Astronomical Satellite could at 12 and 25 microns, and many hundred
times smaller than NASA's Cosmic Background Explorer could at 3.5 and 4.9 microns.
Detectors
Light gathered by WISE's telescope is focused onto what is called a focal plane,
which consists of four detector arrays, one for each infrared wavelength observed by
WISE. Each of the detector arrays contain about one million pixels (1,032,256 to be
exact). This is a giant technology leap over past infrared survey missions. The
Infrared Astronomical Satellite's detectors contained only 62 pixels in total.
The 3.4- and 4.6-micron detectors convert light to electrons using an alloy made of
mercury, cadmium and tellurium. The electrons from each of the million-plus pixels
are measured on the spot every 1.1 seconds, and the result sent to the instrument
electronics. These detector arrays, a type known as the HAWAII 1RG, were manufactured
by Teledyne Imaging Systems, Camarillo, Calif. They need to be warmer than the rest
of the instrument to improve their performance. The 12- and 22-micron detectors sense
light using silicon mixed with a tiny amount of arsenic. They have readout
electronics specially developed for the low-temperatures of WISE and were
manufactured by DRS Sensors &amp; Targeting Systems, Cypress, Calif.
Cryostat
Because WISE is designed to detect infrared radiation from cool objects, the
telescope and detectors must be kept at even colder temperatures to avoid picking up
their own signal. The WISE telescope is chilled to 12 Kelvin (minus 261 degrees
Celsius or minus 438 degrees Fahrenheit) and the detectors for the 12- and 22-micron
detectors operate at less than 8 Kelvin (minus 265 degrees Celsius or minus 447
degrees Fahrenheit). The shorter wavelength 3.4- and 4.6-micron detectors operate at
a comparatively balmy 32 Kelvin (minus 241 degrees Celsius or minus 402 degrees
Fahrenheit). To maintain these temperatures, the telescope and detectors are housed
in a cryostat, essentially a giant Thermos bottle.
The WISE cryostat, manufactured by Lockheed Martin Advanced Technology Center, Palo
Alto, Calif., has two tanks filled with frozen hydrogen. The colder, or primary
cryogen tank, the smaller of the two tanks, cools the 12- and 22-micron detector
arrays. To achieve this low operating temperature, a larger 12-Kelvin secondary tank
protects the primary tank from nearly all the heat from the outer structure of the
cryostat, which is comparatively warm at about 190 Kelvin (minus 83 degrees Celsius
or minus 117 degrees Fahrenheit). This secondary tank also cools the telescope and
the 3.4- and 4.6-micron detectors. Small heaters are used to warm the 3.4- and
4.6-micron detectors from 12 to 32 Kelvin.
It is important to maintain a vacuum inside the cryostat when it is cold and on the
ground; otherwise air would freeze inside it. It would become a giant popsicle. A
deployable aperture cover seals the top of the cryostat while on the ground to
prevent air from getting in. After WISE is safely in orbit, a signal is sent to eject
the aperture cover. Three pyrotechnic separation nuts will fire, and the cover will
be pushed away from the spacecraft.
An aperture shade is mounted at the top of the telescope to shield the open cryostat
system from the sun and Earth's heat.</description>
  </Instrument>
</Product_Context>
