<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:pds ="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" 
    xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
    xmlns:xsi ="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation=
    "http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1  https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:canberra.dss46_26m</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>DSS-46 Radio Telescope</title>
        <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-07-19</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Original context file for the DSS-46 antenna near Canberra, Australia.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:radiosci.documentation:dsn.810-005</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This reference is to a PDS collection containing several versions of the NASA Deep 
                Space Network (DSN) Telecommunications Link Design Handbook (Document 810-005).
                The Handbook is maintained in a modular format to provide interface 
                design data to flight projects using the DSN.  Modules are updated as appropriate.
                Each member product in the PDS collection is the set of modules as they applied
                at that point in time.  Modules include:
                001 Handbook Introduction
                101 70-m Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces
                102 26-m Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces (omitted in 2009 and later versions)
                103 34-m HEF Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces
                104 34-m BWG Antennas Telecommunications Interfaces
                105 Atmospheric and Environmental Effects
                106 Solar Corona and Solar Wind Effects
                107 Radio Source Catalog
                201 Frequency and Channel Assignments
                202 34-m and 70-m Doppler
                203 Sequential Ranging
                205 Command Service
                206 Telemetry General Information
                207 34-m and 70-m Telemetry Reception
                208 Telemetry Data Decoding
                209 Open-Loop Radio Science
                210 Delta Differrential One-way Ranging
                211 Wideband Very Long Baseline Interferometry
                214 Pseudonoise and Regenerative Ranging
                301 Coverage and Geometry
                302 Antenna Positioning
                303 Media Calibration
                304 Frequency and Timing
                305 Test Support
                901 Handbook Glossary
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.dsn</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on the NASA Deep Space Network as a whole.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.canberra</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on the Canberra Deep Space Communication Complex.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:dsn.rss</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_instrument</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on the commanding, radio tracking, and
                radio science instrumentation at the telescope. 
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>

        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>https://www.cdscc.nasa.gov/Pages/welcome.html</reference_text>
            <description>
                An overview of the Canberra Deep Space Communications Complex with photographs.
                Pull down the Antennas menu and select "DSS 46" for this antenna.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Telescope>
        <aperture unit='m'>26</aperture>
        <telescope_longitude unit='deg'>148.983079</telescope_longitude>
        <telescope_latitude unit='deg'>-35.405015</telescope_latitude>
        <telescope_altitude unit="m">677.510</telescope_altitude>
        <coordinate_source>
            Geodetic coordinates derived using an ellipsoid with semi-major axis a = 6378136.3 m 
            and flattening f = 298.257 (see DSN document 810-005, Module 301 issued 2001-01-15, 
            Table 5 and associated text). These coordinates are valid for the years 1983-2009.
        </coordinate_source>
        <description>
            DSS-46 was used primarily for communication with Earth orbiting spacecraft and for
            initial acquisition of any spacecraft immediately after launch. It partnered with
            DSS-16 (at Goldstone, CA) and DSS-66 (near Madrid, Spain) in a 26-m subnet for
            this purpose.  DSS-46 could transmit 50-2000 W at 2.1 GHz (S-band).  It could receive
            right- and left-circularly polarized signals simultaneously at both 2.3 GHz and 8.4 GHz; 
            its receiver could combine the signals to obtain a rotatable linear polization. 
            
            The antenna was constructed in 1965 at the Honeysuckle Creek Tracking Station in
            Australia to support the Apollo missions. On 21 July 1969 (Australian time) the 
            antenna received and relayed to the world the first television images of Neil 
            Armstrong's historic first steps on the Moon. The Honeysuckle Creek station was 
            converted for use in NASA's Deep Space Network after the end of the Apollo and 
            Skylab programs, with the antenna given the new designation DSS-44. The antenna 
            supported many missions, including those to Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn and the Sun,
            until the closure of the Honeysuckle Creek Tracking Station in December 1981.  In 
            1983 the antenna was moved to its current location at Tidbinbilla, re-designated 
            DSS-46 and modified to expand its capabilities for early launch acquisition (tracking
            a spacecraft after it has launched from Earth).  The antenna continued to support 
            NASA and international missions studying the Sun, Earth, Moon and the planets in 
            our solar system until its retirement from deep space service in December 2009.
            
            The Canberra Deep Space Communications Complex (CDSCC) is managed by the Commonwealth 
            Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO), Australia's national science 
            research agency. The CDSCC is at Tidbinbilla, about 35 km southwest of Canberra, ACT.
        </description>
    </Telescope>
    
</Product_Context>
