<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:pds ="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" 
    xmlns:ctli="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/ctli/v1"
    xmlns:xsi ="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation=
    "http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1  https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:canberra.dss42_34m</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>DSS 42 34-m Radio Telescope</title>
        <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-07-19</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Original context file for the 34-m DSS 42 antenna near Canberra, Australia.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:radiosci.documentation:dsn.810-005</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_to_document</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This reference is to a PDS collection containing several versions of the NASA Deep 
                Space Network (DSN) Telecommunications Link Design Handbook (Document 810-005).
                The Handbook is maintained in a modular format to provide interface 
                design data to flight projects using the DSN.  Modules are updated as appropriate.
                Each member product in the PDS collection is the set of modules as they applied
                at that point in time.  Modules include:
                001 Handbook Introduction
                101 70-m Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces
                102 26-m Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces (omitted in 2009 and later versions)
                103 34-m HEF Subnet Telecommunications Interfaces
                104 34-m BWG Antennas Telecommunications Interfaces
                105 Atmospheric and Environmental Effects
                106 Solar Corona and Solar Wind Effects
                107 Radio Source Catalog
                201 Frequency and Channel Assignments
                202 34-m and 70-m Doppler
                203 Sequential Ranging
                205 Command Service
                206 Telemetry General Information
                207 34-m and 70-m Telemetry Reception
                208 Telemetry Data Decoding
                209 Open-Loop Radio Science
                210 Delta Differrential One-way Ranging
                211 Wideband Very Long Baseline Interferometry
                214 Pseudonoise and Regenerative Ranging
                301 Coverage and Geometry
                302 Antenna Positioning
                303 Media Calibration
                304 Frequency and Timing
                305 Test Support
                901 Handbook Glossary
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.dsn</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on the NASA Deep Space Network as a whole.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.canberra</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on the Canberra Deep Space Communications Compolex.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:canberra.dss42_26m</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>context_to_associate</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on DSS-42
                when its aperture was 26 meters (1964 to early 1980s).
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:dsn.rss</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_instrument</reference_type>
            <comment>
                This context product provides more information on the commanding, radio tracking, and
                radio science instrumentation at the telescope.  Only information appropriate to years
                2000 and earlier would be applicable to DSS 42 operations.
            </comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                DSN/Flight Project Interface Design
                GEO-10, DSN Coverage and Geometry
                Rev. E (Initial Issue, 1997-07-15)
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                This document provides DSN station coordinates which are required for spacecraft 
                navigation and location of stations with respect to other points on the Earth's 
                surface.  This document is a precursor to Module 301 in DSN document 810-005, the
                DSN Telecommunication Link Design Handbook, which was issued in its current form
                (as Rev. E) on 2001-01-15.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>https://www.cdscc.nasa.gov/Pages/welcome.html</reference_text>
            <description>
                An overview of the Canberra Deep Space Communications Complex with photographs.
                Pull down the Antennas menu and select "DSS 42" for this antenna.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
    </Reference_List>
 
    <Telescope>
        <aperture unit='m'>34</aperture>
        <telescope_longitude unit='deg'>148.981265</telescope_longitude>
        <telescope_latitude unit='deg'>-35.400679</telescope_latitude>
        <telescope_altitude unit="m">675.356</telescope_altitude>
        <coordinate_source>
            Geodetic coordinates derived using an ellipsoid with semi-major axis a = 6378136.3 m 
            and flattening f = 298.257 (see Table 5, DSN/Flight Project Interface Design, GEO-10,
            DSN Coverage and Geometry, Rev. E dated 1997-07-15)
        </coordinate_source>
        <description>
            Deep Space Station 42 (DSS-42) was the first antenna built at the Tidbinbilla tracking 
            station site near Canberra, Australia.  It entered service in mid 1964 and was designed
            to last 15 years.  Its first deep space mission support was for NASA's Mariner 4 
            spacecraft on its historic first flyby of Mars. Along with other dishes in the Deep 
            Space Network (DSN), it returned the first close up images of the surface of Mars.
            
            DSS-42 was originally constructed as a 26-m diameter antenna. To extend its life and 
            increase its capabilities, the dish was extended to 34-m in the early 1980s.  DSS-42 
            provided two-way radio communications with many dozens of robotic deep space spacecraft 
            until its retirement from service in early 2000, well past its original expected design
            life.
            
            Due to some structural weakness and metal fatigue, the antenna was dismantled. The quadrupod
            and subreflector structure from inside the dish was retained and moved to a location behind
            the Tidbinbilla Visitor Center where it stands today, along with one of its dish panels.
            
            The Canberra Deep Space Communications Complex (CDSCC) is managed by the Commonwealth 
            Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO), Australia's national science 
            research agency. The CDSCC is at Tidbinbilla, about 35 km southwest of Canberra, ACT.
        </description>
    </Telescope>
    
</Product_Context>
