<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:eso-paranal.vlt_yepun_8m2_ut4</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Very Large Telescope (VLT) Unit Telescope 4 (UT4) Yepun, 8.2-m Telescope</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>   
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-10-09</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Created from information from ESO Website: https://www.eso.org/public/teles-instr/paranal-observatory/
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.eso-paranal</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Telescope>
        <aperture unit="m">8.2</aperture>
        <telescope_longitude unit="deg">109.59604</telescope_longitude>
        <telescope_latitude unit="deg">-24.62704</telescope_latitude>
        <telescope_altitude unit="m">2635.43</telescope_altitude>
        <description> Unit Telescope 4 (Yepun) of the Very Large Telescope (VLT) at ESO's Paranal Observatory, Chile.
            The telescope is one of four 8.2-m Ritchey-Chretien Cassegrain telescopes with a 22-tonne Zerdour primary 
            mirror of 14.4 m focal length, and a 1.1-m lightweight beryllium secondary mirror.
            
            The unit telescope has alt-azimuth mount. In such a mount the telescope tube moves around a horizontal axis 
            called elevation axis. The two bearings which support the tube are mounted on a fork rotating around a vertical 
            axis, called azimuth axis, thus allowing for pointing over the entire sky. The telescope tube itself consists 
            of a steel structure supporting at the bottom the primary mirror (M1) in its cell, and at the top the M2 Unit 
            by means of metallic beams called "spiders".
            
            The Very Large Telescope uses active optics.The optical quality of the image is continually monitored by an image 
            analyser using a reference star and the contributions of the various optical aberrations (defocus, astigmatism, 
            coma, etc.) are computed. To achieve the best optical quality, discrete correction commands are given to the primary 
            mirror support system, controlling the shape of the thin flexible M1,and to the M2 Unit, which controls the position 
            of the M2 mirror along 5 degrees of freedom, namely one for focusing,two for centering, and two for pointing. 
            The M2 mirror itself is configured as a rigid lightweight convex hyperboloid.
        
        Information from the ESO telescope website: http://www.eso.org/sci/facilities/paranal/telescopes/ut.html
        </description>
    </Telescope>
</Product_Context>
