<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:irtf.3m0</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>InfraRed Telescope Facility 3.0-Meter Telescope</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>   
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-09-21</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Created from information from IRTF website:    http://irtfweb.ifa.hawaii.edu
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.irtf</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:irtf.3m0.mirsi</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:irtf.3m0.mirac</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:irtf.3m0.mirac2</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:irtf.3m0.mirlin</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Telescope>
        <aperture unit="m">3</aperture>
        <telescope_longitude unit="deg">155.4719</telescope_longitude>
        <telescope_latitude unit="deg">19.8262</telescope_latitude>
        <telescope_altitude unit="m">4168.07</telescope_altitude>
        <description>A 3.0-meter (9.8 ft) telescope optimized for use in infrared astronomy and located on Mauna Kea in Hawaii. 
            It was first built to support the Voyager missions and is now the US national facility for infrared astronomy, providing 
            continued support to planetary, solar neighborhood, and deep space applications. The IRTF is operated by the University 
            of Hawaii under a cooperative agreement with NASA. According to the IRTF's time allocation rules, at least 50% of the 
            observing time is devoted to planetary science.
            
            The IRTF is a 3.0 m (118" effective aperture) classical Cassegrain telescope. The Cassegrain focus f/ratio is f/38 and the
            primary mirror f/ratio is 2.5. Several aspects of the design of IRTF are optimized for IR observations. The secondary mirror 
            is undersized to prevent the instrument from seeing the thermal emission from the telescope structure around the primary mirror. 
            The primary mirror itself is 126" in diameter, but only the center 118" is used. A small mirror in the center of the secondary 
            mirror prevents the instrument from seeing its own thermal emission. The f/ratio is long to have a small secondary mirror, 
            again to minimize the telescope's thermal emission. The mirror coatings are chosen to have minimal thermal emission. The emissivity 
            of the telescope is usually below 4%. The secondary mirror is mounted on a chopping mechanism to rapidly switch the pointing of 
            the telescope from target to sky at up to 4 Hz.
            
            The IRTF is mounted on a large English yoke equatorial mount. The mount is very stiff, reducing flexure and allowing for accurate 
            pointing of the telescope. Since the telescope is on an equatorial mount, the telescope can observe targets through the zenith without 
            concern for field rotation. The yoke mount prevents the telescope from pointing north of +69 degrees declination. Since the telescope
            was primarily intended for planetary science, this restriction was considered to be acceptable. Since the telescope is on a heavy 
            mounting, it is relatively immune from vibration or wind shake.
        
        Telescope Limits Declination	The Hour Angle Limits
                +69:56:00
                -59:00:00	                  +/- 5:04:47
        
        </description>
    </Telescope>
</Product_Context>
