<?xml-model href="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 http://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/schema/released/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:keck.10m_keck1</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>0.0</version_id>
        <title>10-m Keck I Ritchey-Chretien altazimuth reflector</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-03-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>Initial version exported from OLAF</description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.keck</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>telescope_to_facility</reference_type>
            <comment>W.M. Keck Observatory (OLAF observatory code 378)</comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Telescope>
        <aperture unit='m'>10</aperture>
        <telescope_longitude unit='deg'>204.525284</telescope_longitude>
        <telescope_latitude unit='deg'>19.825945</telescope_latitude>
        <telescope_altitude unit='m'>4160</telescope_altitude>
        <coordinate_source>Aerial Survey - North American (1983) Datum</coordinate_source>
        <description>
        The 10-m Keck I Ritchey-Chretien altazimuth reflector is a 10 m telescope located at 19.825945, 204.525284 at the W.M. Keck Observatory.
        
        Instrument Host Overview
========================
  The Keck I telescope began science operations in May, 1993.  It
  was built through the W. M. Keck Foundation and is operated by the
  California Association for Research in Astronomy which includes
  the University of California, the California Institute of
  Technology and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.
  The Keck I is located at the W. M. Keck Observatory near the
  summit of Mauna Kea, Hawaii. The geodetic coordinates of the
  telescope are:

    Longitude    : 155d 28.4' W
    Latitude     : +19d 49.6' N
    Altitude:    : 4124m
    Mean seeing  : about 0.5 arcseconds full-width-half-max in the
                   K-band

  The overview and location given here are reproduced from the
  W. M. Keck Observatory web site, http://www2.keck.hawaii.edu/.


Telescope Properties
--------------------
  The primary mirror comprises 36 hexagonal segments.  Each segment
  is 1.8 meters, measured across the corners.  The maximum diameter
  of the primary mirror is 10.5 meters, and its focal length is 17.5
  meters.

  The telescope has 2 secondary mirrors.  The f/15 secondary mirror
  forms a Richey Chretien system with the primary mirror.  It can be
  used directly with an instrument mounted at the rear of the
  support structure for the primary mirror or with a flat tertiary
  mirror for a bent Cassegrain or Nasmyth focus.

  The f/25 secondary mirror is used with the infrared instruments at
  Keck I. The gold-plated mirror has a central hole to reduce the
  reflection of radiation to the detector from beyond the edge of
  the primary mirror or from the central obstruction for chop angles
  up to +/-150 arcseconds. A chopping mechanism resides behind this
  secondary mirror and does not obstruct the detector.  As the
  chopping mechanism tilts, the image moves on the detector.  This
  provides a way to rapidly center a target on the detector, then
  chop to a nearby part of sky without moving the telescope. The
  Keck Observatory website provides a tutorial for the chopping
  mechanism,
  http://www2.keck.hawaii.edu/inst/tools/chp/Chopping.html.

  The optical features of the f/15 and f/25 secondary mirror are:

                                 f/15   f/25
                                 -----  ------
    Focal length (m)           : 149.6  249.7
    Scale (mm/arcsec)          : 0.725  1.211
    Field diameter (arcmin)    : 20     10
    Field diameter (mm)        : 870    727
    Radius of curvature* (m)   : 2.14   0.82

  The telescope properties given here are reproduced from the Keck
  Telescope and Facility Instrument Guide, available at
  http://www2.keck.hawaii.edu/observing/kecktelgde/ktelinstupdate.pdf.
        </description>
    </Telescope>
</Product_Context>
