<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1G00.xsd">

    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:laboratory.odu-ftir</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Old Dominion University Fourier Transform Infrared Spectrometer Laboratory</title>
        <information_model_version>1.16.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-08-26</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                 Initial creation of the context product.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:multi-host.brukifs125hr_ftspec</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>facility_to_instrument</reference_type>
            <comment>This instrument at this lab is a Bruker IFS 120HR Fourier Transform Spectrometer that has been internally upgraded to the equivalent of a Bruker IFS 125HR model.</comment>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Facility>
        <name>Old Dominion University Fourier Transform Spectrometer Laboratory</name>
        <type>Laboratory</type>
        <description>
            Old Dominion University Fourier Transform Spectrometer Laboratory, under the direction of Dr. Peter Bernath, focuses on molecular spectroscopy and atmospheric remote sensing applications.
            The laboratory uses a Bruker FTS 120/125HR Fourier transform spectrometer to assess pure and gas-broadened samples of hydrocarbon compounds useful in comparing to atmospheric chemistry
            of Jupiter, Saturn, Saturn's moon Titan, and exoplanets. The spectrometer currently used is Bruker IFS 120HR hardware (“bench”) with Bruker IFS 125HR  electronics (i.e., our 120 was 
            upgraded to a 125). The maximum optical path difference of the Fourier transform spectrometer is 4.2 m. We used a 20 cm long cold cell (25 C to about -50 C) with KBr windows in the sample 
            compartment. The cell was cooled with a recirculating chiller that used ethanol. For these measurements in the 3 micron region a CaF2 beamsplitter and liquid N2 cooled InSb detector were used.
            
            The laboratory is located on the campus of Old Dominion University, Department of Chemistry and Biochemsitry, Chemistry Building, 4501 Elkhorn Ave., Norfolk, Virginia, 23529, USA. 
        </description>
    </Facility>
</Product_Context>
