<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">

    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:laboratory.asf</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Australian Synchrotron Facility</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-08-27</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
			Initial creation of the context product, plus
			snuck in lidref change to brukifs125hr
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:asf.thz_farir_beamline</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>facility_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:multi-host.brukifs125hr_ftspec</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>facility_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Facility>
        <name>Australian Synchrotron</name>
        <type>Laboratory</type>
        <description>
          Australian Synchrotron facility is a 3 GeV national synchrotron facility located in Clayton (southeastern suburbs) in Melbourne,
          Victoria, Australia. The Australian Synchrotron is a light source facility (in contrast to a collider), which uses particle 
          accelerators to produce a beam of high energy electrons that are boosted to nearly the speed of light and directed into a storage 
          ring where they circulate for many hours. As the path of these electrons are deflected in the storage ring by either bending magnets 
          or insertion devices, they emit synchrotron light. The light is channelled to experimental endstations containing specialised 
          equipment, enabling a range of research applications including high resolution imagery that is not possible under normal laboratory 
          conditions.
          
          The Australian Synchrotron supports the research needs of Australia’s major universities and research centres, and businesses ranging 
          from small-to-medium enterprises to multinational companies. During 2014-15 the Australian Synchrotron supported more than 4,300 
          researcher visits and close to 1,000 experiments in areas such as medicine, agriculture, environment, defence, transport, advanced 
          manufacturing and mining.
          
          The electrons used to provide the synchrotron light are first produced at the electron gun, by thermionic emission from a heated metal
          cathode. The emitted electrons are then accelerated to an energy of 90 keV (kilo-electron volts) by a 90 kilovolt potential applied 
          across the gun and make their way into the linear accelerator. The linear accelerator (or linac) uses a series of RF cavities, operating 
          at a frequency of 3 GHz, to accelerate the electron beam to an energy of 100 MeV, over a distance of around 15 metres. Due to the nature 
          of this acceleration, the beam must be separated into discrete packets, or 'bunches'. The bunching process is done at the start of the 
          linac, using several 'bunching' cavities. The linac can accelerate a beam once every second. Further along the linac quadrupole magnets 
          are used to help focus the electron beam. The booster is an electron synchrotron which takes the 100 MeV beam from the linac and 
          increases its energy to 3 GeV. The booster ring is 130 metres in circumference and contains a single 5-cell RF cavity (operating at 500 
          MHz) which provides energy to the electron beam. Acceleration of the beam is achieved by a simultaneous ramping up of the magnet strength 
          and cavity fields. Each ramping cycle takes approximately 1 second (for a complete ramp up and down). The storage ring is the final 
          destination for the accelerated electrons. It is 216 metres in circumference and consists of 14 nearly identical sectors. Each sector 
          consists of a straight section and an arc, with the arcs containing two dipole 'bending' magnets each. Each dipole magnet is a potential 
          source of synchrotron light and most straight sections can also host an insertion device, giving the possibility of 30+ beamlines at the 
          Australian Synchrotron. Two of the straight sections are used to host the storage ring 500 MHz RF cavities, which are essential for 
          replacing the energy that the beam loses through synchrotron radiation. The storage ring also contains a large number of quadrupole 
          and sextupole magnets used for beam focusing and chromaticity corrections. The ring is designed to hold 200 mA of stored current with a 
          beam lifetime of over 20 hours. The electron beam is kept within a very high vacuum at all times during the acceleration process and 
          within the storage ring. This vacuum is necessary as any beam collisions with gas molecules will quickly degrade the beam quality and 
          reduce the lifetime of the beam. The vacuum is achieved by enclosing the beam in a stainless steel pipe system, with numerous vacuum 
          pump systems continually working to keep the vacuum quality high. Pressure within the storage ring is typically around 10−13 bar (10 nPa).
          
          Each digital and analogue I/O channel is associated with a database entry in a customised distributed open source database system called 
          EPICS (Experimental Physics and Industrial Control System). The condition of the system is monitored and controlled by connecting 
          specialised GUIs to the specified database entries. There are about 115,000 database entries (also known as process variables), most of 
          which relate to the physical I/O. About 35,000 of these are permanently archived at intervals ranging from milliseconds to minutes. Some 
          high level control of the physics-related parameters of the beam is provided through MATLAB which also provides data analysis tools and an 
          interface with a computerised model of the accelerator. Personnel and equipment protection is achieved through the use of PLC-based systems, 
          which also transfer data to EPICS. The Beamlines also use EPICS as the basis for their control.
          
          Facility Website -- http://www.synchrotron.org.au
        </description>
    </Facility>
</Product_Context>
