<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">

    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:laboratory.cls</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Canadian Light Source Facility</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>Centre canadien de rayonnement synchrotron (CCRS)</alternate_id>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-06-15</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                 Initial creation of the context product, plus
		snuck in lidref change to brukifs125hr
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:cls.farir_beamline</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>facility_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:multi-host.brukifs125hr_ftspec</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>facility_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Facility>
        <name>Canadian Light Source</name>
        <type>Laboratory</type>
        <description>
          Canada's national synchrotron light source facility located at the University of Saskatoon in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan.
          The CLS has a third-generation 2.9 GeV storage ring, and the building occupies a footprint the size of a football field.
          It opened in 2004 after a 30-year campaign by the Canadian scientific community to establish a synchrotron radiation 
          facility in Canada. It has expanded both its complement of beamlines and its building in two phases since opening, and its 
          official visitors have included Queen Elizabeth II and Prince Philip. As a national synchrotron facility with over 1000 individual
          users, it hosts scientists from all regions of Canada and around 20 other countries. Research at the CLS has ranged from viruses
          to superconductors to dinosaurs, and it has also been noted for its industrial science and its high school education programs.
          
          The injection system consists of a 250 MeV LINAC, a low energy transfer line, a 2.9 GeV booster synchrotron and a high energy transfer
          line. The LINAC was operated for over 30 years as part of the Saskatchewan Accelerator Lab and operates at 2856 MHz. The 78m low 
          energy transfer line takes the electrons from the below-ground LINAC to the ground level booster in the newer CLS building, via two 
          vertical chicanes. The full energy 2.9 GeV booster, chosen to give high orbit stability in the storage ring, operates at 1 Hz, with an 
          RF frequency of 500 MHz, unsynchronised with the LINAC. This results in significant beam loss at the extraction energy.
          
          The storage ring cell structure has a fairly compact lattice with twelve straight sections available for injection, RF cavities and 9 
          sections available for insertion devices. Each cell has two bending magnets detuned to allow some dispersion in the straights – the 
          so-called double-bend achromat structure – and thus reduce the overall beam size. As well as the two bend magnets each cell has three 
          families of quadrupole magnets and two families of sextupole magnets. The ring circumference is 171m, with a straight section length 
          of 5.2m. The CLS is the smallest of the newer synchrotron facilities, which results in a relatively high horizontal beam emittance of 
          18.2 nm-rad. The CLS was also one of the first facilities to chicane two undulators in one straight section, to maximize the number 
          of insertion device beamlines.
          
          All five of the phase I X-ray beamlines use insertion devices. Four use permanent magnet undulators designed and assembled at the CLS, 
          including one in-vacuum undulator and one elliptically polarized undulator (EPU). The HXMA beamline uses a superconducting wiggler 
          built by the Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics in Novosibirsk. Phase II added two further devices including another Budker superconducting 
          wiggler, for the BMIT beamline. Phase III will add four more devices, filling 8 of the 9 available straight sections. Longer term development 
          includes the replacement of two of the phase I undulators with elliptically polarizing devices.
          
          Facility Website -- http://www.lightsource.ca
        </description>
    </Facility>
</Product_Context>
