<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:facility:observatory.naoj-hawaii</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>National Astronomical Observatory of Japan at Mauna Kea, Hawai'i</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_title>Subaru Telescope</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-10-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Created from information from NAOJ website:     https://www.nao.ac.jp/en/
                    and the telescope website:                      https://subarutelescope.org
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:telescope:naoj-hawaii.subaru_8m2</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>facility_to_telescope</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>Iye et al., (2004) Current Performance and On-Going Improvements of the 8.2 m
            Subaru Telescope, Publ. Astron. Soc. Japan, 56, 381-397.</reference_text>
            <description>Published document providing an overview of the Subaru telescope and facility.</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Facility>
        <name>National Astronomical Observatory of Japan at Mauna Kea, Hawai'i</name>
        <type>Observatory</type>
        <address>Summit of Mauna Kea, C/O 640 N. A'ohoku Place, #209, Hilo, HI 96720</address>
        <country>United States</country>
        <description>
            Located on the summit of Mauna Kea in Hawai'i, access is managed by Mauna Kea Observatories, through
            the University of Hawai'i's Hilo Base Facility. The observatory is located at 19°49'33" N, 155°28'35" W.
            
            Excerpt from (Iye et al., 2004):
            Following the recommendations of the Science Council of Japan, the project was fully approved and construction 
            of JNLT began in 1991 April (Kogure, Kodaira 1991). A call for proposals for renaming JNLT ended up with its 
            new name, Subaru Telescope, after the old and familiar Japanese name for the visible star cluster Pleiades 
            (Kodaira 1992). Progress of the project and the instrumentation plan was critically reviewed at another international 
            conference held in Tokyo in 1994 (Iye, Nishimura 1995). The Subaru Telescope base facility was established at the 
            University of Hawaii campus in Hilo, Hawaii, in 1997 April, and more than 20 NAOJ staff relocated from the Mitaka 
            campus to begin work on the telescope in collaboration with local staff recruited through the Research Corporation 
            of the University of Hawaii. The progress of construction was reported on several occasions (Iye 1997; Kaifu 1998), 
            and the engineering First Light of the Subaru Telescope was achieved on 1998 December 24. Reports on First Light 
            observations were published in 2000 (Kaifu et al. 2000; Iye et al. 2000). An inauguration ceremony was held in 
            1999 September. The 9- year construction project was completed in 2000 March, and the telescope has been made 
            available to both Japanese and the international community of astronomers since 2000 December.
        </description>
    </Facility>
</Product_Context>
