<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.hay</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>HAYABUSA</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.hayabusa</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:amica.hay</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:lidar.hay</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nirs.hay</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--noSpice        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--noSpice            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:spice.hay</lid_reference> -->
<!--noSpice            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type> -->
<!--noSpice        <Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:asteroid.25143_itokawa</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:asteroid.asteroid</lid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibrator.cal_lamps</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibrator.calibration</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibrator.ff_lamp</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibrator.flat_field</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibration_field.sky</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.earth</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mars</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.saturn</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.earth.moon</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.31_leo</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.alpha-beta_crv</lid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.alf_aur</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.alf_ori</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.alf_sco</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.alf_vir</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.bet_tau</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.calibration_field</lid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:star.tau_sco</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Fujiwara, A., J. Kawaguchi, D.K. Yeomans, M. Abe, T. Mukai, and 17 others, The
                   rubble-pile asteroid Itokawa as observed by Hayabusa, Science 312, 1330-1334,
                   2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.FUJIWARAETAL2006</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument_Host>
        <name>HAYABUSA</name>
        <type>Spacecraft</type>
        <naif_host_id>HAY</naif_host_id>

        <description>
 
 
      Instrument Host Overview
      ========================
 
  The HAYABUSA spacecraft is box-shaped with approximate dimensions of
  1.5 x 1.2 x 1.2 meters.  Two solar panels with a combined area of 12
  square meters provide power for the spacecraft including the four ion
  engines.  The spacecraft launch mass was 530 kg including 60 kg of xenon
  fuel and 70 kg of hydrazine fuel for the attitude control jets.  Each of
  the four ion engines uses microwave ionization of the xenon fuel and
  electrostatic acceleration of the ionized fuel to generate 5.2 - 23.6 mN
  of thrust (Isp = 3200 s).  Up to 3 of the 4 ion engines operate at one
  time.  The sample return capsule is 40 cm in diameter, has a height of 20
  cm and has a mass of 16.5 kg.  The surface hopper (MINERVA) is nearly
  cylindrical (10 x 12 cm) and by itself has a mass of 591 g. The
  spacecraft was designed to be three axis stabilized with 3 momentum
  wheels operating in orthogonal directions.
 
  Upon its return to Earth in June 2010, the return capsule separated
  from the mother spacecraft with a velocity of 17 cm/sec.  Its spin rate
  was about 0.2 Hz.  At 20 G, a timer was armed to jettison the parachute
  cover at an altitude of about 10 km.  The capsule recovery was near
  Woomera, Australia, the landing velocity was about 6 m/s and the
  Landing footprint was estimated to be 169 x 16 km (4 sigma).  To assist
  recovery, the sample capsule had a 242 MHz beacon radio signal.  An
  introduction to the spacecraft description and mission results can be
  found in [FUJIWARAETAL2006].
 
  Fujiwara, A., J. Kawaguchi, D.K. Yeomans, M. Abe, T. Mukai, and 17
  others, The rubble-pile asteroid Itokawa as observed by Hayabusa,
  Science 312, 1330-1334, 2006.
 
 
      System Description
      ==================
 
  The spacecraft coordinate system has the high gain antenna (HGA)
  pointing in the +Z direction with the AMICA camera, NIRS, LIDAR, XRS,
  along with the low gain X and S band antenna pointing in the -Z
  direction.  The ion engines point in the +X direction with the star
  tracker pointing in the -X direction.  The solar panel nearest the star
  tracker is in the +Y direction (Y = X x Z) with the second solar panel
  pointing in the -Y direction.  Bi-propellant attitude control thrusters
  are located on each corner of the spacecraft.  The power output of the
  solar panels is 2.6 kw at 1 AU.
 
  Along with the solar panels and HGA, the science instruments are hard
  mounted to the spacecraft.  The LIDAR, XRS, AMICA and sample horn are
  attached to the outside of the -Z deck with the NIRS mounted on the -X
  deck but pointing in the -Z direction.  MINERVA is located on the -Z axis
  near the sampling horn.  The AMICA, NIRS,and LIDAR have co-aligned
  fields-of-view.  The interior of the spacecraft contains the propulsion
  module.
 
  The ionized plasma is accelerated by high-voltage electrodes through
  four thruster heads which protrude from one side of the spacecraft body
  to provide ion thrusting of the spacecraft.  A nitrogen
  tetroxide/hydrazine propulsion system with a peak thrust of 22 N was used
  for maneuvering until late December 2005 when this fuel was exhausted.
  The spacecraft is powered by gallium-arsenide solar cells and a 15 A-hr
  rechargeable nickel-metal hydride (Ni-MH) battery. The battery suffered
  degredation during the close proximity spacecraft activities in late
  2005.
 
  Because of the sun, Earth and asteroid geometry at encounter and the
  spacecraft design, most often the spacecraft hovered above the asteroid
  along the Sun-asteroid line so that radio communications with Earth
  could be maintained at the same time the solar panels were directed
  toward the sun.  Three optical cameras were carried on board the
  spacecraft.  In addition to the AMICA science camera, two wide angle
  cameras were used for optical navigation.  They were equipped with
  500 x 500 CCDs with a resolution of 216 arcsec/px, 13 mm focal lengths
  and with a f ratio of 9.6.  The spacecraft was also equipped with a star
  tracker (266 x 384 CCD, focal length = 12 mm, f/1.4, resolution = 375
  arc seconds).  Of the four laser range finders (LRF) on board, three were
  used to measure the distance to the asteroid&apos;s surface when the the
  spacecraft was close (120 to 7 meters) while the fourth LRF was to be
  used to detect the deflection of the sampling horn when it touched the
  surface; this would then trigger the pellet firing to generate surface
  sample ejecta to capture.
 
  The coordinates and some of the larger elements of the spacecraft are
  shown in the schematic figure below.
 
                                     +Z
 
                                     /\  HGA
                            -------------------
                             \                /
                              \              /
                         --------------------------
                         |                        |
                         |                        |_
                         |                        |_]  ion engines
                         |                        |_]   +X
                        _|                        |
                  NIRS | |                        |
                          ----| |--------------| |-
                           | | LIDAR            XRS
                           | |
                           | |      -Z
                           | |
                           | |
                           | |  Sample horn
                          /   \
 
 
 
      Communications Subsystem
      ========================
 
  The communications subsystem includes the 1.6 meter two axis gimbaled,
  parabolic high gain antenna (HGA), two medium gain horn antennae (MGA)
  located on the HGA deck, four micro strip low gain antennae (LGA), an
  X-band transmitter (XTX), and two X-band receivers (XRX).  The uplink
  frequency is 7156.533 MHz and the downlink frequency is 8408.210 MHz.
  The signal has right hand circular polarization.  The XRX receives and
  demodulates command signals and receives and filters range signals.  The
  maximum transmitter power is 20 W and the bit rates can be set at 8, 16,
  32, 64, 128, 256, 512, 1024, 2048, 4096, or 8192 bps with a maximum of
  about 5 MB per day.
 
 
      Command and Data Handling Subsystem
      ===================================
 
  The Data Handling Subsystem (DHS) comprises the command and telemetry
  processors, a solid state Data Recorder (DR), and an interface to a
  redundant data bus for communicating with other processor-controlled
  subsystems. The functions provided by the DHS are command management,
  telemetry management, and autonomous operations.
 
  The command function operates on inputs from the two command receivers
  at one of three rates: 15.625 bps, 125 bps, or 1000 bps. The format of
  the uplinked commands is Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems
  (CCSDS) compliant, with only a single virtual channel. Four types of
  commands are supported: discrete commands are used to turn on or off a
  function provided by a spacecraft subsystem; serial magnitude commands
  are used to set values to one or more parameters of a subsystem; user
  data commands are used to send a block of user data to a subsystem; and
  memory write commands are used to write a block of data to a portion of a
  memory installed in a subsystem.  The DHS relays these commands as they
  are to intelligent subsystems (or components) using the data bus, or
  sends discrete and serial magnitude commands as physical signals to
  non-intelligent subsystems (or components) on serial interfaces. A series
  of commands that perform a specific function can be stored as a command
  macro, which can be executed with a command sent from the ground or by
  one of the methods described below.
 
  The DHS can also store a sequence of time-tagged commands or command
  macros, which is called a timeline, for later execution at specified
  spacecraft times.  When the DHS detects an anomaly, it can automatically
  execute a command or command macro. Intelligent subsystems can also
  request the DHS to issue a command or command macro to another subsystem.
  During normal operations, most of commands are executed from a timeline,
  which have been pre-stored from the ground. In this way, most operations
  are carried out when the spacecraft is out of ground contact.
 
  The telemetry function collects engineering status and science data
  using dedicated serial interfaces from non-intelligent subsystems (or
  components), or using the data bus from intelligent subsystems (or
  components). These data are always packetized either by the DHS or by
  intelligent subsystems (or components), and placed into CCSDS-compliant
  transfer frames. The transfer frames are directed to the DR, the
  downlink, or both. Data recorded on the DR are read back, packed into
  transfer frames and placed into the downlink on command.  Recorder
  playback data can be interleaved with real time data on the downlink.
 
  The downlink data rate is selectable among 11 rates ranging from 8192
  bps to 8 bps to match the communication link capability throughout the
  mission.

        </description>
    </Instrument_Host>
</Product_Context>
