<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mpfl</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>MARS PATHFINDER LANDER</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.mars_pathfinder</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:asimet.mpfl</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:imp.mpfl</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rss.mpfl</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:windsock.mpfl</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mars</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.mars.deimos</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.mars.phobos</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:sun.sun</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S. W., N. A. Renzetti, The Deep Space Network as an instrument for radio
                   science research, NASA Technical Reports Server, 1993STIN...9521456A, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ASMAR-RENZETTI1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Cook, R., P. Katemeyn, and C. Salvo, Mars Pathfinder Project Mission Plan,
                   JPL Document 11355, PF-100-MP-02, 90 pp., 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.COOKETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Golombek, M.P., The Mars Pathfinder Mission, J. Geophys. Res., 102,
                   3953-3965, 1997.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GOLOMBEK1997</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument_Host>
        <name>MARS PATHFINDER LANDER</name>
        <type>Spacecraft</type>
        <naif_host_id>MPFL</naif_host_id>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Host Overview - Spacecraft
  =====================================
 
    Launch Vehicle Description
    --------------------------
      The launch vehicle used for Mars Pathfinder was the McDonnell
      Douglas Delta II 7925.  An engine section in the Delta first
      stage housed the Rocketdyne RS-27 main engine and two
      Rocketdyne LR101-NA-11 vernier engines.  The vernier engines
      provided roll control during main engine burn, and attitude
      control after main engine cutoff and before second stage
      separation.  The RS-27 main engine was a single start, liquid
      bi-propellant rocket engine which provided approximately
      894,094 N of thrust at lift off.  The first stage propellant
      load (96,000 kg) consisted of RP-1 fuel (thermally stable
      kerosene) and liquid oxygen as an oxidizer.  The RP-1 fuel tank
      and liquid oxygen tank were separated by a center body section
      that housed control electronics, ordnance sequencing equipment,
      a telemetry system, and a rate gyro.  First stage thrust
      augmentation was provided by nine solid-propellant Graphite
      Epoxy Motors (GEMs), each fueled with 12,000 kg of
      hydroxyl-terminated polybutadiene solid propellant.  Each GEM
      provided an average thrust of 439,796 N at lift off.  The main
      engine, vernier engines, and six of the GEMs were ignited at
      lift off.  The remaining three GEMs were ignited in flight.
      The GEMs were jettisoned from the first stage after motor
      burnout.
 
      The interstage assembly extended from the top of the first
      stage to the second stage mini-skirt.  This assembly carried
      loads to the first stage, and contained an exhaust vent and six
      spring driven separation rods.
 
      The Delta II 7925 second stage propulsion system included a
      restartable, liquid bi-propellant Aerojet AJ10-118K engine that
      consumed Aerozine 50 fuel (a 50/50 mix of hydrazine and
      asymmetric dimethyl hydrazine) and nitrogen tetroxide (N2O4).
      Since Aerozine 50 and nitrogen tetroxide are hypergolic, no
      catalyst or igniter in the engine thrust chamber was required.
      The second stage had a total propellant load of 6000 kg and
      provided a thrust of 42,000 N.  Gaseous helium was used for
      pressurization, and a nitrogen cold gas jet system provided
      attitude control during coast periods and roll control during
      powered flight.  Hydraulically activated gimbals provided pitch
      and yaw control.  The forward section of the second stage
      housed the guidance and control equipment that provided
      guidance sequencing and stabilization signals for both the
      first and second stages.  Both first and second stages had a
      battery driven DC power system.  Separate batteries were used
      for the guidance and control system, ordnance, and engine
      systems.  The instrumentation and flight termination system
      were powered by the same battery.
 
      The Payload Assist Module D (PAM-D) was the third stage of the
      Delta II 7925 launch vehicle and provided the final velocity
      required to place the Pathfinder spacecraft on a trajectory to
      Mars.  The PAM-D upper stage consisted of (1) a spin table to
      support, rotate, and stabilize the Pathfinder spacecraft /
      PAM-D combination before separating from the second stage, (2)
      a Star-48B solid rocket motor for propulsion, (3) an active
      Nutation Control System (NCS) to provide stability after
      spin-up of the spacecraft/PAM-D stack, (4) a 3717C payload
      attach fitting to mount the Star-48B motor to the spacecraft,
      and (5) a yo-yo de-spin system designed to decrease the spin
      rate of the upper stage / spacecraft stack from 70 RPM to 12
      +/- 2 RPM.  The Star-48B provided an average thrust of 67,168 N
      and was fueled with 2000 kg of solid propellant that was
      composed primarily of ammonium perchlorate and aluminum.
 
      During launch and ascent through the sensible atmosphere, the
      Pathfinder spacecraft / PAM-D upper stage combination was
      protected from aerodynamic forces by a 2.9 m diameter payload
      fairing.  The payload fairing was jettisoned from the launch
      vehicle during second stage powered flight at a minimum
      altitude of 111 km.
 
 
    Flight System Description
    -------------------------
      The Mars Pathfinder Flight System consisted of six major
      subsystems: Attitude and Information Management (AIM);
      Telecommunications; Entry, Descent, and Landing (EDL); Power
      and Pyrotechnics; Propulsion; and Mechanical Structure.  Brief
      descriptions of the subsystems are given below.
 
 
    Mechanical Structure
    --------------------
      The Mars Pathfinder flight system was effectively three
      spacecraft in one.  The flight system was a standard
      interplanetary spacecraft in one mode, an atmospheric entry
      vehicle in another, and a surface lander in the third.  The
      major components of the spacecraft were the cruise stage, the
      entry vehicle (consisting of the heatshield, backshell, and
      attached hardware), and the lander (containing the rover).
      Components from all other subsystems were distributed through
      each of these elements.
 
      The purpose of the lander was to provide engineering support to
      the science instruments and rover during surface operations.
      The landing approach employed by Mars Pathfinder required the
      lander to have self righting capability.  A simple tetrahedron
      design was developed to limit the possible landing
      orientations.  The lander was able to right itself if it landed
      on any face of the tetrahedron by driving actuators which
      connected three faces of the tetrahedron (the petals) with the
      fourth (the base petal).  All thermally sensitive electronics
      were contained in the insulated Integrated Support Assembly
      (ISA) located inside the tetrahedron.  This enclosure provided
      a controlled environment to minimize the effects of the extreme
      temperature variations on Mars.  The lander high gain antenna
      and low gain antenna were attached to the outside of the ISA,
      as was the Imager for Mars Pathfinder.  The rover was attached
      to one of the side petals.
 
      A detailed description of the entry vehicle is given in the
      following EDL subsystem description.  The cruise stage was
      responsible for controlling the vehicle during cruise, and was
      home to most of the components required for interplanetary
      flight.  These included launch vehicle separation devices;
      attitude sensors; propulsive thrusters, tanks, and other
      equipment; cruise antennas; and solar arrays.  The cruise stage
      was jettisoned prior to entry into the Martian atmosphere and
      impacted the surface.  To eliminate duplication of
      capabilities, cruise stage hardware utilized key
      telecommunications, attitude and information management
      services, and power support from equipment that resided on the
      lander.  As a result, there was a significant umbilical
      extending between the lander and cruise stage.
 
 
    Entry, Descent, and Landing Subsystem
    -------------------------------------
      The Entry, Descent, and Landing subsystem was responsible for
      safely placing the lander on the surface of Mars.  In order to
      do this, the velocity had to be reduced from the initial entry
      velocity of 7.6 km/s to a level that limited the maximum
      landing shock to less than 40 g&apos;s.  Specific components of the
      system required to do this included a 2.65 meter diameter
      aeroshell, accelerometers, a parachute, an incremental bridle,
      retrorockets, airbags, and a radar altimeter.
 
      The aeroshell was used to reduce the velocity of the vehicle
      from 7.6 km/s to .370 km/s, removing over 99% of the initial
      kinetic energy and protecting the lander against the resultant
      extreme aerodynamic heating.  The heatshield was a
      Viking-heritage, 70 degree half angle blunt cone.  Thermal
      protection was provided by Viking-heritage SLA-561V ablative
      material.  Ablative material was also applied to the backshell
      to protect the lander from the effects of recirculation flow
      around the entry vehicle.  During the entry and descent phases,
      accelerometers on the lander provided parachute deployment
      timing information and acceleration data.  A 12.7 meter
      diameter Viking heritage disk-gap-band parachute was used for
      terminal descent.  The parachute was designed to open at
      supersonic speeds with a maximum deployment dynamic pressure of
      700 N/m^2.
 
      The EDL system also included separation devices designed to
      separate the heatshield from the backshell after parachute
      deployment.  The heatshield had to be separated and released
      from the backshell so that the lander could be deployed on the
      incremental bridle.  The incremental bridle was designed to
      provide separation between the backshell-mounted retrorockets
      and the lander and to improve stability during the rocket
      firing.  A radar altimeter on the lander was used to determine
      when to ignite the three retrorockets.  The retrorockets were
      sized to bring the backshell/lander system to a complete stop
      at approximately 15 m above the surface.  Four airbags attached
      to the faces of the tetrahedral lander were inflated just
      before the rockets fired and were designed to limit landing
      loads to less than 40 Earth g&apos;s.  The airbags were inflated
      using three gas generators in 1/4 of a second.  The generators
      continued to maintain the pressure in the airbags for over one
      minute past initial pressurization.  Just prior to contacting
      the surface, cable cutters released the lander from the
      parachute, backshell, and retrorockets.  The lander hit with a
      vertical velocity of 12 m/s and a horizontal velocity of 6 m/s.
      After ground impact and tumbling, the airbags deflated and were
      retracted.  The three lander petals were then opened to
      establish an upright configuration on the surface.
 
      All of the details of the timing for the entire EDL procedure
      were determined in real time on board the spacecraft.
 
 
    Attitude and Information Management Subsystem
    ---------------------------------------------
      The AIM subsystem performed all spacecraft computing functions
      including command and telemetry handling, HGA pointing, payload
      data compression, cruise attitude determination and control,
      and EDL timing.  This subsystem was built around a single
      high-performance (20 MIPS), 32-bit, single-board R6000
      computer.  The computer had 128 Mbyte of dynamic RAM for flight
      software, engineering measurements, and science data.  An
      additional 4 Mbytes of electronically erasable PROM was
      included to hold flight software boot code, critical sequences
      and data.  The speed and capabilities of this computer greatly
      simplified both software development and mission operations.
 
      Internal interfaces within AIM were implemented using a VME bus
      backplane.  Major VME interfaces included the Power &amp;
      Pyrotechnics subsystem, the Reed Solomon downlink board, the
      hardware command decoder, and the power converter unit.  A
      Mil-Std-1553 bus served for engineering data links to remote
      engineering units which collected status data from the
      celestial sensors and analog telemetry channels.  Celestial
      sensors included a modified Magellan/IUS star scanner and a
      five head sun sensor.  The spacecraft was spin stabilized
      during cruise, and maintained an Earth point profile for most
      of the flight (except for portions near Earth and Mars).  The
      attitude determination and control system was required to
      maintain at least 2 degrees inertial pointing throughout
      cruise.  Attitude determination and HGA control was required
      during the surface phase.  The autonomous pointing accuracy
      requirement for the HGA was 3.5 degrees (note that more
      accurate pointing was possible using downlink dithering).  The
      AIM was also responsible for collecting and packetizing science
      data from the instruments.
 
      Flight software in the AIM controlled the uplink interface,
      downlink telemetry, instrument control, engineering / science
      data collection and formatting, bus control, sequence and
      command processing, attitude determination / control, and power
      / pyro functions.  The flight software design was coded in &apos;C&apos;.
      The operating system was an adaptation of VxWorks, a
      commercially-available operating system for the R6000 computer.
      The operating system provided a file system and an interprocess
      communications protocol for flight software components.
 
 
    Telecommunications Subsystem
    ----------------------------
      The Telecommunications subsystem provided communications
      capability during cruise, EDL and surface operations and
      support for radio navigation during cruise.  The baseline
      design was a direct to Earth X-band system.  There were two
      major elements to this subsystem: the Radio Frequency Subsystem
      (RFS) and the Antenna Subsystem.  All RFS components were
      located in the lander ISA.  Primary RFS functions were
      performed by a single string Cassini transponder, a 13 watt
      (RF) Solid State Power Amplifier, a newly developed Telemetry
      Modulation Unit, and a Cassini Command Decoder Unit.  This
      single string approach was designed to work for the duration of
      the short Pathfinder mission, however, a partially redundant
      backup downlink capability was also provided.  This backup
      system included a small X-band transmitter with an integrated 5
      W (RF) power amplifier and an additional TMU.  This backup
      provided significantly less performance than the primary
      system, but was designed to be sufficient to satisfy the
      primary mission objectives in an emergency.
 
      The Antenna Subsystem consisted of five antennas for cruise,
      EDL and surface operations.  A waveguide connected the RFS in
      the lander to a medium gain antenna (MGA) located on the cruise
      stage.  A medium gain antenna was required to maintain a
      minimum 20 b/s link through cruise.  The MGA was a standard
      Mars Observer design.  Two antennas were provided for EDL
      communications.  The backshell LGA was used during entry and
      early parachute descent.  The EDL LGA was a whip antenna
      attached to the top of the lander and was used during the final
      portion of parachute descent.  Two antennas were provided on
      the lander.  The principal antenna was a steerable high gain
      antenna mounted on the ISA.  The HGA was a mechanically-steered
      slotted plate with 2 degrees of freedom in pointing.  It
      provided a nominal 125 b/s command uplink rate and a telemetry
      downlink rate of approximately 600 b/s into a DSN 34-m antenna
      (or 2700 b/s into a 70-m antenna).  These data rate
      capabilities assumed 3.5 degrees pointing of the HGA.  Improved
      pointing (using a dithering scheme with the DSN) could improve
      these rates.  These rates were also conservative in that they
      contained a 3 dB link margin.  A Low Gain Antenna was provided
      for emergency situations in the event the HGA should fail.  The
      LGA provided an emergency 7.8 b/s command uplink rate and a
      minimum 40 b/s downlink rate over a 60 degree beam width.
 
 
    Power and Pyrotechnics Subsystem
    --------------------------------
      The Power and Pyrotechnics Subsystem was responsible for
      generating, storing and distributing power during cruise and
      surface operations.  In addition, this subsystem was
      responsible for controlling and initiating all pyrotechnic
      devices required for EDL and surface operations.  Power was
      generated during cruise by a 4.4 m^2 Gallium Arsenide (GaAs)
      solar array which covered the top surface of the cruise stage.
      The 5.5 mm thick cells were arranged to prevent any single
      failures from catastrophically impacting the power output.
      Power was generated on the surface by 2.9 m^2 of GaAs solar
      arrays mounted on the exposed surfaces of the lander petals.
      The lander and cruise stage used the same 5.5 mm thick cells.
 
      A 40 amp-hr (~1120 W-hr @ 28 V) silver zinc battery was used to
      provide energy storage during the mission.  Silver zinc
      batteries are typically used in primary battery applications
      (like launch vehicles), but Pathfinder re-qualified the
      technology for use as a rechargeable battery.  The advantage of
      this type of battery is a much higher energy density than
      typical NiCd or NiH batteries.  The disadvantage is a
      relatively short cycle life (limited to 30-100 cycles).  The
      battery was only used to support launch, trajectory correction
      maneuvers (TCMs) and surface operations, however, so the cycle
      capability was sufficient for primary operations.
 
      The power distribution system used an unregulated bus
      controlled by a shunt regulator.  Pyro devices were initiated
      using a secondary power distribution system (isolated from the
      main) to prevent ground loop problems.  Because of the rapid
      firing of pyros during EDL, special thermal batteries were
      included as a backup power source for the pyro system.  The
      pyro system was designed to provide sufficient arm and enable
      controls to satisfy all system safety requirements.
 
 
    Propulsion Subsystem
    --------------------
      The Propulsion subsystem included all equipment needed to
      perform attitude control and TCM&apos;s during cruise and Rocket
      Assisted Deceleration during EDL.  The cruise stage propulsion
      system consisted of four blow-down hydrazine titanium
      propellant tanks connected with eight 4.45 N (1 lb) thrusters
      via series latch valves.  These thrusters were arranged to
      allow coupled turns and both axial and transverse translational
      maneuvers.  The purpose and function of the RAD rockets are
      described more fully in the EDL section above.
 
 
    Mass Summary
    ------------
      The spacecraft launch mass was 894 kg, including the hydrazine
      (N2H4) propellant, science instruments, and a free-ranging
      rover surface vehicle.  The required amount of propellant was
      calculated using the maximum available spacecraft launch mass
      of 905 kg.  The entry mass was 584 kg.  The entry mass was a
      key driver on the EDL system design, so careful margin
      management was important.
 
 
    Spacecraft Summary
    ------------------
      Launch Mass:        894 kg (Includes Propellant)
      Entry Mass:         584 kg
      Lander Mass:        370 kg
 
      Basic Design:
         - Aeroshell, parachute, RAD rocket and airbag Entry, Descent,
           and Landing (EDL) system
         - Self righting, tetrahedral lander
         - Active thermal design for cruise
         - Free ranging rover
 
      Command And Data Handling
         - Integrated Attitude and Information Management System (AIM)
 
      Computation
         - R6000 Computer with VME bus, 22 Millions of Instructions Per
           Second (MIPS), 128 Mbyte mass memory
 
      Power
         - Solar powered cruise stage and lander
 
      Telemetry And Command
         - Surface operations telemetry rate via High Gain Antenna (HGA),
           X-Band: 6 kb/s to 70 m Deep Space Network
         - Surface operations command rate via HGA, X-Band: 250 b/s
 
      Propulsion
         - Monopropellant hydrazine used for cruise
         - Eight 4.4 N thrusters
         - Total delta-v of 130 m/s
 
 
  Instrument Host Overview - DSN
  ==============================
    The Pathfinder radio telecommunications system was used to
    monitor the distance between Earth and Pathfinder and its rate of
    change in order to determine the rate of precession of Mars.
    This utilized elements of the NASA Deep Space Network (DSN) in
    addition to the instrumentation on board the spacecraft.
 
    The Deep Space Network is a telecommunications facility managed
    by the Jet Propulsion Laboratory of the California Institute of
    Technology for the U.S.  National Aeronautics and Space
    Administration.
 
    The primary function of the DSN is to provide two-way
    communications between the Earth and spacecraft exploring the
    solar system.  To carry out this function the DSN is equipped
    with high-power transmitters, low-noise amplifiers and receivers,
    and appropriate monitoring and control systems.
 
    The DSN consists of three complexes situated at approximately
    equally spaced longitudinal intervals around the globe at
    Goldstone (near Barstow, California), Robledo (near Madrid,
    Spain), and Tidbinbilla (near Canberra, Australia).  Two of the
    complexes are located in the northern hemisphere while the third
    is in the southern hemisphere.
 
    The network comprises four subnets, each of which includes one
    antenna at each complex.  The four subnets are defined according
    to the properties of their respective antennas: 70-m diameter,
    standard 34-m diameter, high-efficiency 34-m diameter, and 26-m
    diameter.
 
    These DSN complexes, in conjunction with telecommunications
    subsystems onboard planetary spacecraft, constitute the major
    elements of instrumentation for radio science investigations.
 
    For more information see [ASMAR&amp;RENZETTI1993].

        </description>
    </Instrument_Host>
</Product_Context>
