<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.sdu</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>STARDUST</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.next::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.stardust::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:cida.sdu::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:dfmi.sdu::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:dynsci.sdu::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:navcam.sdu::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--noSpice        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--noSpice            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:spice.sdu::1.0</lidvid_reference> -->
<!--noSpice            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type> -->
<!--noSpice        <Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:src.sdu::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:asteroid.5535_annefrank::1.0</lidvid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibration.calibration::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibration.non_science::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:comet.81p-wild_2_1978_a2::1.0</lidvid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:comet.9p-tempel_1_1867_g1::1.0</lidvid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
<!--        <Internal_Reference> RChen/EN hope this isn't really needed -->
<!--            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:unk.unk::1.0</lidvid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Brownlee, D.E., P. Tsou, J.D. Anderson, M.S. Hanner, R.L. Newburn, Z. Sekanina,
                   B.C. Clark, F. Horz, M.E. Zolensky, J. Kissel, J.A.M. McDonnell, S.A. Sandford,
                   and A.J. Tuzzolino, Stardust: Comet and interstellar dust sample return
                   mission, J. Geophys. Res., 108, (E10), 8111, 2003, doi:10.1029/2003JE002087.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.BROWNLEEETAL2003</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Tsou, P., D.E. Brownlee, S.A. Sandford, F. Horz, and M.E. Zolensky, Wild 2 and
                   interstellar sample collection and Earth return, J. Geophys. Res., 108, (E10),
                   8113, 2003.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.TSOUETAL2003</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Veverka, J., K. Klaasen, M. A&apos;Hearn, M. Belton, D. Brownlee, S. Chesley, B.
                   Clark, T. Economou, R. Farquhar, S. Green, A. Harris, O. Groussin, J. Kissel,
                   J.-Y. Li, K. Meech, J. Melosh, J. Richardson, P. Schultz, J. Silen, J.
                   Sunshine, P. Thomas, S., Bhaskaran, D. Bodewits, B. Carcich, A. Cheuvront, T.
                   Farnham, S. Sackett, D. Wellnitz, and A. Wolf, Return to Comet Tempel 1:
                   Results from Stardust-NExT, Icarus (tentative), 2011, in press, preprint
                   included in all Stardust-NExT PDS data sets.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.VEVERKAETAL2011</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument_Host>
        <name>STARDUST</name>
        <type>Spacecraft</type>
        <naif_host_id>SDU</naif_host_id>

        <description>
 
      This description was copied from the &apos;Stardust Mission Plan&apos;
      document with permission from the Stardust project.  It has been
      updated to reflect the completion of the primary mission.
 
      SDN:  This description has been updated for the Stardust-NExT
      extended mission.  The original description was left largely
      intact and a short section added at the end for SDN.  The prefix
      &apos;SDN&apos; occurs before that section.
 
 
      STARDUST was a 3-axis stabilized spacecraft designed to perform
      its prime mission (Wild 2 encounter) at 1.9 AU from the sun and
      2.6 AU from the earth. During the cruise periods to and from
      this encounter, it was able to function adequately at a
      maximum distance of 2.7 AU from the sun and 3.6 AU from the
      earth.
 
      The spacecraft was equipped with a power subsystem, fixed solar
      panels and one rechargeable battery, capable of delivering a
      minimum of 170 watts (W) during standard cruise operations at
      aphelion and a minimum of 300 W at comet encounter. The solar
      panels had a maximum off-sun pointing constraint of 60 degrees
      to avoid problems caused by refraction of light.
 
      Communications were achieved via either a high-gain, medium-gain
      or one of three low gain antennas. During the mission, Deep Space
      Network (DSN) support was provided with primarily 34-m
      antennas with 70-m support being used during the close comet
      encounter, trajectory correction maneuvers, and other special
      activities. These antennas provided the capability for a minimum
      of 4000 bits per second (bps), 7900 bps expected, at encounter
      via the high-gain antenna and a 70-m DSN station. This data rate
      could be increased to 22120 bps with additional tight attitude
      control. At maximum Earth range, 40 bps could be achieved via the
      medium gain antenna and a 34-m DSN station. The low-gain
      antennae, in conjunction with a 34-m DSN antenna, were ideal for
      near-Earth phases (Launch, Earth flyby and Earth return) when
      Sun-Earth-spacecraft angles were near 90 degrees, especially since
      they could support communications within 0.05 AU (+3 dB margin) of
      the earth at a minimum data rate of 40 bps.
 
      Attitude control and propulsive maneuvers were performed using a
      redundant helium-fed mono-propellant (hydrazine) propulsion
      subsystem. The subsystem was comprised of one titanium propellant
      tank and a total of 16 thrusters (two strings of 8), all mounted
      on the lower deck of the spacecraft (opposite the high-gain
      antenna and solar panels - pointing toward the -z-axis of the
      spacecraft). Eight of these were 0.2 lb-f (0.89 N) thrusters and
      were used primarily for attitude control. The other eight are 1.0
      lb-f (4.45 N) thrusters and were used for propulsive maneuvers. To
      avoid potential contamination of the aerogel collector, placement
      of thrusters on the upper deck (+z) was avoided. This
      configuration, however, generated uncoupled thrusts during
      attitude control burns and added complexity to trajectory
      simulations.
 
      The normal spacecraft attitude during the mission pointed the
      +z-axis of the spacecraft to the sun. Deviations from the normal
      attitude were performed during communication periods and
      delta-velocity burns. Off-sun pointing was also permitted
      during non-primary science experiments, comet and interstellar
      dust particle collection, as long as the power generated by
      the solar arrays was adequate at the desired off-sun angle. During
      the comet encounter period, the +x-axis was pointed to the dust
      stream.
 
      Whipple shields were placed on the spacecraft to protect it from
      high velocity dust impacts during the comet encounter. The barriers
      were designed to stop a 1 cm size particle traveling at 6 km/s
      (which was essentially equal to the comet encounter relative
      velocity).
 
      Science objectives were met using three science subsystems:
      Aerogel Dust Collector and Sample Return Capsule (SRC), Cometary
      and Interstellar Dust Analyzer (CIDA) and the Dust Flux Monitor
      Instrument (DFMI). The imaging camera was also used for science
      purposes but its main function was to perform optical navigation
      prior to encounter with comet Wild 2.
 
      The current best estimate of the mass breakdown of the flight
      system is summarized in this table:
 
         STARDUST Mass Element List (Rev. Z)
 
         Component      Mass (kg)   Component             Mass (kg)
         S/C Power       33.378     Navigation Camera     12.686
         S/C Harness     20.971     DFMI                   1.530
         S/C Telecom     19.222     CIDA                  10.966
         S/C ACS          9.951     SRC Avionics           1.992
         S/C C&amp;DH        10.394     SRC Harness            0.869
         S/C Thermal     10.060     SRC Thermal           13.683
         S/C Structures 104.412     SRC Structures         9.271
         S/C Mechanisms   6.131     SRC Mechanisms        17.184
         S/C Propulsion   19.538    SRC Parachute          4.194
         Pressurant (He)   0.202    Total Dry            305.397
         Propellant       85.000    Total Wet            390.599
 
 
      SDN:  Stardust-NExT update
      ==========================
 
        Extended mission
        ----------------
 
          The Stardust spacecraft flew by Earth in January, 2006 to
          successfully return the SRC.  The Stardust-NExT extended
          mission was developed soon after and used SDU, without the SRC
          and with an estimated 14kg+ of fuel, to fly the remaining
          instruments (CIDA, DFMI, and NAVCAM) as a scientific
          investigation past the comet 9P/Tempel 1 in February, 2011.
 
          The limited fuel made flying the extended mission quite
          challenging, but maneuvers and operations were optimized to
          minimize fuel usage, and the spacecraft successfully encountered
          Tempel 1 on 15 February, 2011 with all instruments in working
          order.
 
 
        Postscript
        ----------
 
          In March, 2011 the project commanded SDU to perform a final
          propulsive maneuver designed to burn the remaining fuel to
          exhaustion to calibrate and/or validate the fuel estimation
          techniques which had been used.
 
          The final telemetry from the Stardust spacecraft activity
          indicated that the fuel consumed during this activity was no more
          than could be accounted for by the volume of the fuel system
          lines.  So at the end of two scientific missions, the Stardust
          fuel tank was literally empty.

        </description>
    </Instrument_Host>
</Product_Context>
