<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1F00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1F00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mo</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>MARS OBSERVER</title>
        <information_model_version>1.15.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-02-24</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Changed inst LIDs from
                      u:n:p:c:i:instID.scID to
                      u:n:p:c:i:scID.instID
                    And per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.7,
                    changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.mars_observer</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mo.rss</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mars</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Albee, A.L., and D.F. Palluconi, Mars Observers&apos; Global Mapping Mission,
                   EOS, 71, 1099-1107, 1990.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ALBEE-PALLUCONI1990</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Asmar, S. W., N. A. Renzetti, The Deep Space Network as an instrument for radio
                   science research, NASA Technical Reports Server, 1993STIN...9521456A, 1993.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ASMAR-RENZETTI1993</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument_Host>
        <name>MARS OBSERVER</name>
        <type>Spacecraft</type>
        <naif_host_id>MO</naif_host_id>

        <description>
 
 
    Mars Observer was launched September 25, 1992 from Cape Canaveral
    on a Titan III built by Martin Marietta Corporation, with an
    upper Transfer Orbit Stage from Orbital Sciences Corporation.
    Flight controllers lost contact with the spacecraft on August
    21, 1993, effectively terminating the mission.
 
    For most Mars Observer experiments, data were to be collected by
    instruments on the spacecraft.  Those data were then to be
    relayed via the telemetry system to stations of the NASA Deep
    Space Network (DSN) on the ground.  Radio Science experiments
    (such as radio tracking of the spacecraft and bistatic radio
    scattering experiments) required that DSN hardware also
    participate in data acquisition.  The following sections provide
    an overview first of the spacecraft and then of the DSN ground
    system as both supported Mars Observer science activities.
 
    Instrument Host Overview - Spacecraft
    =====================================
 
      The Mars Observer spacecraft provided a stabilized,
      nadir-oriented platform for continuous observations of Mars by
      an advanced set of science instruments.However, communication
      with the spacecraft was lost three days before it was scheduled
      to enter Mars orbit in late August 1993.  Only data from
      Earth-Mars cruise and a very small amount of distant-encounter
      Mars data were obtained from Mars Observer.
 
      The spacecraft contract was originally won by the RCA
      Astro-Space Division (ASD), which subsequently became the
      General Electric Astro-Space Division when the two companies
      merged.  The selection of RCA was intended to make maximum use
      of existing designs and technologies from DMSP/TIROS weather
      satellites and Satcom-K communication satellites.  General
      Electric sold ASD to Martin Marietta Corporation at about the
      time Mars Observer was launched; Martin Marietta was the prime
      contractor when the spacecraft was lost.
 
      The dimensions of the rectangular bus were 2.1 x 1.5 x 1.1 m in
      the x-y-z dimensions.  When fully deployed, the six-panel solar
      array was 7.0 x 3.7 meters, and would have developed over a
      kilowatt of power at Mars.  The mass of the spacecraft was
      about 1028 kg, including 166 kg of payload but excluding the
      approximately 1346 kg of propellant required, most of which was
      intended for orbit insertion and orbit circularization at Mars.
      The propellant also included 63 kg of hydrazine, which would
      have been used for spacecraft control during mapping.
 
      At launch (25 September 1992), the solar panels and high-gain
      antenna were folded against the rectangular bus and the two
      science booms (Magnetometer and Gamma-Ray Spectrometer) were
      retracted.  During early cruise the partially-deployed
      spacecraft was stabilized in a controlled 0.01-rpm roll about
      the y-axis; communications were conducted with Earth via a
      low-gain antenna.  For trajectory correction and orbit
      insertion maneuvers the spacecraft was oriented under three-
      axis control and then returned to cruise attitude.
 
      In its mapping orbit, Mars Observer was to be controlled in
      three axes, using its horizon sensors to point the science
      instruments on the +Z face toward the nadir.  The six-panel
      solar-array was to be fully deployed on a boom to track the Sun
      during each orbit, and the high-gain antenna boom was to be
      fully deployed to track the Earth around each orbit.
 
      Spacecraft pointing control was provided by four reaction
      wheels.  Attitude information during mapping was to be provided
      by a Mars horizon sensor that defined the nadir direction, a
      star-mapper for inertial attitude, gyros and accelerometers for
      measuring angular rates and linear accelerations, and multiple
      sun sensors.  The spacecraft was required to maintain adequate
      pointing control and to provide sufficient telemetry to allow
      reconstruction of the pointing after each orbit.  The telemetry
      stream provided data from the sensors sufficient to
      characterize nadir and high-gain antenna pointing to within +/-
      3 mrad (per axis, 3 sigma) and boom-mounted science instrument
      pointing to within +/- 25 mrad (per axis, 3 sigma).
 
      Two independent propulsion systems were provided.  All major
      maneuvers, both in cruise and during orbit insertion, were to
      be accomplished by a hypergolic, bipropellant system.  A
      hydrazine system was available for orbit trim maneuvers during
      the mapping period and some attitude control functions,
      including unloading of the momentum wheels.  The hydrazine
      thrusters were chosen to minimize contamination of the
      instruments during the mapping period.
 
      Most instruments were rigidly mounted on a nadir-pointing
      spacecraft panel and, in general, provided simultaneous views
      of the same nadir area.  No movable scan platform was provided;
      the spacecraft was to be continuously pointed toward nadir,
      rotating at the orbital rate.  Those instruments that required
      scanning or multiple fields of view were constructed with
      internal scanning mechanisms.  The Gamma Ray Spectrometer and
      Magnetometer sensor assemblies were mounted on individual booms
      on the spacecraft.  The steerable high-gain antenna (used for
      radio science) was mounted on a third boom.
 
      For more information regarding the Mars Observer spacecraft,
      see [ALBEE&amp;PALLUCONI1990]
 
 
    Instrument Host Overview - DSN
    ==============================
      The Mars Observer Radio Science investigations utilized
      instrumentation with elements both on the spacecraft and at the
      NASA Deep Space Network (DSN).  Much of this is shared
      equipment, being used for routine telecommunications as well as
      for Radio Science.
 
      The Deep Space Network is a telecommunications facility managed
      by the Jet Propulsion Laboratory of the California Institute of
      Technology for the U.S.  National Aeronautics and Space
      Administration.
 
      The primary function of the DSN is to provide two-way
      communications between the Earth and spacecraft exploring the
      solar system.  To carry out this function the DSN is equipped
      with high-power transmitters, low-noise amplifiers and
      receivers, and appropriate monitoring and control systems.
 
      The DSN consists of three complexes situated at approximately
      equally spaced longitudinal intervals around the globe at
      Goldstone (near Barstow, California), Robledo (near Madrid,
      Spain), and Tidbinbilla (near Canberra, Australia).  Two of the
      complexes are located in the northern hemisphere while the
      third is in the southern hemisphere.
 
      The network comprises four subnets, each of which includes one
      antenna at each complex.  The four subnets are defined
      according to the properties of their respective antennas: 70-m
      diameter, standard 34-m diameter, high-efficiency 34-m
      diameter, and 26-m diameter.
 
      These DSN complexes, in conjunction with telecommunications
      subsystems onboard planetary spacecraft, constitute the major
      elements of instrumentation for radio science investigations.
 
      For more information see [ASMAR&amp;RENZETTI1993].
 

        </description>
    </Instrument_Host>
</Product_Context>
