<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a16l</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>APOLLO 16 LUNAR MODULE</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.apollo_16::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:lsrp.a16l::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.moon::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo 16 Preliminary Science Report, NASA SP-315, 622 pages, published by
                   NASA, Washingtion, D.C., 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLO16A1972</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo 16 - Expedition to Descartes (mission report), NASA MR-11, published by
                   NASA, Washingtion, D.C., 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLO16B1972</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Davies, M.E., and T.R. Colvin, Lunar coordinates in the regions of the Apollo
                   landers, Journal of Geophysical Research, Volume 105, Issue E8, pages
                   20,227-20,280, 2000, doi:10.1029/1999JE001165.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.DAVIES-COLVIN2000</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument_Host>
        <name>APOLLO 16 LUNAR MODULE</name>
        <type>Spacecraft</type>
        <naif_host_id>A16L</naif_host_id>

        <description>
 
  Instrument Host Overview
  ========================
    The Apollo 16 lunar module (LM) spacecraft was the fifth crewed
    vehicle to land on the Moon.  It carried two astronauts, Commander
    John W. Young and pilot Charles M. Duke, Jr..  The LM also carried
    a Lunar Roving Vehicle (LRV), an Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments
    Package (ALSEP) that contained scientific experiments to be
    deployed and left on the lunar surface, and other scientific and
    sample collection apparatus.
 
    The LM separated from the CSM at 18:08:00 UT on 20 April 1972 and
    landed at 02:23:35 UT on 21 April (9:23:35 p.m. EST, 20 April) in
    the Descartes highland region just north of the crater Dolland at
    8.9730 S latitude, 15.5002 E longitude (IAU Mean Earth Polar Axis
    coordinate system).  Young and Duke made three moonwalk
    extra-vehicular activities (EVAs) totaling 20 hours, 14 minutes.
    During this time they covered 27 km and collected 94.7 kg of rock
    and soil samples, stopping at 11 sites. The LRV was used during
    EVAs to extend the range of surface lunar exploration.
 
    The first EVA was on 21 April from 16:47:38 UT to 23:58:40 UT,
    during which the astronauts set up the ALSEP and other instruments,
    deployed the LRV, and explored the area around the LM and
    surrounding craters in a 4.2 km-traverse, stopping at Flag Crater
    and Spook Crater.
 
    During the second EVA on 22 April from 16:33:35 UT to 23:56:44 UT
    the astronauts explored a ridge and mountain slope during a 11.1-km
    traverse and visited the Cinco Crater area, halfway up the slope of
    Stone Mountain, and the base of Stone Mountain.
 
    On the third EVA, of 11.4 km, on 23 April from 15:25:28 UT to
    21:05:31 UT they travelled to the southeast rim of North Ray
    Crater, House Rock, and the base of Smoky Mountain.  During all
    these EVAs the astronauts collected samples and took photographs
    and performed other tasks at some sites.
 
    The LM ascent stage lifted off from the Moon on 24 April at
    01:25:48 UT after 71 hours, 2 minutes on the lunar surface.  After
    the lunar module docked with the command and service module
    (piloted by Thomas K. Mattingly II) at 03:35:18 UT, the lunar
    samples and other equipment were transferred from the lunar module,
    and the lunar was jettisoned at 20:54:12 UT on 24 April.  The lunar
    module began tumbling, apparently due to an open circuit breaker in
    the guidance and navigation system.  As a result the planned
    de-orbit and lunar impact could not be attempted.  The lunar module
    remained in lunar orbit with an estimated lifetime of one year.
 
 
    Lunar Module Spacecraft and Subsystems
    --------------------------------------
      The lunar module was a two-stage vehicle designed for space
      operations near and on the Moon.  The ascent and descent stages of
      the lunar module operated as a unit until lift-off from the Moon,
      when the ascent stage functioned as a single spacecraft for
      rendezvous and docking with the command and service module.  The
      ascent stage contained the landing rocket, life-support systems,
      scientific instruments, such as the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments
      Package (ALSEP), the Soil Mechanics instrument package, and the
      lunar rover. The descent stage served as a platform for launching
      the ascent stage and was left behind on the Moon.
 
      An S-band antenna was used for all telemetry, TV, voice, and range
      communications with Earth. VHF was used for communications between
      the astronauts and the lunar module, and the lunar module and
      orbiting command module.  There were redundant transceivers and
      equipment for both S-band and VHF.  An environmental control system
      recycled oxygen and maintained temperature in the electronics and
      cabin.  Power was provided by 6 silver-zinc batteries.  Guidance and
      navigation control were provided by a radar ranging system, an
      inertial measurement unit consisting of gyroscopes and
      accelerometers, and the Apollo guidance computer.
 
 
    Scientific Experiments
    ----------------------
      The following scientific experiments were performed on board or near
      the Apollo 16 Lunar Module:
 
      - Handheld Photography documented the deployment of experiments,
        augmented crew observations and descriptions of the lunar
        traverses, and recorded the effects of the interaction between
        Apollo equipment and the lunar surface.
 
      - The Soil Mechanics Experiment studied the properties of the lunar
        soil.
 
      - The Solar Wind Composition Experiment collected samples of the
        solar wind for analysis on Earth.
 
      - The Lunar Portable Magnetometer measured the strength of the Moon&apos;s
        magnetic field at different locations near the landing site.
 
      - The Far Ultraviolet (UV) Camera/Spectrograph acquired UV images and
        spectra of astronomical objects.
 
      - The Cosmic Ray Detector measured very high energy cosmic rays from
        the Sun and our galaxy.
 
    For more information about the lunar module and its experiments, see
    the Apollo 16 Preliminary Science Report [APOLLO16A1972].
 
 
  This instrument host description was provided by the NASA National Space
  Science Data Center.

        </description>
    </Instrument_Host>
</Product_Context>
