<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.near</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>NEAR EARTH ASTEROID RENDEZVOUS</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.near_earth_asteroid_rendezvous</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--removed in 1.1    	<Internal_Reference> -->
<!--removed in 1.1    		<lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.support_archives::1.0</lid_reference> -->
<!--removed in 1.1    		<reference_type>instrument_host_to_investigation</reference_type> -->
<!--removed in 1.1    	</Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:grs.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mag.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:msi.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nis.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:nlr.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rss.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--noSpice        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--noSpice            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:spice.near</lid_reference> -->
<!--noSpice            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type> -->
<!--noSpice        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--:grs        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--:grs            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:xgr.near</lid_reference> -->
<!--:grs            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type> -->
<!--:grs        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:xrs.near</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:asteroid.253_mathilde</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:asteroid.433_eros</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:asteroid.asteroid</lid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planetary_system.solar_system</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Santo, A.G., S.C. Lee, and R.E. Gold, NEAR Spacecraft and Instrumentation, The
                   Journal of the Astronautical Sciences, Vol. 43, No. 4, pp. 373-397,
                   October-December 1995.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.SANTOETAL1995</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    
    <Instrument_Host>
        <name>NEAR EARTH ASTEROID RENDEZVOUS</name>
        <type>Spacecraft</type>
        <naif_host_id>NEAR</naif_host_id>

        <description>
 
This description contains excerpts from:
   Santo, A.G., S.C. Lee, and R.E. Gold, NEAR Spacecraft and
   Instrumentation, The Journal of the Astronautical Sciences, Vol. 43,
   No. 4, pp. 373-397, October-December 1995 [SANTOETAL1995] describing
   the NEAR spacecraft.
 
 
    Instrument Host Overview
    ========================
      The NEAR spacecraft design is mechanically simple, and geared toward
      a short development and test time. Except for the initial deployment
      of the solar panels and protective instrument covers, the spacecraft
      has only one moveable mechanism. A distributed architecture allows
      parallel development and test of each subsystem, yielding an
      unusually short spacecraft integration and test period. Several
      innovative features of the NEAR design include the first use of an
      X-band solid state power amplifier for an interplanetary mission,
      the first use of a hemispherical resonator gyroscope in space, and
      extremely high-accuracy high voltage power supply control.
 
 
    System Description
    ====================
      Most electronics are mounted on the forward and aft decks. The
      science instruments, except for the magnetometer, are hard-mounted
      on the outside of the aft deck with co-aligned fields-of-view. The
      magnetometer is mounted on the High Gain Antenna (HGA) feed. The
      interior of the spacecraft contains the propulsion module.
 
      The spacecraft design was selected for its mechanical simplicity.
      The solar panels, the HGA, and the instruments are all fixed. The
      solar panels and HGA can be fixed because throughout most of the
      mission the Sun-spacecraft-Earth  angle is less than 40 degrees.
      While the HGA is pointed to the Earth, the Sun to solar panel angle
      is small and the energy output from the resultant solar illumination
      incident on the panels is sufficient. During the first two months
      after launch and for a short time during the Earth flyby, the
      Sun-spacecraft-Earth angle is greater than 40 degrees. At these
      times, the telecommunication link is sufficient to allow
      communications with the Earth through the medium or low gain
      antennas while keeping the solar panels pointed within 40 degrees of
      the Sun. During asteroid operations, the geometry allows the
      spacecraft to be oriented as needed for scientific data collecting,
      while maintaining the required Sun to solar panel angle. While
      mechanically simple and reliable, hard-mounting the HGA, solar
      panels, and instruments drives other areas of spacecraft and mission
      design. The resultant spacecraft moments-of-inertia are such that
      closed-loop control of the vehicle pointing must be maintained
      throughout the mission. Because the power system is designed for
      100% sunlight operation, the 450 N thruster location is chosen such
      that the panels can be oriented towards the Sun during all large
      delta(V) maneuvers. Finally, scientific operations and high speed
      downlink to Earth cannot always be carried out simultaneously.
 
    Command and Data Handling Subsystem
    ======================================
      The Command and Data
      Handling (C&amp;DH) subsystem comprises redundant APL-built command and
      telemetry processors, redundant Solid State Recorders (SSR), a power
      switching unit to control spacecraft relays, and an interface to-a
      redundant 1553 standard bus for communicating with other
      processor-controlled subsystems. The redundant components are
      cross-strapped among themselves, and among the redundant uplink
      chains of the telecommunications subsystem.  The functions provided
      by the C&amp;DH subsystem are command management, telemetry management,
      and autonomous operations.
 
      The command function operates on cross-strapped inputs from the two
      CDUs at either of two rates: 125 bps (normal mode) or 7.8 bps
      (emergency rate). The format of the uplinked commands is
      Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems (CCSDS) compliant,
      with a separate virtual channel for each side of the redundant C&amp;DH
      subsystem. Four types of commands are supported: relay commands are
      directed to the power switching unit to change the state of the
      spacecraft relays; dedicated data commands are directed over
      specific serial interfaces to control SSR and telecommunications
      subsystem operation; 1553 data commands are directed to a specified
      remote terminal on the 1553 bus; and C&amp;DH-specific commands are
      interpreted within the C&amp;DH to control its own operation.  Some of
      the C&amp;DH-specific commands provide facilities for storing commands
      for later execution, either at a specified Mission Elapsed Time
      (MET), or when the spacecraft conditions warrant autonomous action.
      A series of commands that perform a specific function can be stored
      as a command macro; the entire series of commands can be invoked by
      a single macro execute command. During normal operations, the C&amp;DH
      will invoke command macros that have been scheduled for execution at
      a specific MET.  In this way, operations are carried out when the
      spacecraft is out of ground contact. Command macros can also be
      invoked by the autonomy function of the C&amp;DH, to place the
      spacecraft in a safe condition. Approximately 56 K bytes of memory,
      4000 commands, is available for stored commands in each processor.
 
      The telemetry function collects engineering status and science data
      from the housekeeping interface, from dedicated serial interfaces,
      from the remote terminals on the 1553 bus, and from the C&amp;DH
      internal event history buffers. This data is packetized where
      necessary, and placed into CCSDS-compliant transfer frames. The
      transfer frames are directed to the SSRs, the downlink, or both.
      Data recorded on the SSRs is read back, packed into transfer frames
      and placed into the downlink on command. Recorder playback data can
      be interleaved with realtime data on the downlink, and data can be
      recorded on one of the redundant SSRs while the other recorder is
      read back.
 
      SEAKR provides the SSRs. These recorders are constructed out of 16
      Mbit IBM Luna-C DRAMs. One recorder has 0.67 Gbits of storage; the
      other recorder has 1.1 Gbits of storage because it contains an
      additional memory board which is designated as the flight spare, and
      will be used to replace either of the other memory boards in the
      event of a ground test failure.
 
      The downlink data rate is selectable among eight rates ranging from
      26.5 kbps to 9.9 bps to match the communication link capability
      throughout the mission. For all except the highest downlink rate,
      the recorder capacity exceeds the downlink capacity, so bandwidth is
      limited by the downlink.  While the C&amp;DH subsystem controls the rate
      of collection of realtime data to match the downlink rate, the rate
      at which data is placed on the recorder is under the control of the
      subsystems. Each remote terminal on the 1553 bus can request the
      C&amp;DH to pick up and record up to 5336 bits of data per second. This
      feature allows the spacecraft operators complete flexibility with
      respect to the bandwidth used by each instrument.
 
 
    Guidance and Control Subsystem
    ================================
      The Guidance and Control (G&amp;C) subsystem is composed of a suite of
      sensors for attitude determination, actuators for attitude
      corrections, and processors to provide continuous, closed loop
      attitude control.  In
      operational mode, the attitude is controlled to a commanded pointing
      scenario. In safe modes, the G&amp;C maintains the solar panels pointed
      to the Sun for maximum power, and attempts to place the Earth within
      the medium-gain antenna pattern to establish ground communications.
      The G&amp;C subsystem also controls the thrusters for delta(V)
      maneuvers. Finally, the G&amp;C subsystem recognizes many internal
      failure modes and initiates autonomous actions to correct them.

        </description>
    </Instrument_Host>
</Product_Context>
