<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibrator.gll_pct</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>GLL PCT</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Target>
        <name>GLL PCT</name>
        <type>Calibrator</type> <!--RChen/EN was Calibration-->

        <description>
 
    Description
    ===========
      From [CARLSONETAL1992]:
 
      The Photometric Calibration Target (PCT) and an associated optical
      element, the Photometric Calibration Mirror (PCM) together form a
      source of diffusely reflected solar radiation which can be used by
      the remote sensing experiments for intra- and inter-instrument
      comparisons. These two elements are mounted on the Science Boom; the
      mirror reflects solar radiation onto the diffusing target surface
      which is placed outboard from the mirror and in a position that can
      be viewed from the scan platform. In order that the target be
      illuminated over the nominal range of solar cone angles, the mirror
      is convex, with a radius of curvature of 46 cm and located 53 cm
      from the target. The reflecting surface is vacuum deposited
      aluminum, with a protective overcoat formed by its natural oxide.
      The target surface is similar to the Voyager diffuser plate,
      consisting of sand blasted aluminum. The combination produces a
      spectrally gray diffuse surface, with an effective albedo of roughly
      0.05.  They were calibrated over the spectral range of 0.3 to 5.2
      micrometers and for a variety of incidence angles.
        </description>
    </Target>
</Product_Context>
