<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context
  xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
  xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
      <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mercury</logical_identifier>
      <version_id>1.3</version_id>
      <title>Mercury</title>
      <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
      <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
    
      <Alias_List>
          <Alias>
              <alternate_title>NAIF ID 199</alternate_title>
          </Alias>
      </Alias_List>
    
      <Modification_History>
          <Modification_Detail>
              <modification_date>2019-12-06</modification_date>
              <version_id>1.3</version_id>
              <description>
                  Upgrade for MESSENGER migration by PDS Radio Science Advisor.
                  Format improvements for easier reading.
              </description>
          </Modification_Detail>
        
          <Modification_Detail>
              <modification_date>2018-11-18</modification_date>
              <version_id>1.2</version_id>
              <description>
                  From PDS Rings node.
              </description>
          </Modification_Detail>
        
          <Modification_Detail>
              <modification_date>2018-06-23</modification_date>
              <version_id>1.1</version_id>
              <description>
                  From PDS RINGS node. Added NAIF ID alias. Shortened description.
              </description>
          </Modification_Detail>
        
          <Modification_Detail>
              <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
              <version_id>1.0</version_id>
              <description>
                  Extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog, then modified to meet PDS4 requirements.
              </description>
          </Modification_Detail>
        
      </Modification_History>
  </Identification_Area>
  
  <Reference_List>

      <External_Reference>
          <reference_text>
              https://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/planetary/factsheet/mercuryfact.html
          </reference_text>
          <description>
              Fact sheet maintained by NASA Space Science Data Coordinated Archive.
          </description>
      </External_Reference>
      
      <External_Reference>
          <reference_text>
              https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercury_(planet)
          </reference_text>
          <description>
              Overview and summary list of orbital parameters and physical characteristics.
          </description>
      </External_Reference>
      
    <External_Reference>
          <reference_text>
              Solomon, Sean C., Larry R. Nittler, and Brian J. Anderson (editors). 
              Mercury: The View After MESSENGER. United Kingdom: Cambridge University Press,
              583 pp., 2018.
          </reference_text>
          <description>
              A review of knowledge about Mercury after conclusion of observations from the
              first spacecraft to orbit the planet, edited by the MESSENGER mission Principal
              Investigator, his deputy, and the Deputy Project Scientist. Topics include 
              Mercury's chemical composition; the structure of its crust, lithosphere, mantle, 
              and core; Mercury's modern and ancient magnetic field; Mercury's geology, 
              including the planet's major geological units and their surface chemistry and 
              mineralogy, its spectral reflectance characteristics, its craters and cratering 
              history, its tectonic features and deformational history, its volcanic features 
              and magmatic history, its distinctive hollows, and the frozen ices in its polar 
              deposits; Mercury's exosphere and magnetosphere and the processes that govern 
              their dynamics and their interaction with the solar wind and interplanetary 
              magnetic field; the formation and large-scale evolution of the planet; and 
              current plans and needed capabilities to explore Mercury in the future.
          </description>
      </External_Reference>
    
      <External_Reference>
          <reference_text>
              Vilas, Faith, Clark R. Chapman, and Mildred Shapley Matthews (editors). Mercury,
              Tucson: The University of Arizona Press, 794 pp., 1988.
          </reference_text>
          <description>
              A compendium of knowledge about Mercury as of the mid-1980s, ten years after the
              Mariner 10 flybys and more than 20 years before MESSENGER entered Mercury orbit.
              Forty-seven collaborating authors contributed chapters on surface composition, 
              stratigraphy, and geology; tectonics; history; dynamics; magnetic field; atmosphere; 
              the puzzling icy polar deposits; and prospects for future exploration.
          </description>
      </External_Reference>
      
  </Reference_List>
  
  <Target>
      <name>Mercury</name>
      <type>Planet</type>
      <description>
          The innermost planet in the Solar System.
          One of the terrestrial (rocky) planets.
      </description>
  </Target>
  
</Product_Context>
