<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1F00.sch" 
 schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1F00.xsd">
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:individual.greeley_35mm_slides</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>The Ronald Greeley 35mm Slide Collection</title>
        <information_model_version>1.15.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2021-05-19</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>Initial version</description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:asurgcps_slides_jovian_system:document_users_guide:asurgcps_slides_jovian_system_users_guide</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_document</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
    </Reference_List>
    <Investigation>
        <name>The Ronald Greeley 35mm Slide Collection</name>
        <type>Individual Investigation</type>        
        <start_date>1968</start_date>
        <stop_date>2005</stop_date>
        <description>
            The Ronald Greeley 35mm Slide Collection consists of 14,435 color and grayscale slides that include images of planetary bodies (Moon, 
            planets, asteroids, and comets), planetary missions (e.g., Voyager, Galileo, Viking), planetary analog sites on Earth, and presentation 
            materials for research results presented at national conferences. The slides were produced by Dr. Ronald Greeley during his tenure as 
            a research scientist in the late 1960s while at working at NASA Ames, through to the early 2000s when he was a Regents Professor at 
            Arizona State University. The slides were digitized to preserve the research materials of Dr. Ronald Greeley, who played a critical 
            role in the planetary missions to the planets of the inner and outer Solar System. 
            
            The slides were professionally scanned at high resolution (4000 dpi) and organized into document bundles by subject: aeolian and 
            volcanic Earth analog sites, wind tunnel laboratory experiments, general space science, and by individual planetary bodies (e.g., Moon, 
            Mars) and planetary systems (e.g., Jovian System). In addition to the digital products, metadata for each slide (where information is 
            available) is included in the Collection.  The entire slide collection is hosted by the Planetary Data System and the Ronald Greeley 
            Center for Planetary Studies at Arizona State University in order to make this historic slide collection to the greater planetary 
            science community.
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
