<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A10.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A10.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.messenger</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>MESSENGER</title>
        <information_model_version>1.10.1.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>MESS</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>MESS</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-06-21</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                  replaced all lidvid_reference with lid_reference.
                  Changed target:calibration.calibration to target:calibraor.calibration
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mess</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:calibrator.calibration</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.earth</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mercury</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.venus</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Solomon, S.C., R.L. McNutt, Jr., R.E. Gold, and D.L. Domingue, MESSENGER
                   mission overview, Space Science Reviews, 131, 3-39, 2007.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.SOLOMONETAL2007</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>MESSENGER</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>2004-08-03</start_date>
        <stop_date>2015-04-30</stop_date>

        <description>
 
   MESSENGER Mission Overview
   ==========================
     The MErcury Surface, Space ENvironment, GEochemistry,
     and Ranging (MESSENGER) spacecraft was launched from
     the Cape Canaveral Air Station on 2004-08-03, on an
     approximately 8 year mission to become the first
     probe to orbit the planet Mercury.
 
     The MESSENGER payload consists of seven instruments
     and a radio science (RS) experiment.  The instruments
     are the Mercury Dual Imaging System (MDIS), the Gamma-
     Ray and Neutron Spectrometer (GRNS), the X-Ray
     Spectrometer (XRS), the Magnetometer (MAG), the
     Mercury Laser Altimeter (MLA), the Mercury Atmospheric
     and Surface Composition Spectrometer (MASCS), and the
     Energetic Particle and Plasma Spectrometer (EPPS).
 
     The MESSENGER mission is fully described in
     [SOLOMONETAL2007].
 
     MDIS
     ----
       The MDIS instrument includes both a wide-angle (WA)
       and a narrow-angle (NA) camera and both are capable
       of summing pixels.  This provides for images of the
       surface that are of nearly uniform horizontal
       resolution (125 m per pixel or better throughout
       MESSENGER&apos;s elliptical orbit).  The WA and NA
       cameras (WAC and NAC) are mounted on opposite sides
       of a pivot platform, making MDIS the only MESSENGER
       instrument capable of pointing independent of
       spacecraft attitude.
 
       MDIS contributes to the understanding of the
       geological landforms and processes that shaped
       Mercury&apos;s surface.
 
     GRNS
     ----
       The GRNS instrument includes two sensors, a Gamma-
       Ray Spectrometer (GRS) and a Neutron Spectrometer
       (NS).  The GRS is a germanium detector with an
       active shield capable of measuring the elemental
       abundances of O, Si, S, Fe, H, K, Th, and U.  The NS
       sensor consists of two lithium glass scintillators
       separated by a thick slab of borated plastic
       scintillator.  The glass scintillators measure
       thermal neutrons, while the borated-plastic
       scintillator counts fast neutrons.
 
       GRNS contributes to the understanding of surface
       elemental abundances and the composition of polar
       deposits.
 
     XRS
     ---
       The XRS detects solar-induced X-ray fluorescence to
       measure the surface abundances of Mg, Al, Si, Ca, Ti
       and Fe.  Three proportional counters measure low-
       energy X-rays from the planet, while a Si-PIN
       detector located on the spacecraft sunshade measures
       the solar X-ray input.  The XRS has a field of view (FOV)
       of 12 degrees and covers an energy range from 1 to 10 keV.
 
       XRS contributes to the understanding of surface
       elemental abundances.
 
     MAG
     ---
       The MAG instrument is a miniaturized three-axis,
       ring-core, fluxgate magnetometer mounted on a
       lightweight 3.6 m carbon-fiber boom extending from
       the spacecraft in the anti-sunward direction.  It
       samples the field at a 20-Hz rate with selectable
       readout intervals between 0.04 s to 1 s. Readout
       intervals of greater than 1 s generate a 0.5 s
       average.
 
       MAG contributes to the mapping of Mercury&apos;s internal
       magnetic field and to understanding the
       magnetospheric structure.
 
     MLA
     ---
       The MLA consists of a 1064 nm laser transmitter and
       four sapphire lens receiver telescopes.  It is
       capable of measuring altitudes to a 30-cm precision
       at ranges up to 1000 km.  Because of this range, the
       MLA will operate for about 30 minutes around the
       periapsis of each orbit.
 
       MLA contributes to the mapping of the northern
       hemisphere topography and the altimetry of polar
       craters and is instrumental in determining Mercury&apos;s
       gravity field, obliquity and libration amplitude.
 
     MASCS
     -----
       The MASCS instrument combines a movable-grating
       Ultraviolet-Visible Spectrometer (UVVS) and a
       Visible-Infrared Spectrograph (VIRS) into one
       package. Both instruments share a single front-end
       telescope.  UVVS spans the spectral range from 115
       to 600 nm with an average spectral resolution of 1
       nm, has a 25 km altitude resolution, and is
       optimized for measuring very weak exospheric
       emissions.  VIRS measures the visible (300-1025 nm)
       and infrared (0.95-1.45 um) spectral ranges
       utilizing a 512 element detector for the visible and
       a 256 element detector for the infrared.
 
       MASCS contributes to the understanding of the
       composition of Mercury&apos;s surface in association with
       particular geological units, and to the
       understanding of neutral species in the exosphere
       especially near the polar regions.
 
     EPPS
     ----
       EPPS consists of an Energetic Particle Spectrometer
       (EPS)and a Fast Imaging Plasma Spectrometer (FIPS).
       The EPS measures the time-of-flight and residual
       energy of ions from 10 keV/nucleon to ~3 MeV and
       electrons to 400 keV.  Its FOV, 160 degrees by 12
       degrees, is divided into six segments of 25 degrees
       each.  The FIPS measures thermal and low-energy ions
       and is sensitive over nearly a full hemisphere, with
       energy per charge (E/q) up to &gt; 15 keV/q.
 
       EPPS contributes to the understanding of the solar
       environment associated with Mercury and its
       magnetosphere.
 
     RS
     --
       The spacecraft&apos;s radio frequency (RF)
       telecommunications system is for communications,
       navigation and radio science (RS).  Precise
       observation of the spacecraft&apos;s Doppler velocity and
       range are used to assist in navigating the
       spacecraft. These observations will be inverted to
       determine the effect of the planet&apos;s gravitational
       field on the spacecraft.  Occultation observations
       of the spacecraft&apos;s RF signal will provide necessary
       measurements of Mercury&apos;s shape in the southern
       hemisphere.
 
       RS contributes to the understanding of Mercury&apos;s
       gravity field, obliquity and libration amplitude
       (Doppler observations) and its global topography,
       especially the southern hemisphere (occultation
       observations).
 
   Mission Phases
   ==============
     Nineteen mission phases were defined for significant
     spacecraft activity periods.  The large number of
     phases is due to the complex sequence of gravitational
     assists necessary to bring the spacecraft into orbit
     around Mercury while maintaining a minimal mass due to
     fuel.  This consideration lead to one Earth flyby, two
     Venus flybys, and three Mercury flybys before orbit
     insertion at Mercury.
 
     The mission phases are defined naturally by the
     various planetary encounters and their intervening
     cruise periods. Given the short encounter times for
     each MESSENGER flyby, we define encounter phases on
     the basis of a 4 week period centered on the closest
     approach to each target body (two weeks before and two
     after) and separate such encounter segments by cruise
     phases. The cruise periods and flybys are named
     according to the planetary body involved. Also defined
     are a launch and an orbit phase.
 
     The mission phases are: Launch, Earth Cruise, Earth
     Flyby, Venus 1 Cruise, Venus 1 Flyby, Venus 2 Cruise,
     Venus 2 Flyby, Mercury 1 Cruise, Mercury 1 Flyby,
     Mercury 2 Cruise, Mercury 2 Flyby, Mercury 3 Cruise,
     Mercury 3 Flyby, Mercury 4 Cruise, Mercury Orbit,
     Mercury Orbit Year 2, Mercury Orbit Year 3,
     Mercury Orbit Year 4, and Mercury Orbit Year 5.
 
     Launch
     ------
       The launch phase has been defined to capture
       instrument data produced between launch and the
       beginning of Phase E.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2004-08-03 (2004-216)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2004-09-12 (2004-256)
 
     Earth Cruise
     ------------
       Earth Cruise is the period of time between launch
       and the week before closest approach to Earth.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2004-09-13 (2004-257)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2005-07-18 (2005-199)
 
     Earth Flyby
     -----------
       Earth Flyby is defined as the four week (28 day)
       period centered on closest approach to Earth.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2005-07-19 (2005-200)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2005-08-16 (2005-228)
 
     Venus 1 Cruise
     --------------
       Venus 1 Cruise is defined as the period between the
       Earth flyby and the first Venus flyby.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2005-08-17 (2005-229)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2006-10-09 (2006-282)
 
     Venus 1 Flyby
     -------------
       Venus 1 Flyby is defined as the four week (28 day)
       period centered on the first of the mission&apos;s two
       closest approaches to Venus.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2006-10-10 (2006-283)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2006-11-07 (2006-311)
 
     Venus 2 Cruise
     --------------
       Venus 2 Cruise is defined as the period between the
       first and second Venus flyby.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2006-11-08 (2006-312)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2007-05-22 (2007-142)
 
     Venus 2 Flyby
     -------------
       Venus 2 Flyby is defined as the four week (28 day)
       period centered on the second of the mission&apos;s two
       closest approaches to Venus.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2007-05-23 (2007-143)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2007-06-20 (2007-171)
 
     Mercury 1 Cruise
     ----------------
       Mercury 1 Cruise is defined as the period between
       the second Venus flyby and first Mercury flyby.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2007-06-21 (2007-172)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2007-12-30 (2007-364)
 
     Mercury 1 Flyby
     ---------------
       Mercury 1 Flyby is defined as the four week (28 day)
       period centered on the first of the mission&apos;s three
       closest approaches to Mercury.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2007-12-31 (2007-365)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2008-01-28 (2008-028)
 
     Mercury 2 Cruise
     ----------------
       Mercury 2 Cruise is defined as the period between
       the first and second Mercury flyby.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2008-01-29 (2008-029)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2008-09-21 (2008-265)
 
     Mercury 2 Flyby
     ---------------
       Mercury 2 Flyby is defined as the four week (28 day)
       period centered on the second of the mission&apos;s three
       closest approaches to Mercury.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2008-09-22 (2008-266)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2008-10-20 (2008-294)
 
     Mercury 3 Cruise
     ----------------
       Mercury 3 Cruise is defined as the period between
       the second and third Mercury flyby.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2008-10-21 (2008-295)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2009-09-15 (2009-258)
 
     Mercury 3 Flyby
     ---------------
       Mercury 3 Flyby is defined as the four week (28 day)
       period centered on the third of the mission&apos;s three
       closest approaches to Mercury.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2009-09-16 (2009-259)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2009-10-14 (2009-287)
 
     Mercury 4 Cruise
     ----------------
       Mercury 4 Cruise is defined as the period between
       the third Mercury flyby and Mercury orbit insertion.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2009-10-15 (2009-288)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2011-03-03 (2011-062)
 
     Mercury Orbit
     -------------
       The Orbit phase begins at Mercury orbit insertion
       and continues until the end of mission. This phase
       begins the most intensive science portion of the mission
       with full instrument utilization throughout the
       period.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2011-03-04 (2011-063)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2012-03-17 (2012-077)
 
     Mercury Orbit Year 2
     --------------------
       The Orbit phase year 2 begins the extended mission. This phase
       continues the most intensive science portion of the mission
       with full instrument utilization throughout the period.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2012-03-18 (2012-078)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2013-03-17 (2013-076)
 
     Mercury Orbit Year 3
     --------------------
       The Orbit phase year 3 continues the extended mission. This phase
       continues the most intensive science portion of the mission
       with full instrument utilization throughout the period.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2013-03-18 (2013-077)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2014-03-17 (2014-076)
 
     Mercury Orbit Year 4
     --------------------
       The Orbit phase year 4 continues the extended mission. This phase
       continues the most intensive science portion of the mission with
       full instrument utilization throughout the period.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2014-03-18 (2014-077)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2015-03-17 (2015-076)
 
     Mercury Orbit Year 5
     --------------------
       The Orbit phase year 5 continues the extended mission through to
       the end of orbital operations. This phase continues the most
       intensive science portion of the mission with full instrument
       utilization through near the end of the period which ended when
       the spacecraft impacted Mercury as expected on 30 April 2015.
 
       Mission Phase Start Time : 2015-03-18 (2014-077)
       Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2015-04-30 (2015-120)
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
