<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model
    href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context
    xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1
            https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.juno</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>2.1</version_id>
        <title>JUNO</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>2.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-07-10</modification_date>
                <version_id>2.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    added instrument LIDs
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:mwr.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:uvs.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:grav.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:waves.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:jade.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:jedi.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:junocam.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:jiram.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:fgm.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument:rmi.jno</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>        
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:dust.dust</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.earth</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.jupiter</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planetary_system.solar_system</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--notyet       <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--notyet            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:plasma_cloud.io_plasma_torus</lid_reference> -->
<!--notyet            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--notyet       </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:plasma_stream.solar_wind</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> wait for Rings -->
<!--            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:ring.jupiter.rings</lid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>instrument_host_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.jupiter.callisto</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.jupiter.europa</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.jupiter.ganymede</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.jupiter.io</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.earth.moon</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Stephens, S. K., Juno Project Mission Plan, Rev. D, JPL D-35556, 15 August 2013.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.JPLD-35556</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>JUNO</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>2011-08-05</start_date>
        <stop_date nilReason="unknown" xsi:nil="true"></stop_date>

        <description>
The majority of the text in this file
was extracted from the Juno Mission Plan Document, S. Stephens, 29 March
2011.[JPL D-35556]
 
 
Mission Overview
================
  Juno launched on 5 August 2011.  The spacecraft uses a deltaV-EGA trajectory
  consisting of a two part deep space maneuver on 30 August and 14 September
  2012 followed by an Earth gravity assist on 9 October 2013 at an altitude of
  559 km.  Jupiter arrival is on 5 July 2016 using two 53.5-day capture orbits
  prior to commencing operations for a 1.3-(Earth) year-long prime mission
  comprising 32 high inclination, high eccentricity orbits of Jupiter.  The
  orbit is polar (90 degree inclination) with a periapsis altitude of
  4200-8000 km and a semi-major axis of 23.4 RJ (Jovian radius) giving an
  orbital period of 13.965 days.  The primary science is acquired for
  approximately 6 hours centered on each periapsis although fields and
  particles data are acquired at low rates for the remaining apoapsis portion
  of each orbit.
 
  Currently, 5 of the first 7 periapses are dedicated to microwave radiometry
  of Jupiter&apos;s deep atmosphere with most of the remaining orbits dedicated to
  gravity measurements to determine the structure of Jupiter&apos;s interior.  All
  orbits will include fields and particles measurements of the planet&apos;s
  auroral regions.  Juno is spin stabilized with a rotation rate of 2
  rotations per minute (RPM).  For the radiometry orbits the spin axis is
  precisely perpendicular to the orbit plane so that the radiometer fields of
  view pass through the nadir.  For gravity passes, the spin axis is aligned
  to the Earth direction, allowing for Doppler measurements through the
  periapsis portion of the orbit.  The orbit plane is initially very close to
  perpendicular to the Sun-Jupiter line and evolves over the 1.3-year mission.
  Generally, data acquired during the periapsis passes are recorded and played
  back over the subsequent apoapsis portion of the orbit, although some data
  can be downlinked during the gravity passes.
 
  Juno&apos;s instrument complement includes Gravity Science using the X and Ka
  bands to determine the structure of Jupiter&apos;s interior; magnetometer
  investigation (MAG) to study the magnetic dynamo and interior of Jupiter as
  well as to explore the polar magnetosphere; and a microwave radiometer (MWR)
  experiment covering 6 wavelengths between 1.3 and 50 cm to perform deep
  atmospheric sounding and composition measurements.  The instrument
  complement also includes a suite of fields and particle instruments to study
  the polar magnetosphere and Jupiter&apos;s aurora.  This suite includes an
  energetic particle detector (JEDI), a Jovian auroral (plasma) distributions
  experiment (JADE), a radio and plasma wave instrument (Waves), an
  ultraviolet spectrometer (UVS), and a Jupiter infrared auroral mapping
  instrument (JIRAM).  The JunoCam is a camera included for education and
  public outreach.  While this is not a science instrument, we plan to capture
  the data and archive them in the PDS along with the other mission data.  The
  MAG investigation consists of redundant flux gate magnetometers (FGM) and
  co-located advanced stellar compasses (ASC).  The ASCs are provided by the
  Danish Technical University under an effort led by John Jorgenson.
 
  Scott Bolton is the Juno Principal Investigator.  The Science Team members
  responsible for the delivery and operation of the instruments are listed
  below:
 
    Instrument                                      Acronym   Lead Co-I
    ----------------------------------------------  --------  ---------
    Gravity Science                                 GRAV      Folkner
    Magnetometer                                    MAG       Connerney
    Microwave Radiometer                            MWR       Janssen
    Jupiter Energetic Particle Detector Instrument  JEDI      Mauk
    Jovian Auroral Distributions Experiment         JADE      McComas
    Radio and plasma wave instrument                Waves     Kurth
    Ultraviolet Imaging Spectrograph                UVS       Gladstone
    Jovian Infrared Auroral Mapper                  JIRAM     Adriani
    Juno color, visible-light camera                JUNOCAM   Hansen
 
 
Mission Phases
==============
 
  LAUNCH
  ------
    The Launch phase starts at L-40 min (Launch-40 min), and covers the
    interval from launch, through initial ground station acquisition, until
    the establishment of a pre-defined, stable, and slowly changing Sun-
    pointed attitude when cruise attitude control algorithms and ephemerides
    can be used. The end of the Launch phase is determined by post-launch
    health and safety assessments.  The boundary is at L+3 days, after initial
    acquisition and after confirmation that the Flight System is safe and in
    a power-positive, thermally stable, and commandable attitude.
 
    Target Name              :  N/A
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2011-08-05 (2011-217)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2011-08-08 (2011-220)
 
 
  INNER CRUISE 1
  --------------
    The Inner Cruise 1 phase lasts from post-Launch establishment of a
    pre-defined and stable Sun-pointed attitude when cruise attitude control
    algorithms and ephemerides can be used, until after initial spacecraft and
    instrument checkouts have been performed and the spacecraft has gotten far
    enough from the Sun to allow Earth-pointing instead of Sun-pointing. TCM 1
    (the first planned trajectory correction maneuver) was deemed not
    necessary, hence, was not executed.  The phase spans the interval from L+3
    to L+66 days.
 
    Target Name              :  SOLAR_SYSTEM
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2011-08-08 (2011-220)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2011-10-10 (2011-283)
 
 
  INNER CRUISE 2
  --------------
    The Inner Cruise 2 phase spans the period from L+66 days until L+663
    days.  The Deep Space Maneuvers (DSMs) occur during this phase, near
    aphelion of Juno&apos;s first orbit about the Sun, on the way to Earth Flyby
    and then Jupiter.  There is increased DSN (Deep Space Network) coverage
    associated with the DSMs and a cleanup TCM. DSMs 1 and 2 occur on
    2012-08-30 and 2010-09-14.
 
    Target Name              :  SOLAR_SYSTEM
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2011-10-10 (2011-283)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2013-05-29 (2013-149)
 
 
  INNER CRUISE 3
  --------------
    The Inner Cruise 3 phase spans the interval from L+663 days to L+823
    days.  The duration of this cruise phase is 160 days.  Featured in this
    phase is Earth Flyby (EFB), which gives Juno a gravity assist (providing
    7.3 km/s of deltaV) on its way to Jupiter. It occurs as the spacecraft is
    completing one elliptical orbit around the Sun and includes perihelion.
    Three TCMs were planned before EFB (the last of which was deemed not
    necessary) and one after EFB. There is increased DSN coverage associated
    with the 4 maneuvers and EFB.  The Inner Cruise 3 phase is focused on
    performing the required maneuvers, as well as an integrated operations
    exercise around Earth Flyby, subject to Flight System constraints.
    Closest approach to Earth occurs on 2013-10-09 at 19:21 UTC.
 
    Target Name              :  EARTH, SOLAR_SYSTEM
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2013-05-29 (2013-149)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2013-11-05 (2013-309)
 
    Earth Closest Approach   :  2013-10-09T19:21 (2013-282)
 
 
  OUTER CRUISE
  ------------
    The Outer Cruise phase lasts from L+823 days until the start of Jupiter
    Approach at Jupiter Orbit Insertion (JOI)-6 months (JOI-182 days or
    L+1614 days). The duration of this cruise phase is 791 days, which is
    over 2 years.
 
    Target Name              :  SOLAR_SYSTEM
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2013-11-05 (2013-309)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2016-01-05 (2016-005)
 
 
  JUPITER APPROACH
  ----------------
    The Jupiter Approach phase lasts the final 6 months of cruise before
    Jupiter Orbit Insertion and is an opportunity for final Flight System and
    instrument checkouts as well as science observations to start exercising
    the ground system and Flight System, although orbit insertion preparations
    limit instrument activities close to JOI. There are more frequent
    maneuvers approaching JOI, starting with a TCM at JOI-5 months, and
    correspondingly increasing DSN coverage. The 178-day Jupiter Approach
    phase is preceded by a 26-month Outer Cruise phase.   Jupiter Approach
    starts 3 months after the project is fully staffed up in preparation for
    JOI and the 1.3 years of science orbits.   The phase ends at JOI-4 days,
    which is the start of the JOI critical sequence.
 
    Target Name:             :  JUPITER, SOLAR_SYSTEM
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2016-01-05 (2016-005)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2016-07-01 (2016-183)
 
 
  JUPITER ORBIT INSERTION
  -----------------------
    The JOI phase encompasses the JOI critical sequence. It begins 4 days
    before the start of the orbit insertion maneuver and ends 1 hour after the
    start.  JOI, the second critical event of the mission, occurs at closest
    approach to Jupiter, and slows the spacecraft enough to let it be captured
    by Jupiter into a 53.5-day orbit and set up the geometry for the 14-day
    science orbits.  A cleanup burn at JOI+8.6d during the Capture Orbits
    phase is required to clean up JOI maneuver execution errors. DSN coverage
    is continuous during the JOI phase.
 
    Target Name              :  N/A
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2016-07-01 (2016-183)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2016-07-05 (2016-187)
 
    Perijove 0               :  2016-07-05T02:47:38 (2016-187)
 
 
  CAPTURE ORBITS
  --------------
    The Capture Orbits phase starts at JOI+1h, after the end of the JOI
    critical sequence, and ends at PRM-5.25d, when instruments are off in
    preparation for the PRM maneuver. Between the two 53.5d capture orbits
    is PJ1 (Perijove 1), at which no maneuver is planned so it can be used as
    the first opportunity for science close to Jupiter and an opportunity to
    test the performance of the instruments in the Jupiter environment.  A JOI
    cleanup maneuver at JOI+8.6d is required to clean up JOI maneuver
    execution errors, while additional maneuvers near the first apojove
    following JOI and at PJ1+14d ensure the timing of PJ1 and the large PRM
    burn at perijove of the following orbit.  Solar conjunction occurs after
    apojove of the second capture orbit.  DSN coverage remains continuous
    until the JOI+8.6d maneuver, then remains at elevated levels throughout
    the two capture orbits, and is continuous again around PJ1 and before PRM.
    Instruments are on for most of the Capture Orbits, and there are routine
    checkouts and science observations.
 
    Target Name              :  JUPITER, SOLAR_SYSTEM
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2016-07-05 (2016-187)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2016-10-14 (2016-288)
 
    Perijove 1               :  2016-08-27T12:51:20 (2016-240)
 
 
  PERIOD REDUCTION MANEUVER
  -------------------------
    The Period Reduction Maneuver phase starts at PRM-5.25d, and ends at
    PRM+50h, coinciding with the instrument keepout zone for the maneuver (no
    science observations are planned during this phase). The burn at PJ2
    (Perijove 2) is designed to accomplish a decrease in the period and size
    of the orbit, thus the name Period Reduction Maneuver (PRM).  PRM requires
    a cleanup maneuver in the following orbit to ensure proper timing for
    longitude coverage during the Science Orbits phase. DSN coverage is
    continuous from PRM-14d until PRM+5d.
 
    Target Name              :  N/A
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2016-10-14 (2016-288)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2016-10-21 (2016-295)
 
    Perijove 2               :  2016-10-19T18:11:07 (2016-293)
 
 
  ORBITS 2-3
  ----------
    The Orbits 2-3 phase starts at PRM+50h, after the end of the instrument
    keepout zone for the Period Reduction Maneuver, and near the beginning of
    the first 14-day orbit.  It ends at PJ4-1d, which is the start of the
    first activity period (MWR AP4) in the Science Orbits. As such, the Orbits
    2-3 phase includes most of the last half of Orbit 2 (PJ2 to AJ2) and all
    of Orbit 3 (AJ2 to AJ3).  DSN coverage is continuous from the start of the
    phase until PRM+5d, and then follows a pattern similar to that used for
    the Science Orbits template.  Instrument checkouts after PRM and science
    observations during the rest of Orbit 2 and in Orbit 3 are planned.
 
    Target Name              :  JUPITER
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2016-10-21 (2016-295)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2016-11-15 (2016-320)
 
    Perijove 3               :  2016-11-02T17:52:29 (2016-307)
 
 
  SCIENCE ORBITS
  --------------
    The Science Orbits phase includes Orbit 4 through Orbit 36. Orbit N is
    defined from apojove (AJ) N-1 through apojove N, and includes perijove
    (PJ) N.  Orbit numbering starts before the Science Orbits phase.  JOI
    occurs at PJ0, so Orbit 0 lasts from PJ0 through AJ0 (including a JOI
    cleanup maneuver at JOI+8.6d).  Orbit 1 includes PJ1, and runs from AJ0
    through AJ1. Orbit 2 includes PJ2 (and PRM at PJ2), and runs from AJ1
    through AJ2. Orbit 0, Orbit 1, and the first half of Orbit 2 together
    contain the two 53.5-day capture orbits.  Orbit 3 includes PJ3 (and the
    PRM cleanup maneuver at PJ3+6h), and runs from AJ2 through AJ3. Early
    orbital science is baselined in Orbits 0, 1, 2, and 3, except for JOI and
    PRM keepout zones.  Orbit 4 is the first science orbit. It includes PJ4
    (and the first OTM at PJ4+7.5h), and runs from AJ3 through AJ4. The last
    science orbit is Orbit 36.  It is bookkept as an extra science orbit,
    since the mission uses Orbits 4 through 35 to obtain 32 perijoves with
    MAG and other data that meet Level-1 baseline science requirements. Small
    (up to 8 m/s) orbit trim maneuvers (OTMs) are planned after each set of
    perijove science observations, at PJ+4h, PJ+6h, or PJ+7.5h in Orbits 4
    through 35, to target the perijove longitude required for science
    observations in the next orbit. There is no need for an OTM after PJ36. A
    deorbit maneuver (deterministic deltaV = 77 m/s) is planned near AJ36.
 
    We distinguish activity periods from orbits.  Orbits are used to refer to
    the mission design and navigation strategy (e.g., Nav data cutoffs, which
    occur near AJ orbit boundaries, and trajectory events), while activity
    periods are used to describe science and mission operations (e.g.,
    sequences and data flow).  An activity period (AP) runs from one PJ-1d to
    the next PJ-1d.  Each AP is defined by the number of the PJ science pass
    it contains, and the type (MWR or GRAV).  AP2 and AP3 are the first 14-day
    activity periods (differing slightly from science orbits activity
    periods), and run from PJ2-1d through PJ3-1d and PJ3-1d through PJ4-1d.
    AP3 is followed by the first activity period during the Science Orbits,
    AP4 (an MWR type), from PJ4-1d through PJ5-1d. The Science Orbits phase
    begins at the start of AP4, and continues through AP36, which ends early,
    at AJ36-1h, before the deorbit burn in the Deorbit phase.
 
    Radiation accumulation increases substantially as the orbital line of
    apsides rotates and perijove latitude increases from 3 degrees at JOI to
    36 degrees at PJ36. There are currently no plans for an extended mission.
 
    Target Name              :  JUPITER
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2016-11-15 (2016-320)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2018-02-13 (2018-044)
 
    Perijove 4               :  2016-11-16T16:54:46 (2016-321)
    Perijove 5               :  2016-11-30T15:52:21 (2016-335)
    Perijove 6               :  2016-12-14T14:49:58 (2016-349)
    Perijove 7               :  2016-12-28T13:47:35 (2016-363)
    Perijove 8               :  2017-01-11T13:59:37 (2017-011)
    Perijove 9               :  2017-01-25T12:57:12 (2017-025)
    Perijove 10              :	2017-02-08T11:54:47 (2017-039)
    Perijove 11              :  2017-02-22T10:52:21 (2017-053)
    Perijove 12              :  2017-03-08T09:12:44 (2017-067)
    Perijove 13              :  2017-03-22T08:10:19 (2017-081)
    Perijove 14              :  2017-04-05T07:07:53 (2017-095)
    Perijove 15              :  2017-04-19T06:05:27 (2017-109)
    Perijove 16              :  2017-05-03T06:17:26 (2017-123)
    Perijove 17              :  2017-05-17T05:14:57 (2017-137)
    Perijove 18              :  2017-05-31T04:12:29 (2017-151)
    Perijove 19              :  2017-06-14T03:10:03 (2017-165)
    Perijove 20              :  2017-06-28T03:40:40 (2017-179)
    Perijove 21              :  2017-07-12T02:38:12 (2017-193)
    Perijove 22              :  2017-07-26T01:35:46 (2017-207)
    Perijove 23              :  2017-08-09T00:33:19 (2017-221)
    Perijove 24              :  2017-08-23T00:08:07 (2017-235)
    Perijove 25              :  2017-09-05T23:05:44 (2017-248)
    Perijove 26              :  2017-09-19T22:03:21 (2017-262)
    Perijove 27              :  2017-10-03T21:00:55 (2017-276)
    Perijove 28              :  2017-10-17T20:35:43 (2017-290)
    Perijove 29              :  2017-10-31T19:33:14 (2017-304)
    Perijove 30              :  2017-11-14T18:30:45 (2017-318)
    Perijove 31              :  2017-11-28T17:28:16 (2017-332)
    Perijove 32              :  2017-12-12T17:02:53 (2017-346)
    Perijove 33              :  2017-12-26T16:00:20 (2017-360)
    Perijove 34              :  2018-01-09T14:57:50 (2018-009)
    Perijove 35              :  2018-01-23T13:55:18 (2018-023)
    Perijove 36              :  2018-02-06T12:52:47 (2018-037)
 
 
  DEORBIT
  -------
    The Deorbit phase occurs during the final perijove-to-perijove orbit of
    the mission.  The 7-day phase starts several days after the Orbit 36
    perijove science pass (part of the extra orbit) at AJ36-1h, before the
    start of the apojove deorbit maneuver (by which time we hope to have all
    or most of the PJ36 data on the ground).  It continues through AJ36, and
    ends with Impact into Jupiter at PJ37. In order to meet planetary
    protection requirements and ensure that we do not impact Europa (as well
    as Ganymede and Callisto), the spacecraft performs a deorbit maneuver near
    apojove that reduces our orbital velocity and sends us to a perijove below
    Jupiter&apos;s cloud tops. The mean burn deltaV of 77 m/s is the largest
    maneuver of the mission after the 4 main engine maneuvers, and is planned
    to be performed on RCS (Reaction Control System) thrusters (deltaV to
    Earth angle, ELA ~ 70 degrees). The timing of the burn is not mission
    critical; a contingency delayed execution can occur several days around
    and following apojove if necessary.  Impact into Jupiter marks End of
    Mission (EOM).
 
    Target Name              :  JUPITER
    Mission Phase Start Time :  2018-02-13 (2018-044)
    Mission Phase Stop Time  :  2018-02-20 (2018-051)
 
    Perijove 37              :  2018-02-20T11:39:44 (2018-051)
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
