<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.apollo_14</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>APOLLO 14</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>A14</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>A14</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a14a</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.earth.moon</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo 14 Preliminary Science Report, NASA SP-272, 302 pages, Washington, D.C.,
                   1971.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLO14A1971</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Davies, M.E., and T.R. Colvin, Lunar coordinates in the regions of the Apollo
                   landers, Journal of Geophysical Research, Volume 105, Issue E8, pages
                   20,227-20,280, 2000, doi:10.1029/1999JE001165.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.DAVIES-COLVIN2000</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>APOLLO 14</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>1971-01-31</start_date>
        <stop_date>1971-02-09</stop_date>

        <description>
 
 
  Mission Overview
  ================
    Apollo 14 was launched on 31 January 1971 UT 21:03:02 on a Saturn V
    rocket from Kennedy Space Center.  Lunar orbit insertion took place on
    4 February 1971 UT 06:59:43. The Lunar Module (LM) landed on the Moon
    on 5 February 1971 UT 09:18:11, in the hilly upland region 24 km north
    of the rim of Fra Mauro crater at 3.6 S, 17.5 W, while the
    Command/Service Module (CSM) orbited the Moon. The lunar ascent module
    launched from the Moon on 6 February 1971 UT 18:48:42.  The command
    module returned to Earth on 9 February 1971 UT 21:05:00.
 
    The astronauts on Apollo 14 were commander Alan Shepard, Jr., command
    module pilot Stuart Roosa, and lunar module pilot Edgar Mitchell.
 
    The astronauts made two moonwalk EVA&apos;s totaling 9 hours, 23 minutes,
    one on 5 February and one on 6 February, during which the Apollo Lunar
    Surface Experiments Package (ALSEP) was placed on the surface and
    activated, 42.9 kg of lunar samples were acquired, and photographs
    were taken.  The lunar surface stay-time was 33.5 hours. The duration
    of the lunar orbit was 66.6 hours for a total of 34 orbits.
 
 
  Surface Operations
  ==================
    Shepard and Mitchell made two moonwalk extra-vehicular activities
    (EVAs) totaling 9 hours, 23 minutes.  During this time the astronauts
    traversed a total of 3.45 km and collected 42.9 kg of lunar samples.
    The first EVA began at 14:42:13 UT on 5 February and ended at 19:30:03
    UT.  During this first EVA the astronauts deployed the ALSEP and other
    experiments in the vicinity of the Lunar Module near Doublet Crater.
    During the second EVA, which took place from 8:11:15 to 12:45:56 UT
    on 6 February, the astronauts walked almost to the rim of nearby
    Cone crater, stopping at 13 stations, collecting samples and taking
    panoramic photographs and magnetometer measurements along the traverse.
    The astronauts did not reach the rim of Cone Crater as planned but
    came within about 20 meters of the edge.  The traverse totaled
    approximately 3 km distance, heading out past Triplet, Weird, and
    Flank Craters and returning along a nearly parallel route.  At the
    end of this walk Shepard used a contingency sampler with a 6-iron
    connected to the end to hit two golf balls.  The LM lifted off the
    Moon on 6 February at 18:48:42 UT after 33 hours, 31 minutes on the
    lunar surface.
 
 
  Surface Experiments
  ===================
    The Apollo 14 astronauts performed and deployed many experiments on
    the lunar surface along with the geologic studies, sample return, and
    surface photography.
 
      - The Soil Mechanics Investigations studied the physical properties
        of the lunar regolith through photography and astronaut
        observations.
 
      - The Solar Wind Composition experiment collected samples of solar
        wind on a large piece of foil which was returned to Earth.
 
      - The Lunar Portable Magnetometer, deployed by the astronauts at
        various locations near the landing site to study local magnetic
        sources.
 
    Other experiments were part of the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments
    Package (ALSEP) which was emplaced at the landing site by the
    astronauts.  The instruments, connected by cables to a central station
    which controlled power and communications, ran autonomously.  Data
    collected was converted to a telemetry format and transmitted to
    Earth.  Many of these experiments returned data until January 1976,
    when the ALSEP network was turned off due to budgetary constraints.
 
    The Apollo 14 ALSEP instruments consisted of:
 
      - A Passive Seismometer, designed to measure seismic activity and
        physical properties of the lunar crust and interior.
 
      - An Active Seismometer, designed to study the physical properties
        of the lunar surface and subsurface materials and the structure of
        the local near-surface layers.
 
      - A Suprathermal Ion Detector. Designed to measure positive ions
        reaching the lunar surface to provide data on the plasma
        interaction between the solar wind and the Moon.
 
      - A Cold Cathode Ion Gage, designed to measure the density of
        neutral particles in the tenuous lunar atmosphere.
 
      - A Charged Particle Lunar Environment Experiment, designed to
        measure the energy spectra of low-energy charged particles
        striking the lunar surface.
 
      - A Lunar Dust Detector, designed to assess the long-term effects of
        the lunar dust, radiation, and thermal environment on solar cells.
 
      - A Laser Ranging Retroreflector, designed to reflect laser pulses
        from Earth back to their point of origin to make accurate
        determination of the distance between the earth and Moon.
 
 
  Orbital Science Experiments
  ===========================
    Investigations were also carried out from lunar orbit in the Apollo 14
    Command and Service Module.  Hand-held photography and telescopic
    selenodetic reference point studies were performed from the command
    module, and instruments operated from the Scientific Instrument Module
    (SIM) in the Service Module, comprising:
 
    - An S-Band Transponder Experiment designed to carefully track the CSM
      orbit and measure the lunar gravity field.
 
    - A Bistatic Radar Experiment used measurements of S-Band and VHF
      reflections to probe electromagnetic and structural properties of
      the lunar surface.
 
    Additional experiments were also performed in lunar orbit and during
    the cruise between Earth and Moon
 
    - The Gegenschein Photography Experiment took images of the
      reflections from dust particles at the Moulton point.
 
    - The Window Meteoroid experiment studied micrometeoroid impacts on
      the Apollo 14 Command Module heat shield windows to obtain
      information about the mass flux of micrometeorites.
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
