<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.apollo_15</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>APOLLO 15</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>A15</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>A15</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a15a</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a15l</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.earth.moon</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo 15 Preliminary Science Report, NASA SP-289, 546 pages, published by
                   NASA, Washington, D.C., 1972.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLO15A1972</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Davies, M.E., and T.R. Colvin, Lunar coordinates in the regions of the Apollo
                   landers, Journal of Geophysical Research, Volume 105, Issue E8, pages
                   20,227-20,280, 2000, doi:10.1029/1999JE001165.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.DAVIES-COLVIN2000</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>APOLLO 15</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>1971-07-26</start_date>
        <stop_date>1971-08-07</stop_date>

        <description>
 
  Mission Overview
  ================
    Apollo 15 was launched on 6 July 1971 UT 13:34:00 on a Saturn V
    rocket from Kennedy Space Center.  Lunar orbit insertion took place
    on 29 July 1971 UT 20:05:47.  The Lunar Module (LM) landed on the
    Moon on 30 July 1971 UT 22:16:29, near the Hadley Rille and
    Apennine Mountains (26.13 N, 3.63 E), while the Command/Service
    Module (CSM) orbited the Moon.  The lunar ascent module launched
    from the Moon on 2 August 1971 UT 17:11:22.  The command module was
    returned to Earth on 7 August 1971 UT 20:45:53.
 
    The astronauts on Apollo 15 were commander David Scott, command
    module pilot Alfred Worden, and lunar module pilot James Irwin.
 
    Three excursions on the first Lunar Roving Vehicle (LRV) lasted a
    total of 18 hours and 35 minutes and traversed 27.9 km.  The lunar
    surface stay-time was 66.9 hours.  During the stay, the Apollo
    Lunar Surface Experiment Package (ALSEP) was placed and activated,
    and 77.31 kg of rock and soil samples were collected.  The duration
    of the lunar orbit was 145 hours for a total of 74 orbits.  The
    small sub-satellite was deployed from the CSM on 4 August 1972 UT
    20:13:19 and left in lunar orbit for the first time.
 
 
  Surface Operations
  ==================
    Scott and Irwin made three moonwalk extra-vehicular activities
    (EVAs) totaling 18 hours, 35 minutes.  During this time they covered
    27.9 km and collected 77.31 kg of rock and soil samples.  The LRV was
    used to explore regions within 5 km of the LM landing site.  This
    was the first time a vehicle of this type had been used, and its
    performance on the lunar terrain was very successful.  Two hours
    after landing the cabin was depressurized and Scott performed a
    standup EVA for 33 minutes, describing and photographing the
    surrounding terrain from the LM upper hatch.  The first moonwalk EVA
    was on 31 July from 13:13:10 UT to 19:45:59 UT, during which time
    the LRV was unloaded, deployed, and driven.  Photographs of the
    lunar surface were taken and geologic samples were collected from
    the LM site and during the three geological traverses.  The traverse
    on the first EVA covered 10.3 km to the edge of Hadley Rille to
    Elbow Crater and near St. George Crater and back to the LM, where a
    core sample was taken from three meters below the surface.  The
    ALSEP was deployed at the end of the traverse. On the second EVA,
    on 1 August from 11:48:48 UT to 19:01:02 UT, the LRV was driven on
    a 12.5 km traverse southeast along the base of the Apennine
    Mountains near Index, Arbeit, Crescent, Dune, and Spur craters and
    back to the ALSEP site.  On the third EVA on 2 August from 08:52:14
    UT to 13:42:04 UT the LRV was driven a total of 5.1 km west to
    Scarp Crater and northwest along the edge of Hadley Rille and back
    east across the mare.  The LM lifted off the Moon on 2 August at
    17:11:22 UT after 66 hours, 55 minutes on the lunar surface.
 
 
  Surface Experiments
  ===================
    The Apollo 15 astronauts performed and deployed many experiments on
    the lunar surface along with the geologic studies, sample return,
    and surface photography.
 
      - The Solar Wind Composition experiment collected samples of
        solar wind on a large piece of foil which was returned to
        Earth;
 
      - The Soil Mechanics Investigations studied the physical
        properties of the lunar regolith using observations recorded by
        video and audio and a surface penetrometer which recorded data
        on a drum which was returned to Earth.
 
    Other experiments were part of the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments
    Package (ALSEP) which was emplaced at the landing site by the
    astronauts.  The instruments, connected by cables to a central
    station which controlled power and communications, ran
    autonomously.  Data collected was converted to a telemetry format
    and transmitted to Earth.  Many of these experiments returned data
    until September 1977, when the ALSEP network was turned off due to
    budgetary constraints.
 
    The Apollo 15 ALSEP instruments consisted of:
 
      - A Passive Seismometer, designed to measure seismic activity and
        physical properties of the lunar crust and interior;
 
      - A Lunar Surface Magnetometer, designed to measure the magnetic
        field at the ALSEP site;
 
      - A Solar Wind Spectrometer, designed to measure protons and
        electrons from the solar wind and magnetotail plasma impinging
        on the lunar surface;
 
      - A Suprathermal Ion Detector. Designed to measure positive ions
        reaching the lunar surface to provide data on the plasma
        interaction between the solar wind and the Moon;
 
      - A Heat Flow Experiment, designed to measure the rate of heat loss
        from the lunar interior and the thermal properties of lunar
        material;
 
      - A Cold Cathode Ion Gage, designed to measure the density of
        neutral particles in the tenuous lunar atmosphere;
 
      - A Laser Ranging Retroreflector, designed to reflect laser pulses
        from Earth back to their point of origin to make accurate
        determination of the distance between Earth and the Moon;
 
      - A Lunar Dust Detector, designed to assess the long-term effects
        of the lunar dust, radiation, and thermal environment on solar
       cells.
 
 
  Orbital Science Experiments
  ===========================
    Investigations were also carried out from lunar orbit in the Apollo
    15 Command and Service Module.  Hand-held photography was performed
    from the command module, and a suite of instruments operated from
    the Scientific Instrument Module (SIM) in the Service Module,
    comprising:
 
      - Metric and Panoramic cameras to take photographs of the lunar
        surface from orbit;
 
      - A Laser Altimeter using reflected laser pulses to profile the
        topography of lunar surface;
 
      - A Gamma-ray Spectrometer Experiment to measure gamma ray
        emissions from the lunar surface to determine composition;
 
      - An X-ray Fluorescence Spectrometer Experiment to measure
        secondary X-ray emissions from the lunar surface to determine
        composition;
 
      - An Alpha Particle Spectrometer Experiment to measure radon gas
        emissions from the lunar surface;
 
      - An S-Band Transponder Experiment designed to carefully track
        the CSM orbit and measure the lunar gravity field;
 
      - An Orbital Mass Spectrometer Experiment to study the tenuous
        lunar atmosphere and search for active lunar volcanism;
 
      - A Bistatic Radar Experiment used measurements of S-Band and VHF
        reflections to probe electromagnetic and structural properties
        of the lunar surface;
 
      - A Subsatellite released from the CSM into lunar orbit with
        instruments to measure the Moon&apos;s gravity field, magnetic
        field, and distribution of charged particles.
 
    Additional experiments were also performed in lunar orbit and
    during the cruise between Earth and the Moon:
 
      - The Ultraviolet Photography Experiment took images of Earth
        and the Moon in UV;
 
      - The Gegenschein Photography Experiment took images of the
        reflections from dust particles at the Moulton point;
 
      - The Window Meteoroid experiment studied micrometeoroid impacts
        on the Apollo 15 Command Module heat shield windows to obtain
        information about the mass flux of micro-meteorites;
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
