<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.mars_reconnaissance_orbiter</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MARS RECONNAISSANCE ORBITER</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>MRO</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>MRO</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.mro::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mars::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   unk
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.unk</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>MARS RECONNAISSANCE ORBITER</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>2005-08-12</start_date>
        <stop_date nilReason="unknown" xsi:nil="true"></stop_date>

        <description>
 
  Mission Overview
  ================
 
    The Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter spacecraft was launched from Cape
    Canaveral Air Force Station on 12 August 2005 aboard a Lockheed-Martin
    Atlas V-401 launch vehicle. After a five-month cruise and a two-month
    approach to Mars, MRO entered Mars&apos; orbit on 10 March 2006 and began
    aerobraking.  The primary science phase began on 8 November, 2006.
 
 
  Mission Phases
  ==============
 
    The Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter Mission is divided in time into seven
    phases: Launch, Cruise, Approach and Orbit Insertion, Aerobraking,
    Primary Science, Extended Science, and Relay.
 
    LAUNCH
    ------
      Launch extended from the start of the countdown to the initial
      acquisition, by the DSN, of the orbiter in a safe and stable
      configuration.
 
      The baseline launch vehicle for the MRO mission was the Lockheed-Martin
      Atlas V 401.  This launch vehicle was selected by NASA-KSC (Kennedy
      Space Flight Center) via a competitive procurement under the NASA
      Launch Services (NLS) contract.  The Atlas V 401 was a two-stage
      launch vehicle consisting of the Atlas Common Core Booster and a
      single engine Centaur upper stage.  The Centaur upper stage could
      perform multiple restarts of its main engine.  For precise pointing and
      control during coast and powered flight, the Centaur used a flight
      control system that was 3-axis stabilized. The Atlas large payload
      fairing was used to protect MRO during the Atlas boost phase.  This
      fairing had a diameter of 4.2m and a length of 12.2m.
 
      The launch and injection of MRO occured during the Mars opportunity
      of August 2005. The Atlas booster, in combination with the Centaur
      upper stage, delivered the MRO spacecraft into a targeted parking
      orbit. After a short coast, a restart of the Centaur upper stage
      injected MRO onto an interplanetary transfer trajectory.
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2005-08-12
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2005-08-12
 
    CRUISE
    ------
      Duration: About five months. The cruise phase extended from DSN
      initial acquisition, in a safe and stable configuration, until two
      months prior to the Mars Orbit Insertion (MOI) maneuver. Primary
      activities during cruise included spacecraft and payload checkout and
      calibration.  These activities, along with daily monitoring of orbiter
      subsystems, were performed in order to fully characterize the
      performance of the spacecraft and its payload prior to arrival at
      Mars.  In addition, standard navigation activities were performed
      during this flight phase, the first being the largest TCM performed
      fifteen days after launch.
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2005-08-12
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2006-01-10
 
    APPROACH AND ORBIT INSERTION
    ----------------------------
      This phase extended from two months prior to Mars Orbit Insertion
      (MOI), through MOI, and until the orbiter was checked out and ready to
      begin aerobraking. The orbiter was inserted into a nearly polar orbit
      with a period of 35 hours.
 
      During the last sixty days of the interplanetary transit, spacecraft
      and ground activities were focused on the events necessary for a
      successful arrival and safe capture at Mars. Navigation techniques
      included the use of delta-DOR measurements in the orbit determination.
      This technique yielded a precise determination of the inbound
      trajectory with a series of final TCMs used to control the flight path
      of the spacecraft up to the MOI maneuver.
 
      Also during the approach phase, MRO performed the Optical Navigation
      experiment.  This involved pointing the optical navigation camera
      (ONC) at the moons of Mars - Phobos and Deimos, and tracking their
      motion. By comparing the observed position of the moons to their
      predicted positions, relative to the background stars, the ground was
      able to accurately determine the position of the orbiter.
 
      Upon arrival at Mars on March 10, 2006, the spacecraft performed its
      MOI maneuver using its six main engines.  MOI inserted the spacecraft
      into an initial, highly elliptical capture orbit.  The delta-V
      required to accomplish this critical maneuver was 1015 m/s and took
      about 26 minutes to complete. For most of the burn, the orbiter was
      visible from the DSN stations.  The signal was occulted as the orbiter
      went behind Mars, and appeared again a short time later. The reference
      MRO capture orbit had a period of 35 hours and a periapsis altitude of
      300km.  The orientation of the ascending node was 8:30 PM LMST.  The
      capture orbit was been selected such that aerobraking would be
      completed prior to the start of solar conjunction (September 23,
      2006).
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2006-01-10
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2006-03-10
 
 
    AEROBRAKING
    -----------
      The Aerobraking Phase of the mission consisted of three sub-phases,
      Aerobraking Operations, Transition to PSO Operations, and Solar
      Conjunction.
 
      Aerobraking Operations Sub-Phase
      --------------------------------
 
      One week after MOI, aerobraking operations commenced.  During this
      time period, the orbiter used aerobraking techniques to supplement its
      onboard propulsive capability and to reduce its orbit period to that
      necessary for the primary science orbit (PSO).  Aerobraking Operations
      consisted of a walk-in phase, a main phase, and a walkout phase, and
      was followed by a transition to the PSO.  During the walk-in phase, the
      spacecraft established initial contact with the atmosphere as the
      periapsis altitude of the orbit was slowly lowered.  The walk-in phase
      continued until the dynamic pressures and heating rate values required
      for main phase, or steady state aerobraking, were established.  During
      the main phase of aerobraking operations, large scale orbit period
      reduction occurred as the orbiter was guided to dynamic pressure
      limits. Main phase aerobraking continued until the orbit lifetime of
      the orbiter reached 2 days.  (Orbit lifetime is defined as the time it
      takes the apoapsis altitude of the orbit to decay to an altitude of
      300km.)  When the orbit lifetime of the orbiter reached 2 days, the
      walkout phase of aerobraking operations began.  During the walkout
      phase, the periapsis altitude of the orbit was slowly increased as the
      2 day orbit lifetime of the orbiter was maintained.  Once the orbit of
      the orbiter reached an apoapsis altitude of 450km, the orbiter
      terminated aerobraking by propulsively raising the periapsis of its
      orbit out of the atmosphere.
 
      Because the PSO had nodal orientation requirements, the aerobraking
      phase of the MRO mission had to proceed in a timely manner and be
      completed near the time the desired nodal geometry was achieved. After
      approximately 4.5 months of aerobraking, the dynamic pressure control
      limits were reset such that the orbiter will fly to the desired 3:00
      pm LMST nodal target.
 
      Transition to PSO Operations Sub-Phase
      --------------------------------------
 
      Once the orbit apoapsis altitude was reduced to 450 km, the orbiter
      terminated aerobraking by raising periapsis to a safe altitude and
      begin a transition to the Primary Science Phase.  The periapsis of
      the transition orbit rotated around Mars from over the equatorial
      latitudes to the North Pole.  When periapsis reached the North Pole,
      apoapsis was reduced propulsively to 255 km and orbit rotation stopped
      - the orbit was frozen with periapsis over the South Pole and apoapsis
      over the North Pole.  The SHARAD antenna and the CRISM cover were
      deployed, the instruments were checked out and remaining calibrations
      were performed.  The payloads collected data in their normal operating
      modes to ensure that the end-to-end data collection and processing
      systems worked as planned.
 
      Solar Conjuction Sub-Phase
      --------------------------
 
      Orbiter activities in preparation for science were then temporarily
      suspended during a four week period surrounding solar conjunction.
 
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2006-03-17
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2006-11-07
 
      Aerobraking Operations Sub-Phase Start Time: 2006-03-17
      Aerobraking Operations Sub-Phase Stop Time: 2006-09-15
 
      Transition to PSO Operations Sub-Phase Start Time: 2006-09-15
      Transition to PSO Operations Sub-Phase Stop Time: 2006-10-09
 
      Solar Conjunction Sub-Phase Start Time: 2006-10-09
      Solar Conjunction Sub-Phase Stop Time: 2006-11-07
 
 
    PRIMARY SCIENCE
    ---------------
      The 255 x 320 km Primary Science Orbit (PSO) was a near-polar orbit
      with periapsis frozen over the South Pole.  It was sun-synchronous with
      an ascending node orientation that provided a Local Mean Solar Time
      (LMST) of 3:00 p.m. at the equator.  Because of the eccentricity of
      the Mars orbit around the Sun, true solar time varied by nearly 45
      minutes over the course of one Mars year.
 
      The Primary Science Phase of the mission began after solar conjunction
      and after turn-on and checkout of the science instruments in the
      Primary Science Orbit.  The phase started on 8 November 2006 and
      extended for about one Mars year, through December 19, 2008.
 
      The science investigations were functionally divided into daily global
      mapping and profiling, regional survey, and globally distributed
      targeting investigations.  The global mapping instruments were the MCS
      and the MARCI.  The targeted investigations were HiRISE, CRISM, and
      CTX. The survey investigations were CRISM and CTX (in survey modes),
      and SHARAD.  The global mapping instruments required nadir pointing,
      low data rate, and continuous or near-continuous operations.  The
      global mapping investigations were expected to use less than 5% of the
      expected downlink data volume.  The targeted and survey instruments
      were high data rate instruments and required precise targeting in
      along-track timing and/or cross-track pointing for short periods of
      time over selected portions of the surface.  More than 95% of the
      available downlink data volume was expected to be used for
      targeted and survey investigations. All instruments were able to take
      data simultaneously.
 
      The Phoenix lander arrived at Mars on May 25, 2008. Phoenix used
      MRO to characterize its prime landing site choices early in the
      Primary Science Phase. MRO also provided relay support for Entry,
      Descent, and Landing (EDL) activities and for telecommunications late
      in the PSP after Phoenix arrived at Mars.
      Phoenix and MRO also coordinated some observations to maximize
      science return to the Mars Exploration Program.
 
      NASA may approve, as resources and on-orbit capability permit,
      continuation of science observations beyond the Primary Science Phase
      until end of the Relay Phase (also End of Mission).  The orbiter will
      remain in the Primary Science Orbit during the Relay Phase.
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2006-11-08
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2008-12-19
 
 
    EXTENDED SCIENCE
    ---------------
      NASA approved continuation of science observations after the Primary
      Science Phase ended. MRO operations are continuing in the Extended
      Science Phase, which is funded for another Mars year. MRO carries
      enough fuel to continue operating for several more years.
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2008-12-20
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : 2010-12-19
 
 
    RELAY
    -----
      MRO provides critical relay support to missions launched as part
      of the Mars Exploration Program after MRO.  For spacecraft launched in
      the 2007 opportunity, this relay support occurred before the end of
      the MRO Primary Science Phase.   Following completion of the Primary
      and Extended Science Phases, MRO will continue to provide critical
      relay support for Mars missions until its end of mission.
 
      The Phoenix lander arrived at Mars on May 25, 2008. MRO provided
      science imaging support for site characterization and selection
      and relay support for Phoenix Entry,
      Descent and Landing activities and for its science data return.
      Another mission, the Mars Science Laboratory (MSL) was originally
      proposed for the 2009 Mars launch opportunity but has been delayed
      until the 2011 opportunity.  MSL will also need science imaging support
      for site characterization and selection and relay support for EDL and
      science data return.  The MRO Mission Plan describes the generic
      support activities for any mission as well as current early planning
      in support of Phoenix and MSL.
 
      The orbiter has been designed to carry enough propellant to remain
      operational for 5 years beyond the end-of-mission (EOM) on December
      31, 2010 to support future MEP missions.  As this is beyond the EOM,
      no activities have been planned for this time period.  To ensure that
      the orbiter remains in a viable orbit during this time, its orbit
      altitude will be increased at EOM to about 20 km inside the orbit of
      the Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft.
 
      The MRO approach to planetary protection differs from any previous
      Mars orbiter.  The NASA requirements for planetary protection,
      NPG8020.12B, allow a class III mission, like MRO, to use either the
      &apos;probability of impact/orbit lifetime&apos; or a &apos;total bio burden&apos;
      approach.  Implementing the Level 1 MRO requirements with the
      instruments selected via the NASA AO requires low orbits whose
      lifetimes are incompatible with a &apos;probability of impact/orbit
      lifetime&apos; approach to Planetary Protection.  Therefore, MRO is
      implementing the requirements of NPG8020.12B using the &apos;total
      bio-burden&apos; approach.  This approach has been documented in the MRO
      Planetary Protection Plan (D-23711). The details of cleaning
      requirements are documented in the MRO Planetary Protection
      Implementation Plan, MRO 212-11, JPL D-22688. The MRO launch targets
      will be biased away from a direct intercept course with Mars to ensure
      a less than 1 in 10,000 chance of the launch vehicle upper stage
      entering Mars atmosphere.
 
      The End-of-Mission (EOM) is planned for December 31, 2010 just prior
      to the third solar conjunction of the mission.  The orbiter will
      perform a propulsive maneuver to place itself in a higher orbit to
      increase the orbit lifetime and enable extended mission operations.
 
      Mission Phase Start Time : 2010-12-20
      Mission Phase Stop Time  : to be determined
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
