<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.deep_space_1</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.1</version_id>
        <title>DEEP SPACE 1</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2019-01-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.1</version_id>
                <description>
                    Per "Guide toPDS4 Context Products" v1.3,
                    - changed all lidvid_reference to lid_reference
                    - changed target LIDs to new formation rule
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.ds1</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:comet.19p_borrelly</lid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Rayman, M.D., The Successful Conclusion of the Deep Space 1 Mission: Important
                   Results without a Flashy Title, 53rd International Astronautical Congress/World
                   Space Congress, Houston, TX, IAC-02-Q.5.2.03, 10-19 October, 2002.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.RAYMAN2002</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>DEEP SPACE 1</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>1998-10-24</start_date>
        <stop_date>2001-12-18</stop_date>

        <description>
 
The text below is summarized from
      the the New Millennium Project Technology Validation Reports for
      Deep Space 1 with permission of the web site NASA Responsible
      official, C.W. Minning.
 
  Mission Overview
  ================
    The primary goal of the DS1 mission was to validate advanced, high
    risk technologies that are important for future space and Earth
    science programs.  Secondary goals were scientific in nature, and
    included obtaining images, spectra  and particles and fields
    measurements of a near-Earth asteroid and a comet.
 
    Deep Space 1 was launched from Pad 17-A at the Cape Canaveral Air
    Station at 12:08 UT (8:08 a.m. EDT), 24 October 1998, the first
    launch under NASA&apos;s Med-Lite booster program, on a Delta 7326-9.5
    (a Delta II Lite launch vehicle with three strap-on solid-rocket
    boosters and a Star 37FM third stage). At 13:01 UT the third stage
    burn put DS1 into its solar orbit trajectory. DS1 separated from
    the Delta II about 550 km above the Indian Ocean. Telemetry was
    received by the NASA Deep Space Network 1 hour, 37 minutes after
    launch, a 13 minute delay from the expected time. The reason for
    the delay is not known.
 
    DS1 flew by the near-Earth asteroid 9969 Braille (1999 K2) at
    04:46 UT (12:46 a.m. EDT) on 29 July 1999 at a distance of about
    26 km at approximately 15.5 km/sec relative velocity. A software
    problem caused the spacecraft to go into a safing mode at
    approximately 12:00 UT on 28 July, but the problem was solved and
    the spacecraft returned to normal operations at 18:00 UT. Up to
    six minor trajectory correction maneuvers were scheduled in the 48
    hours prior to the flyby. The spacecraft made its final pre-
    encounter transmission about 7 hours before closest approach,
    after which it turned its high-gain antenna away from Earth to
    point the MICAS camera/spectrometer camera towards the asteroid.
    The spacecraft had a target-tracking problem and the MICAS
    instrument was not pointed towards the asteroid as it approached,
    so no images or spectra were obtained. MICAS turned off about 25
    seconds before closest approach at a distance of about 350 km and
    measurements were taken with the PEPE plasma instrument. The
    spacecraft then turned after the encounter to obtain images and
    spectra of the opposite side of the asteroid as it receded from
    view, but due to the target-tracking problem only two black and
    white images and a dozen spectra were obtained. The images were
    taken at 915 and 932 seconds after closest approach from 14,000 km
    and the spectra were taken about 3 minutes later. The data were
    transmitted back to Earth over the next few days. The diameter of
    Braille is estimated at 2.2 km at its longest and 1 km at its
    shortest. The spectra showed it to be similar to the asteroid
    Vesta.
 
    The primary mission lasted until 18 September 1999, after which
    the spacecraft entered an extended mission phase.  Early in this
    phase, the commercial star tracker failed, leaving the craft
    unable to point its main antenna toward Earth or operate its ion
    propulsion system.  A two-phase approach allowed recovery of the
    mission. First, ground crews devised a new method of pointing the
    high-gain antenna at the Earth, so the radio signal received at
    the Deep Space Network could be used as an indicator of the
    spacecraft attitude. Second, new software was developed to allow
    the science camera to perform the duties of the star tracker,
    allowing the spacecraft to return to three-axis operation and
    continue its mission.
 
    DS1 flew by Comet 19P/Borrelly at 22:30 UT on 22 September 2001 (8
    days after the comet&apos;s perihelion).  The flyby occurred at a
    distance of 2171 km with approximately 16.58 km/sec relative
    velocity.  At the time, 19P/Borrelly was 1.36 AU from the sun and
    1.48 AU from the Earth.  Three different types of science data
    were obtained during the encounter: The miniature integrated
    camera and spectrometer (MICAS) obtained both optical (0.5 to 1.0
    microns) images, and spectra from 1.3 to 2.6 microns, and the
    Plasma Experiment for Planetary Exploration (PEPE) obtained
    measurements of the ion and electron energy and ion mass to charge
    ratios.  The images obtained near closest approach represent the
    highest resolution images of a comet&apos;s nucleus to date.
 
 
  Mission Phases
  ==============
    DS1 Mission Timeline
 
     Launch (Cape Canaveral, Florida):      24 Oct 1998
     Instrument verification completed:     13 Jul 1999
     Asteroid Braille (1992 K2) encounter:  28 Jul 1999
     End of primary mission:                18 Sep 1999
     Coast period (MICAS observes Mars):    20 Oct 1999
     Star tracker failure:                  11 Nov 1999
     Comet Borrelly encounter:              22 Sep 2001
     Deep Space 1 retired:                  18 Dec 2001
 
    Launch:
 
    Following launch, several days were spent conducting an evaluation
    of the spacecraft, verifying its health and preparing it for
    mission operations.   Dedicated technology experiments began
    within a week of launch.  Of course, some technologies were used
    as part of regular spacecraft operations, in particular the solar
    array, transponder, and AuotNav, but those and all other
    technologies also were subjected to in depth characterization
    tests.   Radiometric determination of the trajectory was combined
    with results of the IPS tests to generate and optimize an updated
    low-thrust trajectory that was transmitted to the spacecraft.
    After verification of its functional capability, AutoNav was tuned
    in flight, particularly to account for discrepancies between the
    predicted and the actual MICAS images.   As the mission
    progressed, more reliance was placed on AutoNav, with conventional
    navigation used to validate its performance.  After ten days of
    thrusting, the spacecraft was turned to thrust along the vector
    (subject to a variety of constraints) for reaching the encounter
    targets for the primary and extended mission.
 
    Cruise 1:
 
    In February 1999, a completely new software load of 4.1 MB was
    installed. This new software enabled the testing of four of the
    previously excluded technologies (the software package remote
    agent was not in this load), upgraded AutoNav (to accommodate
    scattered light in the MICAS images), fixed bugs identified after
    launch and improved spacecraft operability.  To accommodate the
    remote agent experiments in May, the flight software was patched
    and remote agent software was uploaded. In June, following the
    remote agent experiment, the flight software was replaced again.
    This last load contained new operational enhancements and upgrades
    to a number of systems, including AutoNav upgrades for enhanced
    image processing and functions needed to execute encounters.
 
    The thrusting for the primary mission was accomplished in two
    major periods. The brief hiatus in the thrust arc was inserted to
    allow days for activation and initial testing of PEPE in the
    absence of the IPS plasma, and experiments incompatible with the
    IPS thrust attitude. The second thrust segment ended on April 27,
    1999.
 
    Braille Encounter:
 
    All the technology testing was completed by July 1999.  Following
    the end of the testing, on July 29, 1999, the DS1 spacecraft
    encountered (9969) 1992 KD at 15.5 km/s. As a result, the closest
    approach to Braille was 28.3 +/- km rather than the planned 15 km.
    The asteroid is believed to be elongated with a mean radius of
    roughly 2 km and is the smallest solar system body targeted by
    DS1. During the final days of the spacecraft&apos;s approach to the
    body, AutoNav did lock onto the asteroid but the accuracy was not
    high.
 
    Cruise 2:
 
    Following the encounter with Braille, DS1 had months of thrusting
    until the primary mission ended on Sept 18, 1999.  When DS1 was
    launched, the plan for the primary mission incorporated a plan for
    an extended mission taking the spacecraft to comet Borrelly.  The
    extension was approved by NASA in August 1999.  Most of the
    extended mission would be devoted to IPS thrusting.  On Oct 20
    1999, a coast period began which lasted through mid-December 1999
    during which calibrations of all MICAS channels were conducted.
    On November 11, 1999, after all the Mars infrared spectra were
    taken, the spacecraft&apos;s stellar reference unit (SRU) stopped
    reporting attitude data to the spacecraft computer.   On June 21,
    2000, the IPS thrusting was restarted under routine operations.
 
    Borrelly Encounter:
 
    Following its primary mission, DS1 embarked on an extended mission
    devoted to comet science.   In November 1999, the spacecraft had
    suffered the loss if its stellar reference unit (SRU), its source
    of 3-axis attitude knowledge.   This was considered to be
    catastrophic, but the operations team completed an ambitious two-
    phase, 7-month recovery that included the development of new
    software and new methods for operating the spacecraft.
 
    One feature of the recovery was to use the visible CCD camera in
    the miniature integrated camera/spectrometer (MICAS), one of the
    technologies tested during the primary mission, as an attitude
    sensor. The problem of navigating to the vicinity of the comet was
    different from that of reaching a typical planetary encounter,
    because the uncertainty in the comet&apos;s ephemeris dominated
    navigation errors. From 25 August to 10 hours before the closest
    approach to September 22, DS1 conducted 11 imaging sessions
    spanning ranges to the comet of 40.3 x 10^6 km to 6 x 10^5 km.
 
    On approach to Borrelly, DS1 viewed the comet near the south
    ecliptic pole.   The spacecraft&apos;s  approach of 2171 km was at
    22:29:33 UTC on 22 September 2001, with v(inf) = 16.58 km/s.  The
    encounter took place 1.36 AU from the Sun, 8 days after
    perihelion.
 
    Science data were acquired with 3 instrument suites. All were
    body- fixed, so pointing required spacecraft maneuvers. MICAS&apos;
    1024 x 1024 CCD with 13-micro-rad pixels collected images in the
    range of 0.5 to 1.0 micrometer. MICAS also obtained spectra from
    1.3 to 2.6 micrometers with a sampling interval of 7 nm. Ion and
    electron energy and angle spectra and ion mass/charge measurements
    were made with an instrument included on the flight, the plasma
    experiment for planetary exploration (PEPE). Over its 2.8pi sr
    field of view, PEPE was sensitive between 8 eV and 32 keV, with a
    resolution of 5% (energy and mass/charge). Magnetic field and
    plasma wave measurements were made with sensors that had been
    carried as an assessment of the IPS. These IPS diagnostic sensors
    (IDS) measured the effects of the IPS on the spacecraft and space
    environment during the primary mission and were reprogrammed in
    flight to collect cometary science data.
 
    Cruise 3 (HYPEREXTENDED MISSION):
 
    The return of the data from Borrelly concluded DS1&apos;s two-year
    extended mission.   The spacecraft was undamaged by the encounter
    and continued operating after the extended mission.
 
    DS1&apos;s hyperextended mission included testing eight of the
    technologies onboard, with a focus on the IPS. On 18 December
    2001, following the last IPS test and the dumping of some final
    data, a command was sent to place the spacecraft in one of its
    safe states, now with the downlink off. This last command product
    was the 9905th of the mission.
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
