<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.giotto_extended_mission</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>GIOTTO EXTENDED MISSION</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>GEM</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>GEM</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.gio::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
<!--        <Internal_Reference> -->
<!--            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:comet.26p-grigg-skjellerup_1_1922_k1::1.0</lidvid_reference> -->
<!--            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type> -->
<!--        </Internal_Reference> -->
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   The Giotto Mission, R. Reinhard and B. Battrick, ESA SP-1077, ESA Pub Div,
                   Noordwijk, Netherlands, 1986.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ESA-SP1077</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Images of the Nucleus of Comet Halley, R. Reinhard, N. Longdon, and B. Battrick
                   (eds), ESA SP-1127, Vol 1, ESA Pub Div, Noordwijk, Netherlands, 1992.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.ESA-SP1127</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Grensemann, M.G. and G. Schwehm, ESA&apos;s Report to the 30th Cospar Meeting, July
                   1994.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.GRENSEMANN-SCHWE1994</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>GIOTTO EXTENDED MISSION</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>1990</start_date>
        <stop_date>1992</stop_date>

        <description>
 
      Giotto was launched on 2 July, 1985, at 11:23:16 UTC aboard an
      Ariane-1. The mission reached fruition 8 months later during the
      night of 13-14 March, 1986, when Giotto passed comet Halley at a
      distance of less than 596 km of the nucleus, making spectacular
      images of the nucleus.
 
      Giotto was not expected to survive the passage through the cometary
      dust surrounding Halley, where particles would strike the spacecraft
      with an explosive force 50 times that of a bullet.  However, after
      passing Halley, the spacecraft still appeared to be functioning quite
      well.
 
      It was decided to continue payload operation until the early morning
      of 14 March, and to make an additional science pass during the night
      of 14/15 March.  It was found that the magnetometer (MAG), the optical
      probe experiment (OPE), the energetic particles analyzer (EPA), and
      the particulate impact analyzer (PIA) were working nominally; the
      Johnstone plasma analyzer (JPA) and the dust impact detector system had
      lost some of their measuring capabilities but could still provide more
      than 60% of their scientific data.  The ion mass spectrometer (IMS) had
      lost one measurement channel (HERS, the high energy range spectrometer,
      optimized for measurements in the outer coma), but the high intensity
      spectrometer (HIS) optimized for measurements in the inner coma had
      survived the encounter.  The Reme plasma analyzer (RPA) seemed to be
      severely damaged;  only its electron electrostatic analyzer (EESA)
      could still provide sufficient scientific data to permit determination
      of electron spatial density.
 
      In February 1990 the long process of reactivation was started, as
      Giotto made its approach towards Earth.  The spacecraft had been
      dormant for 4 years, had been subjected to cyclic extremes of
      temperature and was in an unknown attitude, one, more over that
      precluded communication via its high gain antenna (HGA).  There was
      only one way to communicate with Giotto and that was via the
      omni-directional low gain antenna (LGA) mounted on the top of the
      spacecraft.
 
      Once experiment checkout had been completed, the Control Centre made
      preparations for directing the spacecraft towards comet
      Grigg-Skjellerup. This was no ordinary maneuver, as Earth&apos;s
      gravitational field was to provide the kick needed to bring Giotto
      into the otherwise unreachable orbit.  At 10:00 UT on 2 July, 1990,
      exactly 5 years after its launch, and with the MAG and EPA activated,
      Giotto flew over Earth at an altitude of 22 000 km and made space
      history once again.
 
      After this activity, Giotto was put into its second hibernation which
      would last until the spacecraft was reactivated again on 4 May, 1992
      for its mission to comet P/Grigg-Skjellerup.  At that time the
      spacecraft to Earth range was 219 x 10**6 km. The operations with
      Giotto, who&apos;s health showed no further degradation since 1990 continued
      without problems, concentrating on guiding the spacecraft as close as
      possible toward its new target.
 
      Two orbit-control maneuvers were performed:  the first on 22 May,
      reducing the predicted flyby distance from 167 400 km to 510 km.  The
      final maneuver was performed on July 8, reducing the expected flyby
      distance to near zero.
 
      During actual encounter phase on 10 July, 1992 there were no problems.
      The science data processed in real time at European Space Operations
      Centre (ESOC) provided immediate access to the cometary environment.
 
      At 03:00 on 11 July, 1992 all experiments were switched-off.  After a
      period of seven years in orbit around the Sun, Giotto operations were
      officially terminated on 23 July 1992, after the completion of final
      orbit adjustments and after configuring the spacecraft for its third
      hibernation.
 
      In its present trajectory course, Giotto will pass 219 000 km above the
      Earth&apos;s surface on 1 July 1999, 14 years after the spacecraft&apos;s launch.
      Future operation of the spacecraft is considered doubtful, partly
      because the fuel remaining (4 +/- 3 kg) is insufficient for anything
      more than an Earth or Moon fly-by in 1999, and partly because of the
      age by then of both the spacecraft itself and the ground systems used
      to support the GEM mission.
 
      Spacecraft ID              : GIO
      Target name                : GRIGG-SKJELLERUP
      Spacecraft Operations Type : FLYBY
 
      Mission Phases
      ==============
 
      Launch
      ------
      The Giotto spacecraft was launched on July 2,
      1985 onboard an Ariane-1 rocket from Kourou, French Guyana.
 
      Mission phase start time: 1985-07-02
      Mission phase stop time:  1985-07-02
 
 
      Reactivation
      ------------
      In February 1990 the long process of reactivation was started, as
      Giotto made its approach towards Earth.  The spacecraft had been
      dormant for 4 years, had been subjected to cyclic extremes of
      temperature and was in an unknown attitude, one, more over that
      precluded communication via its high gain antenna (HGA).  There was
      only one way to communicate with Giotto and that was via the
      omni-directional low gain antenna (LGA) mounted on the top of the
      spacecraft.
 
      Two hours after the start of the reactivation activities, the NASA
      Deep Space Network Station at Madrid reported acquisition of a weak
      signal (-166 dBm), and about 150 hours after starting, full control
      of the spacecraft was established through the HGA and Giotto again
      performed beyond its design envelope.
 
      From the spacecraft telemetry data received and analyzed, it was
      evident that Giotto had survived its odyssey through space extremely
      well.  A check of the payload concluded, with a high degree of
      confidence, that the hibernation period had not caused any further
      degradation in instrument performances and that a viable payload
      remained to support another cometary encounter.
 
      Once experiment checkout had been completed, the Control Centre made
      preparations for directing the spacecraft towards comet
      Grigg-Skjellerup. This was no ordinary maneuver, as Earth&apos;s
      gravitational field was to provide the kick needed to bring Giotto
      into the otherwise unreachable orbit.  At 10:00 UT on 2 July, 1990,
      exactly 5 years after its launch, and with the MAG and EPA activated,
      Giotto flew over Earth at an altitude of 22 000 km and made space
      history once again.
 
      After this activity, Giotto was put into its second hibernation.
 
      The second reactivation of the Giotto spacecraft had been scheduled
      for 4 May 1992. At 16:55 h local time, the first commands were sent
      from the European Space Operations Centre (ESOC) in Darmstadt, Germany,
      via NASA&apos;s Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena (Calif.), to the 70 m
      Deep-Space Network (DSN) ground station in Madrid, Spain, for uplinking
      to Giotto. At that time, the space probe was 219 million kilometres
      from Earth.
 
      The commands sent were the first in an extensive series designed to
      awaken Giotto from its hibernation configuration. To ensure reception
      of the signals by the tiny omnidirectional antenna on the top of the
      spacecraft, the DSN&apos;s most powerful 95 kW transmitter had to be used.
 
      The spacecraft was configured to allow the transmitter connected to
      the Low-Gain Antenna to be turned on. At 18:14 h local time, the Madrid
      ground station reported the reception of a downlink carrier with a
      signal strength of -171 dBm, as predicted by the ESOC Operations Team.
      Giotto was back, again at the first attempt, just as in 1990 after its
      first period of hibernation! Once again, Giotto had lived up to the
      confidence that the Project and Operations Teams had placed in it.
      Only the waiting required was a little nerve-racking, because the
      remoteness of the spacecraft from Earth meant that one had to wait
      nearly half an hour for the spacecraft&apos;s response to a command to be
      seen on the ground!
 
      A series of &apos;blind&apos; maneuvers were subsequently performed to orient
      Giotto so that its High-Gain Antenna (HGA) pointed towards Earth and
      telemetry could be received.  This was accomplished on 7 May 1992,
      when good telemetry was received continuously. At this point, the
      Giotto reactivation effort could be truly declared a success!
 
 
      Mission phase start time:  1990-02-19
      Mission phase stop time:   1992-07-09
 
 
      Flyby
      -----
 
      There were a number of features of the comet Grigg-Skjellerup encounter
      that were most unlike those at encounter with Halley:
 
      (1) Grigg-Skjellerup would approach Giotto at an angle of 68 degrees
          instead of head-on as at Halley: hence the bumper shield would
          afford no protection.
 
      (2) The relative velocity was 14 km/s, with the comet meeting Giotto
          from below and behind, whereas Halley had met Giotto head-on at
          68 km/s.
 
      (3) The Earth range at encounter was 214 x 10**6 km leading to a round-
          trip light time of 24 min.  At Halley, the range had been 140 x
          10**0 km and the round-trip light time was 16 min.
 
 
      The good navigation of Giotto was confirmed by the data obtained by the
      OPE, based on an analysis of the brightness increase of the sunlight
      scattered by the dust particles in the inner coma.  The closest
      approach was inferred to have occurred at a distance smaller than
      200 km, with the brightness peak recorded at 15:30:43 with an
      uncertainty of only 3 seconds.  At 03:00 on 11 July, 1992 all
      experiments were switched-off.
 
      Already at 03:00 UTC, more than 12 hours before the closest approach,
      the JPA detected the presence of cometary ions.  During the last hour
      before closest approach, after JPA confirmed the increase in the
      density of the ions, RPA, the EPA, and the IMS also reported detection
      of ions.  Meanwhile, periodic bit errors in telemetry were noticed at
      ESOC, causing occasional loss of data.
 
      At 15:20 the Optical Probe Experiment (OPE) could see cometary dust. At
      15:31:02, when the first housekeeping telemetry format was received
      after the major impact, the data showed the HGA to be oscillating
      slightly around its nominal value.  An increase in the spin rate by
      0.003 RPM was also observed while the solar aspect angle readings were
      fluctuating between 89.26 degrees and 89.45 degrees, indicating a
      nutation of about 0.1 degrees.  The small nutation of the spacecraft,
      experienced around closest approach, can be explained by the spacecraft
      being hit by one large dust particle of at least 30 mg effective mass,
      assuming that this particle struck on the upper end of the solar cell
      array.
 
      At 03:00 on 11 July, 1992 all experiments were switched-off.  After a
      period of seven years in orbit around the Sun, Giotto operations were
      officially terminated on 23 July 1992, after the completion of final
      orbit adjustments and after configuring the spacecraft for its third
      hibernation.
 
      In its present trajectory course, Giotto will pass 219 000 km above the
      Earth&apos;s surface on 1 July 1999, 14 years after the spacecraft&apos;s launch.
      Future operation of the spacecraft is considered doubtful, partly
      because the fuel remaining (4 +/- 3 kg) is insufficient for anything
      more than an Earth or Moon fly-by in 1999, and partly because of the
      age by then of both the spacecraft itself and the ground systems used
      to support the GEM mission.
 
      Mission phase start time: 1986-07-09
      Mission phase stop time:  1986-07-11
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
