<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.mariner_10</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>MARINER 10</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>MARINER_10</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>MARINER 10</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.m10::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.mercury::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:planet.venus::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:plasma_stream.solar_wind::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   unk
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.unk</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>MARINER 10</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>1973-11-03</start_date>
        <stop_date>1975-03-24</stop_date>

        <description>
 
  Mission Overview
  ================
 
    Mariner 10 was the seventh successful launch in the Mariner series
    and the first spacecraft to use the gravitational pull of one planet
    (Venus) to reach another (Mercury). The spacecraft flew by Mercury
    three times in a heliocentric orbit and returned images and data on
    the planet. Mariner 10 is the only spacecraft to have visited
    Mercury.
 
    Spacecraft and Subsystems
 
    The spacecraft structure was an eight-sided framework with eight
    electronics compartments. It measured 1.39 m diagonally and 0.457 m
    in depth. Two solar panels, each 2.7 m long and 0.97 m wide, were
    attached at the top, supporting 5.1 sq m of solar cell area. The
    rocket engine was liquid-fueled, with two sets of reaction jets used
    to stabilize the spacecraft on three axes. It carried a low-gain
    omnidirectional antenna, composed of a honeycomb-disk parabolic
    reflector, 1.37 m in diameter, with focal length 55 cm. Feeds
    enabled the spacecraft to transmit at S- and X-band frequencies. The
    spacecraft carried a Canopus star tracker, located on the upper ring
    structure of the octagonal satellite, and acquisition sun sensors on
    the tips of the solar panels. The interior of the spacecraft was
    insulated with multiplayer thermal blankets at top and bottom. A
    sunshade was deployed after launch to protect the spacecraft on the
    solar-oriented side.
 
    Instruments on-board the spacecraft measured the atmospheric,
    surface, and physical characteristics of Mercury and Venus.
    Experiments included television photography, magnetic field, plasma,
    infrared radiometry, ultraviolet spectroscopy, and radio science
    detectors. An experimental X-band, high-frequency transmitter was
    flown for the first time on this spacecraft.
 
    Mission Profile
 
    Mariner 10 was placed in a parking orbit after launch for
    approximately 25 minutes, then placed in orbit around the Sun en
    route to Venus. The orbit direction was opposite to the motion of
    the Earth around the Sun. Mid-course corrections were made. The
    spacecraft passed Venus on February 5, 1974, at a distance of 4200
    km. It crossed the orbit of Mercury on March 29, 1974, at 2046 UT,
    at a distance of about 703 km from the surface. The TV and UV
    experiments were turned on the comet Kohoutek while the spacecraft
    was on the way to Venus. A second encounter with Mercury, when more
    photographs were taken, occurred on September 21, 1974, at an
    altitude of about 47,000 km. A third and last Mercury encounter at
    an altitude of 327 km, with additional photography of about 300
    photographs and magnetic field measurements occurred on March 16,
    1975. Engineering tests were continued until March 24, 1975, when
    the supply of attitude-control gas was depleted and the mission was
    terminated.
 
    Total research, deployment, launch, and support costs for the
    Mariner series of spacecraft (Mariners 1 through 10) was
    approximately $554 million.
 
 
  Mission Phases
  ==============
 
      EARTH VENUS CRUISE
      ------------------
      The Earth-Venus cruise period is defined as spanning the time
      between launch and 3 days before Venus closest approach.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : SOLAR WIND
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1973-11-03
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1974-02-01T23:59:59.999Z
 
      VENUS ENCOUNTER
      ---------------
      The Venus encounter period is defined as spanning 6 days about
      Venus closest approach. Closest approach to Venus occurred at
      1974-02-05 17:01:50 UT.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : VENUS
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1974-02-02T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1974-02-08T23:59:59.999Z
 
      VENUS MERCURY CRUISE
      --------------------
      The Venus-Mercury cruise period is defined as spanning the time
      between 3 days after Venus encouter and 3 days before Mercury
      closest approach.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : SOLAR WIND
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1974-02-09T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1974-03-26T23:59:59.999Z
 
      MERCURY ENCOUNTER I
      -------------------
      The first Mercury encounter period is defined as spanning 6 days
      about Mercury closest approach. Closest approach to Mercury
      occurred 1974-03-29 20:46:38 UT at an altitude of 703 km.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : MERCURY
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1974-03-27T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1974-04-02T23:59:59.999Z
 
      MERCURY MERCURY CRUISE I
      ------------------------
      The Mercury-Mercury cruise period is defined as spanning the time
      between 3 days before Mercury Encounter I and 3 days before
      Mercury Encounter II.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : SOLAR WIND
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1974-04-03T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1974-09-17T23:59:59.999Z
 
      MERCURY ENCOUNTER II
      --------------------
      The second Mercury encounter period is defined as spanning 6 days
      about Mercury closest approach. Closest approach occurred
      1974-09-21 21:59:00 at an altitude of 47,000 km.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : MERCURY
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1974-09-18T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1974-09-24T23:59:59.999Z
 
      MERCURY MERCURY CRUISE II
      -------------------------
      The Mercury-Mercury cruise period is defined as spanning the time
      between 3 days before Mercury Encounter II and 3 days before
      Mercury Encounter III.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : SOLAR WIND
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1974-09-25T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1975-03-12T23:59:59.999Z
 
      MERCURY ENCOUNTER III
      ---------------------
      The third and last Mercury encounter period is defined as spanning
      6 days about Mercury closest approcah. Closest approach occurred
      1975-03-16 22:39:23 at an altitude of 327 km.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : MERCURY
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1975-03-13T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1975-03-19T23:59:59.999Z
 
      END OF MISSION CRUISE
      ---------------------
      The end of mission cruise period is defined as spanning the time
      between 3 days after Mercury Encounter III and when the mission
      was terminated.
 
      Spacecraft Id                  : M10
      Target Name                    : SOLAR WIND
      Mission Phase Start Time       : 1975-03-20T00:00:00.000Z
      Mission Phase Stop Time        : 1975-03-24T23:59:59.999Z
 
  References
  ==========
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
