<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1700.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:mission.apollo_17</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>APOLLO 17</title>
        <information_model_version>1.7.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Alias_List>
            <Alias>
                <alternate_id>A17</alternate_id>
                <alternate_title>A17</alternate_title>
            </Alias>
        </Alias_List>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2016-10-01</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    extracted metadata from PDS3 catalog and
                    modified to comply with PDS4 Information Model
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a17a::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:instrument_host:spacecraft.a17l::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_instrument_host</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <Internal_Reference>
            <lidvid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:target:satellite.moon::1.0</lidvid_reference>
            <reference_type>investigation_to_target</reference_type>
        </Internal_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Apollo 17 Preliminary Science Report, NASA SP-330, published by NASA,
                   Washington, D.C., 1973.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.APOLLO17A1973</description>
        </External_Reference>
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                   Davies, M.E., and T.R. Colvin, Lunar coordinates in the regions of the Apollo
                   landers, Journal of Geophysical Research, Volume 105, Issue E8, pages
                   20,227-20,280, 2000, doi:10.1029/1999JE001165.
            </reference_text>
            <description>reference.DAVIES-COLVIN2000</description>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>APOLLO 17</name>
        <type>Mission</type>
        <start_date>1972-12-07</start_date>
        <stop_date>1972-12-19</stop_date>

        <description>
 
 
  Mission Overview
  ================
    Apollo 17 was launched on 7 December 1972 UT 5:33:00 on a Saturn V
    rocket from Kennedy Space Center.  Lunar orbit insertion took place on
    10 December 1972 UT 19:47:23.  The Lunar Module (LM) landed on the Moon
    on 11 December 1972 UT 19:54:57, on the southeastern rim of Mare
    Serenitatis in a valley at Taurus-Littrow (20.19 North longitude,
    30.77 East latitude [DAVIES&amp;COLVIN2000]), while the Command/Service
    Module (CSM) orbited the Moon.  The lunar ascent module launched from
    the Moon on 14 December 1972 UT 22:54:37.  The command module was
    returned to Earth on 19 December 1972 UT 19:24:59.  Apollo 17 was the
    final lunar landing mission in NASA&apos;s Apollo program.
 
    The astronauts on Apollo 17 were commander Eugene Cernan, command module
    pilot Ronald Evans, and lunar module pilot Harrison Schmitt.  Three
    excursions, using the Lunar Roving Vehicle (LRV), lasted a total of 22
    hours, 4 minutes and traversed 35.7 km.  The lunar surface stay-time was
    75 hours.  During the stay, the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package
    (ALSEP) was placed and activated, and 110.5 kg of rock and soil samples
    were collected.  The duration of the lunar orbit was 147.6 hours for a
    total of 75 orbits.
 
 
  Surface Operations
  ==================
    Cernan and Schmitt made three moonwalk extra-vehicular activities
    (EVAs).  The LRV was used to explore regions within 7.5 km of the LM
    landing site. The first moonwalk EVA started on 11 December at 23:54:49
    UT and ended on 12 December at 07:06:42 UT, during which time the LRV
    was unloaded, deployed, and driven.  Photographs of the lunar surface
    were taken and geologic samples were collected from the LM site and
    during all three geological traverses.  The ALSEP was deployed 185
    meters West-Northwest of the LM landing site.  The traverse on the
    first EVA covered 3.3 km, out to Steno and Emory craters and back.
    The surface electrical properties experiment was set up during this
    traverse and a seismic explosives charge deployed.
 
    The second EVA started on 12 December at 23:28:06 UT and ended on 13
    December at 07:05:02 UT.  The LRV was driven out to Nansen crater and
    back by way of Lincoln scarp, Shorty crater, and Camelot crater.  It
    covered 20.3 km and included deployment of several seismic explosives
    packages. The tape recorder from the surface electrical properties
    experiment, the cosmic ray experiment, and the lunar neutron probe were
    retrieved at the end of this EVA.  The third EVA ran from 13 December
    22:25:48 UT until 14 December 05:40:56 UT.  This traverse went out to
    the North massif and Sculptured Hills, and returned via Cochise,
    Shakespeare, Van Serg, and Sherlock craters.  The traverse covered a
    distance of 12.1 km.  The LM lifted off the Moon on 14 December at
    22:54:37 UT after 75 hours on the lunar surface.
 
 
  Surface Experiments
  ===================
    The Apollo 17 astronauts performed and deployed many experiments on
    the lunar surface along with the geologic studies, sample return,
    and surface photography.
 
      - The Lunar Traverse Gravimeter Experiment was designed to make a
        high-accuracy survey of the gravitational field in the Apollo 17
        landing area;
 
      - The Soil Mechanics Experiment studied the physical properties of
        the lunar regolith using observations recorded by video and audio;
 
      - The Surface Electrical Properties Experiment obtained data about
        the electromagnetic energy transmission, absorption, and reflection
        characteristics of the lunar surface and subsurface.
 
      - The Lunar Surface Cosmic Ray Experiment was a set of detectors hung
        from the LM, designed to measure solar wind particles, low energy
        cosmic rays, and radon;
 
      - The Neutron Probe was designed to measure the rates of low-energy
        neutron capture as a function of depth in the lunar regolith.
 
    Other experiments were part of the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments
    Package (ALSEP) which was emplaced at the landing site by the
    astronauts.  The instruments, connected by cables to a central station
    which controlled power and communications, ran autonomously.  Data
    collected was converted to a telemetry format and transmitted to Earth.
    Many of these experiments returned data until September 1977, when the
    ALSEP network was turned off due to budgetary constraints.
 
    The Apollo 17 ALSEP instruments consisted of:
 
      - A Lunar Ejecta and Meteorites Experiment, designed to measure the
        frequency with which the Moon was impacted by primary cosmic dust
        particles and lunar ejecta;
 
      - A Lunar Atmospheric Composition Experiment, designed to study the
        composition and variations in the tenuous lunar atmosphere;
 
      - A Lunar Surface Gravimeter, designed to obtain highly accurate
        measurements of the lunar gravity and its temporal variations at a
        selected point on the surface;
 
      - A Heat Flow Experiment, designed to measure the rate of heat loss
        from the lunar interior and the thermal properties of lunar
        material;
 
      - A Lunar Seismic Profiling Experiment, designed to acquire data on
        the physical properties of the lunar near-surface materials and to
        monitor natural seismic activity.
 
 
  Orbital Science Experiments
  ===========================
    Investigations were also carried out from lunar orbit in the Apollo 17
    Command and Service Module.  Hand-held photography was performed from
    the command module, and a suite of instruments operated from the
    Scientific Instrument Module (SIM) in the Service Module, comprising:
 
      - Metric and Panoramic cameras to take photographs of the lunar
        surface from orbit;
 
      - A Laser Altimeter using reflected laser pulses to profile the
        topography of lunar surface;
 
      - A Far Ultraviolet Spectrometer provided UV observations of the
        lunar surface, lunar atmosphere, zodiacal light, solar atmosphere,
        Earth, and galactic and stellar sources;
 
      - An Infrared Scanning Radiometer designed to measure the thermal
        emission from the lunar surface in order to obtain a surface
        temperature map;
 
      - A Lunar Sounder Experiment, a synthetic aperture radar, mapped
        the topography and subsurface electrical conductivity structure
        and measured galactic electromagnetic radiation in the lunar
        environment;
 
      - An S-Band Transponder Experiment designed to carefully track
        the CSM orbit and measure the lunar gravity field.
 
    Additional experiments were also performed in lunar orbit and during the
    cruise between Earth and Moon:
 
      - The Mapping Camera Aspect Stellar Photography Experiment took
        stellar photographs simultaneously with the metric photography to
        provide more accurate spacecraft position reference data;
 
      - The Biological Cosmic Ray Experiment (BIOCORE) consisted of a
        group of pocket mice with implanted cosmic ray detectors to
        determine the biological effects of cosmic rays;
 
      - The Biostack Experiment was designed to study the effects of
        cosmic radiation on various biological specimens;
 
      - The Window Meteoroid experiment studied micrometeoroid impacts
        on the Apollo 17 Command Module heat shield windows to obtain
        information about the mass flux of micro-meteorites.
 
      - The Heat Flow and Convection experiment was an engineering test
        performed on board the Apollo 17 Command Module to measure and
        observe the behaviour of fluid flowing in the absense of gravity.
 
    For more information about the experiments, see the &apos;Apollo 17
    Preliminary Science Report&apos; by Johnson Space Center, (1973)
    [APOLLO17A1973].
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
