<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1B00.xsd">
    
    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:other_investigation.wt_threshold</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Planetary Boundary Layer Wind Tunnel Particle Threshold</title>
        <information_model_version>1.11.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2018-05-16</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                Wind tunnel data and documentation for particle threshold for planetary boundary layer analog studies. Initial creation in 
                conjunction with the Devon Burr PDART 2014 project regarding restoration and archiving of the Planetary Aeolian Laboratory 
                historical data for Mars-, Venus-, Titan-, and Earth-analog environments. 
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>
    
    <Reference_List>
        <External_Reference>
            <doi>j.aeolia.2015.07.008</doi>
            <reference_text>
                The Titan Wind Tunnel: A new tool for investigating extraterrestrial aeolian environments, Aeolian Research, 18
                205-214, 2015.
            </reference_text>
        </External_Reference>
    </Reference_List>

    <Investigation>
        <name>wt_threshold</name>
        <type>Other Investigation</type>
        <start_date>2018-05-16</start_date>
        <stop_date nilReason="unknown" xsi:nil="true"></stop_date>
        <description>
        Initially started as part of the PDART 2014 efforts of Devon Burr, this investigation is designed to acculumate 
        planetary boundary layer wind tunnel data for planetary analogs of Mars, Venus, Titan, and Earth (and potentially 
        others) for the purpose of investigating particle entrainment threshold wind speed data. Particle entrainment threshold 
        denotes the wind speed at which a particle of a given size and density will begin to move in the airflow. Historically 
        Ronald Greeley and James D. Iversen setup a series of wind tunnels to run in various planetary analog environments to 
        investigate basic parameters for planetary aeolian processes spanning 1970s-2010s. This work is carried on by numerous
        former students and colleagues expanding what is known about sand and dust movement by wind processes on multiple planetary
        bodies.
        </description>
    </Investigation>
</Product_Context>
