<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <Product_Context xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"
 xmlns:pds="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1D00.xsd">

    <Identification_Area>
        <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:other_investigation.geodesy</logical_identifier>
        <version_id>1.0</version_id>
        <title>Geodesy</title>
        <information_model_version>1.13.0.0</information_model_version>
        <product_class>Product_Context</product_class>
        <Modification_History>
            <Modification_Detail>
                <modification_date>2020-05-03</modification_date>
                <version_id>1.0</version_id>
                <description>
                    Context product for geodesy -- the science of accurately measuring and understanding 
                    the Earth's geometric shape, orientation in space, and gravity field.
                </description>
            </Modification_Detail>
        </Modification_History>
    </Identification_Area>

    <Reference_List>

        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geodesy
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                A brief overview of geodesy and its principal sub-disciplines.
                Updated at irregular intervals.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
            <reference_text>
                Hofmann-Wellenhof, B, and Helmut Moritz, Physical Geodesy, 
                Springer-Verlag Wien, ISBN 978-3-211-33544-4, 2006.
            </reference_text>
            <description>
                An updated edition of the 1967 original by W.A. Heiskanen and H. Moritz.
                The 2006 version incorporates a global integration of geometry and gravity,
                making extensive use of GPS methods.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
        <External_Reference>
           <reference_text>
               Altamimi, Zuheir, Xavier Collilieux, and Laurent Métivier, 
               ITRF 2008: An Improved Solution of the International Terrestrial Reference Frame, 
               Journal of Geodesy, 85, 457-473, 2011.
               doi 10.1007/s00190-011-0444-4
           </reference_text>
           <description>
                A description of the 2008 revised solution for the International Terrestrial 
                Reference Frame. ITRF2008 is based on reprocessed solutions of the four space 
                geodetic techniques: VLBI, SLR, GPS and DORIS, spanning 29, 26, 12.5 and 16 
                years of observations, respectively. The input data were time series (weekly 
                from satellite techniques and 24-h sessions from VLBI) of station positions 
                and daily Earth Orientation Parameters (EOPs). Considering the level of scale 
                consistency between VLBI and SLR, the ITRF2008 scale accuracy is evaluated to
                be at the level of 1.2 ppb (8 mm at the equator) over the common time-span of 
                the observations of both techniques. Although the performance of the ITRF2008
                is demonstrated to be higher than ITRF2005, future ITRF improvement resides in
                improving the consistency between local ties in co-location sites and space 
                geodesy estimates.
            </description>
        </External_Reference>
        
    </Reference_List>
     
     <Investigation>
         <name>Geodesy</name>
         <type>Other Investigation</type>
         <start_date>-0580-01-01</start_date>
         <stop_date>2099-12-31</stop_date>
         <description>
             Geodesy is the science of accurately measuring and understanding the
             Earth's geometric shape, orientation in space, and gravity field.
             Pythagoras (580-490 BC) is credited with postulating that the Earth
             was spherical, and Eratosthenes (276-194 BC) estimated Earth's 
             circumference at 25000 miles. Today the Earth's shape is known to
             result from the competition of gravity, rotation, tides, plate
             tectonics, volcanism, fluid motion (ocean and atmosphere), and other
             forces. Rotation and gravity are themselves also variable.  All factors
             are measured repeatedly and modeled for both historical correlation and
             prediction.
         </description>
     </Investigation>
     
 </Product_Context>
